<stage n="4" title="Implementation — emit a phased TDD goal DAG and hand to autonomous execution" autonomous="true">
  <objective>Convert the approved feature spec (Stage 3) + the Stage 3b Test Plan into a PHASED GOAL DAG and hand it to the autonomous taskvisor daemon — the daemon's per-goal dispatch is what runs /tmux:plan then /tmux:supervisor, so EMITTING goals IS the delegation. For each BE-logic acceptance unit, emit a tests-first goal (validate asserts the new tests fail MEANINGFULLY — an assertion failure, not a collection/compile error) BEFORE its implementation goal (`depends_on` the tests-first goal; validate asserts those same tests green + the resolved static gates). Red&#8594;green is an ORDINARY dependency chain — the daemon already runs `depends_on` prerequisites first, so TDD ordering falls out of existing DAG semantics with NO new daemon mechanics. Every emitted goal's validate renders the FULL Stage-0-resolved quality-gate commands (static-analysis + lint/style + tests, e.g. ecs / cs check for the lint/style gate) carried forward VERBATIM — never re-narrowed to a fixed static/unit/deptrac/e2e subset — PLUS the conditional manifest/schema validators (mono-schema / db-validate) and the Stage-1 code-rule gate (each matched machine-kind rule's validate_cmd; each MUST review-kind rule as a convention-audit review-investigator), all RESOLVED from the Stage 0 TOPOLOGY — never a `src/` skeleton literal. This shard is the Stage 4 body the feature.xml load seam executes; it COMPOSES goal-create chains + the auto-start-taskvisor path, and never re-implements /tmux:plan or /tmux:supervisor. TESTS_MODE GOVERNS THE TEST DELIVERABLE ONLY: when TESTS_MODE=off (resolved upstream) emit NO tests-first goal — every acceptance unit (BE-logic included) becomes a SINGLE implementation goal whose validate carries the FULL Stage-0 static-analysis + lint/style gates, the conditional manifest/schema validators, AND the Stage-1 code-rule gate (ALL non-test gates still apply), PLUS a generated no-test-artifact guard; an ephemeral eval test is permitted ONLY if deleted before completion (no test file persists, hard-gated). TESTS_MODE=required (default) keeps the tests-first &#8594; impl TDD chain below verbatim. Dropping tests NEVER drops a non-test gate.</objective>

  <substep n="4.1" title="Consume upstream context blocks — never re-probe">
    <action>Read the upstream emitted context blocks VERBATIM — do NOT re-probe the filesystem, re-run `tmux-cli rules resolve`, or re-open the architecture decision. Every fact this stage needs was resolved upstream:</action>
    <action>From the Stage 0 capability block: SIGNALS (lang, framework, run_target, has_database, has_frontend, frontend_mode, n_auth_flows), E2E_RUNNER_AVAILABLE, and TOPOLOGY — the RESOLVED source roots, test roots, layer names, root namespace, and the resolved quality-gate commands. Carry the resolved quality-gate command list forward VERBATIM and IN FULL — static-analysis + lint/style + tests, exactly as Stage 0 emitted them (the lint/style gate, e.g. ecs / cs check, is part of the set — NOT re-narrowed to a static/unit/deptrac/e2e subset). These supply EVERY validate command and path rendered below — never a literal.</action>
    <action>From the Stage 1 context dossier: the existing-system surfaces the feature touches (affected modules, call sites, data shapes). These scope each goal's footprint.</action>
    <action>From the Stage 1 context dossier, also consume the APPLICABLE RULES (the code-rule gate input): for EACH matched rule the dossier emitted from `tmux-cli rules match`, take its id, paths, severity, validate_kind, and validate_cmd VERBATIM. Stage 1 (substep 1.2) already ran the match and Go decided WHICH rules apply — Stage 4 CONSUMES these fields by name and NEVER re-runs `rules match`. validate_kind (machine|review) decides routing in 4.3a: machine-kind carries a non-empty validate_cmd (append it to the goal's validate); review-kind's validate_cmd is empty (route MUST review-kind to a convention-audit review-investigator). An empty APPLICABLE RULES set (`{"rules":[]}`) is informational — compose from the Stage-0 gates only, never crash.</action>
    <action>From the Stage 2 approved ADR: the user-confirmed approach and its boundaries — the authoritative design anchor; goals implement it, never re-decide it.</action>
    <action>From the Stage 2 approved-decision block: TESTS_MODE (`required` | `off`), carried through Stage 3. It governs ONLY the test deliverable + the test gate (the 4.3 emission branch + 4.3a part 1b). Every NON-test gate in 4.3a (static-analysis, lint/style, the conditional manifest/schema validators, and the Stage-1 code-rule gate) applies to every emitted goal REGARDLESS of TESTS_MODE.</action>
    <action>From the Stage 3 spec's FINAL APPROVED NAMING MANIFEST (the user-confirmed `| Role | Name | Mirrors | Target path |` table): the concrete per-artifact names + target paths. Every emitted goal's description, acceptance, and footprint references the manifest's APPROVED names + paths VERBATIM — NEVER re-derive, rename, or "improve" a confirmed name; the implementation creates exactly the named artifacts at the named paths.</action>
    <action>From the Stage 3 feature spec + Stage 3b Test Plan: the acceptance units and the ONE Test Plan row per unit ({Acceptance unit, Class, Layer, Driver, Test path}). The Test Plan is the goal-DAG's source of truth — one classified row becomes one (or, for BE-logic, a tests-first&#8594;impl pair of) goal(s).</action>
    <check condition="the Stage 3b Test Plan is absent OR empty (zero acceptance units)">
      <action>Do NOT fabricate goals. Print a named, actionable reason: "Stage 4: no acceptance units in the Test Plan — nothing to emit. Re-run Stage 3/3b to populate the Test Plan." and STOP gracefully (never crash, never invent a goal).</action>
    </check>
  </substep>

  <substep n="4.2" title="Classify acceptance units &amp; assign phases (reuse PHASE_ORDER)">
    <action>For each Test Plan row, read its already-assigned Class (BE-logic / infra / FE / full-stack — Stage 3b classified it; do NOT re-classify, just consume).</action>
    <action>Assign each unit a phase token and REUSE task-plan-generate.xml's PHASE_ORDER ranks verbatim (task-plan-generate.xml step 4.2, ~line 220): gate=0, scaffold=1, domain=2, application=3, infrastructure=4, fixtures=5, error_handling=6, auth=7, action=8, event_listener=9, cross-cutting (middleware/api_docs/messenger/health_check/docker/cicd/dx)=10, final_gate=11. Map a unit's Class to its phase: BE-logic domain/application logic &#8594; domain or application; infra/persistence &#8594; infrastructure; full-stack HTTP action &#8594; action; FE/browser surface &#8594; the relevant cross-cutting or action phase per the ADR. When a unit fits two phases pick the lower rank (earlier).</action>
    <action>Order the units by PHASE_ORDER rank (ascending); break ties by Test Plan row order. This ordered list is the emission sequence — each goal is chained `depends_on` its predecessor so the daemon executes in rank order.</action>
    <rule critical="true">Phase ranks and ordering reuse task-plan-generate.xml's logic — do NOT invent a new phase model and do NOT renumber the ranks. Equal rank is allowed for same-phase and cross-cutting units (interchangeable among themselves).</rule>
  </substep>

  <substep n="4.3" title="Emit the tests-first &#8594; impl goal DAG via goal-create depends_on chains">
    <action>Walk the ordered unit list from 4.2. Maintain PREV_GOAL_ID, initialized empty (the first emitted goal has no predecessor unless an upstream gate goal exists). For each unit, emit goal(s) via the goal-create MCP tool, capturing each returned goal id and passing it as the next goal's `depends_on` — the task-list.xml chain-commit pattern (task-list.xml:122-127). Use goal-create(`depends_on`=[predecessor id]) for routine chaining; NEVER goal-add-prerequisite (that is the escalation backstop and increments escalation_count).</action>
    <action>BRANCH ON TESTS_MODE FIRST: when TESTS_MODE=off, use the single SOLE off-branch below for EVERY unit (any Class) — skip the two TESTS_MODE=required branches entirely. When TESTS_MODE=required (default), use the two branches below per the unit's Class.</action>
    <branch condition="TESTS_MODE=required AND unit Class == BE-logic (pure domain/application logic, TDD per Stage 3b)">
      <action>Emit the tests-first goal A FIRST:
        - description: "tests-first: &lt;unit&gt; — failing &lt;layer&gt; test(s)" (&#8804;120 chars).
        - acceptance: the new test(s) for this unit EXIST at the Test Plan row's resolved test path AND fail with a MEANINGFUL assertion failure (a test that actually ran and asserted), NOT a collection/compile/import error.
        - validate: the RESOLVED unit-test command from TOPOLOGY, CHANGE-SCOPED to the row's resolved Test path — render the runner targeting ONLY the row's test path/classes in the resolved runner's scoping idiom (a positional path for path-addressable runners, `--filter &lt;ClassName&gt;` for class-granular runners, or a suite/type selector + filter such as `--testsuite` / `--component=&lt;c&gt; --type=&lt;suite&gt; --filter=&lt;FootprintToken&gt;` for suite-partitioned runners — resolved from TOPOLOGY, never assume a positional path; one invocation per touched suite), NEVER the component-wide command, so an unrelated PRE-EXISTING failure in another module of the same component cannot red the goal. Emit the red check as a BARE, sh-valid command on which `sh -n` passes — render it as `sh {{generated red-phase gate path}}` referencing a small GENERATED red-phase gate, OR, when the resolved runner exposes a runner flag / exit-code that distinguishes an assertion failure from a collection/compile/import error, that single bare flagged command directly. The "a collection error does NOT count as red" logic lives in the generated red-phase gate, NEVER in the validate string. Stage 4 GENERATES the red-phase gate alongside the goal: it runs the resolved unit-test command (already change-scoped above) and greps the runner's resolved assertion-failure banner PLUS a non-zero failure count, exiting 0 ONLY on a meaningful assertion failure (a test that ran and asserted) and non-zero on a collection/compile/import error or an all-green run. Describe BOTH forms — generated gate is primary/most portable, runner flag/exit-code the alternative for runners that cleanly separate the cases — resolved data-driven from the Stage-0 TOPOLOGY, never a `src/` literal. be-checks parity: test paths OUTSIDE the row's scope are pre-existing debt — reported, NOT gated; only a meaningful assertion failure in the row's OWN test path counts as red. Render the resolved runner + filter — never a `src/` skeleton literal.
        - phase: the unit's 4.2 phase; depends_on: [PREV_GOAL_ID] if set; lane: omit (full).
        Capture goal A's returned id; set PREV_GOAL_ID = A. After capturing this goal's id, pre-seed its spec cache per substep 4.3b (write execute-1-&lt;slug&gt;.md + task-&lt;slug&gt;.md + a `planning` tasks.yaml under .tmux-cli/goals/&lt;A-id&gt;/research/).</action>
      <action>Then emit the implementation goal B:
        - description: "impl: &lt;unit&gt; — make tests-first goal green" (&#8804;120 chars).
        - acceptance: the SAME tests from goal A now PASS (green) AND the FULL Stage-0-resolved quality-gate commands pass (static-analysis + lint/style + tests, carried forward verbatim — incl the lint/style gate, e.g. ecs / cs check), PLUS the matched machine-kind code-rule checks, PLUS the MUST review-rule convention-audit.
        - validate: compose from substep 4.3a's GATE_SET — the same unit-test command now asserting PASS, plus the FULL Stage-0-resolved quality-gate command list VERBATIM (static-analysis + lint/style + tests, incl the lint/style gate e.g. ecs / cs check), plus the conditional mono-schema / db-validate validators, plus each matched machine-kind rule's validate_cmd; route each MUST review-kind rule to a convention-audit review-investigator (NOT a bare validate). All RESOLVED — never `src/` skeleton literals.
        - phase: the unit's 4.2 phase; depends_on: [A's goal id] (so the daemon dispatches B only after A is done — red-before, green-after as an ordinary dependency chain, no new daemon state); lane: omit.
        Capture goal B's returned id; set PREV_GOAL_ID = B. After capturing this goal's id, pre-seed its spec cache per substep 4.3b (write execute-1-&lt;slug&gt;.md + task-&lt;slug&gt;.md + a `planning` tasks.yaml under .tmux-cli/goals/&lt;B-id&gt;/research/).</action>
      <action>If only the tests-first goal is emittable this pass (impl deferred), still chain it correctly via depends_on and record the deferral — never drop the impl half silently.</action>
    </branch>
    <branch condition="TESTS_MODE=required AND unit Class != BE-logic (infra / FE / full-stack — no TDD red/green pair required)">
      <action>Emit a SINGLE implementation goal in the unit's 4.2 phase:
        - description / acceptance: implement the unit per the Test Plan row + ADR.
        - validate: compose from substep 4.3a's GATE_SET — the RESOLVED command(s) for the row's Layer/Driver (integration with a real dependency when has_database resolves true; e2e via the resolved {{e2e_runner}} when has_frontend &amp;&amp; e2e_runner_available; HTTP-level fallback otherwise) PLUS the FULL Stage-0-resolved quality-gate command list VERBATIM (static-analysis + lint/style + tests, incl the lint/style gate e.g. ecs / cs check) PLUS the conditional mono-schema / db-validate validators PLUS each matched machine-kind code-rule's validate_cmd (and each MUST review-kind rule as a convention-audit review-investigator) — same composition as the BE impl goal, all from TOPOLOGY, never a literal.
        - phase: the unit's 4.2 phase; depends_on: [PREV_GOAL_ID] if set; lane: omit.
        Capture the returned id; set PREV_GOAL_ID = it. After capturing this goal's id, pre-seed its spec cache per substep 4.3b (write execute-1-&lt;slug&gt;.md + task-&lt;slug&gt;.md + a `planning` tasks.yaml under .tmux-cli/goals/&lt;id&gt;/research/).</action>
    </branch>
    <branch condition="TESTS_MODE=off (any unit Class — tests are NOT a deliverable this run)">
      <action>Emit a SINGLE implementation goal per unit — NO tests-first goal, NO red/green pair (BE-logic included; the eval-only Test Plan row supplies the coverage classification, not a test deliverable):
        - description: "impl: &lt;unit&gt; — &lt;DDD role per ADR&gt;" (&#8804;120 chars).
        - acceptance: implement the unit per the Test Plan row's eval-only classification + the ADR; the off-mode GATE_SET (4.3a) passes — i.e. the FULL Stage-0 static-analysis + lint/style gates, the conditional manifest/schema validators, AND the Stage-1 code-rule gate ALL pass; AND no test artifact persists in the goal footprint. The worker MAY author an ephemeral test to verify behavior but MUST delete it before completion — no test file may remain.
        - validate: compose from substep 4.3a's off-mode GATE_SET — the FULL Stage-0-resolved static-analysis + lint/style gate list VERBATIM (NO test gate), PLUS the conditional mono-schema / db-validate validators, PLUS each matched machine-kind code-rule's validate_cmd (route each MUST review-kind rule to a convention-audit review-investigator), PLUS the generated no-test-artifact guard (`sh {{generated no-test-artifact guard path}}`). All RESOLVED from TOPOLOGY — never a `src/` skeleton literal.
        - phase: the unit's 4.2 phase; depends_on: [PREV_GOAL_ID] if set; lane: omit.
        Capture the returned id; set PREV_GOAL_ID = it. After capturing this goal's id, pre-seed its spec cache per substep 4.3b (write execute-1-&lt;slug&gt;.md + task-&lt;slug&gt;.md + a `planning` tasks.yaml under .tmux-cli/goals/&lt;id&gt;/research/).</action>
      <action>Stage 4 GENERATES the no-test-artifact guard alongside each off-mode goal: a small bare, sh-valid script that lists NEW/added test files in the goal footprint (the resolved test roots + any test-path patterns under the changed source roots — RESOLVED from the Stage 0 TOPOLOGY, never a literal) and exits NON-ZERO if ANY persists, exit 0 ONLY when none remain. Render it as `sh {{generated no-test-artifact guard path}}` — bare, `sh -n`-valid, never prose; the daemon compiles each validate entry verbatim under sh. This is the HARD enforcement of "eval tests, then deleted": an eval test left behind reds the goal. It is scoped to NEW files in the footprint, so a pre-existing test elsewhere never false-positives.</action>
      <action critical="true">BASELINE-VERIFY the generated guard BEFORE wiring it into the goal validate (mirrors the catalogue's "baseline-run every grep rule at plan time" discipline — `sh -n` proves SYNTAX, not BEHAVIOR): (1) run it against the CURRENT footprint — with no eval test present it MUST exit 0 (green); (2) prove it FIRES on the violation it claims to detect — drop a throwaway footprint-shaped `*Test` file UNDER THE RESEARCH-ROOT (never project source) or match its resolved pattern against a constructed footprint test path, and confirm it exits NON-ZERO (red), then remove the throwaway. A guard that does NOT discriminate — green on both, red on both, or one that matches ALL tests at the path instead of only NEW/footprint ones (the exact "scoped to NEW files" bug) — is VACUOUS: FIX or regenerate it and re-verify; NEVER emit an unverified guard into a goal validate. This baseline-run is read-only / scratch-only and does NOT escape the flow (it edits no project source).</action>
    </branch>
    <action>After every emission, the chain is acyclic by construction (each goal depends only on an ALREADY-created predecessor — goal-create rejects a depends_on pointing at a non-existent goal). If a depends_on would ever point forward or form a cycle, ABORT with a named reason rather than emitting it (mirrors task-plan-generate.xml's G-15 acyclicity guard).</action>
    <rule critical="true">EVERY emitted goal's validate ALWAYS renders the Stage-0-resolved static-analysis + lint/style quality-gate commands (e.g. ecs / cs check for the lint/style gate) carried forward VERBATIM — never re-narrowed to a subset — PLUS the conditional manifest/schema validators (mono-schema / db-validate) PLUS the Stage-1 code-rule gate (matched machine-kind validate_cmd; MUST review-kind as a convention-audit review-investigator), all RESOLVED from the Stage 0 TOPOLOGY (real test/source roots, real layer names) — NEVER a `src/` skeleton literal, project name, port, or hardcoded stack token. The resolved TEST gate is ADDED to this floor when TESTS_MODE=required; when TESTS_MODE=off it is replaced by the generated no-test-artifact guard — but NO non-test gate is EVER dropped (dropping tests never drops a rule gate).</rule>
    <rule critical="true">Red&#8594;green is an ORDINARY depends_on chain (TESTS_MODE=required only). Do NOT add a "red phase" enum, statemachine state, or any daemon change — the tests-first goal's validate asserts meaningful red; the impl goal `depends_on` it and its validate asserts green. The daemon runs prerequisites first; that IS the TDD ordering. When TESTS_MODE=off there is no red/green pair — each unit is a single impl goal (no tests-first goal).</rule>
    <rule critical="true">MEANINGFUL-RED IS A BARE, RUNNABLE COMMAND — NEVER PROSE-IN-VALIDATE: every validate entry the shard emits is a bare, runnable command — a `sh {{generated red-phase gate}}` reference or a single resolved runner flag / exit-code command — never prose, parentheses, or conditional/explanatory text. The "a collection/compile error is not red" intent lives ONLY in the generated red-phase gate script (run the change-scoped tests, grep the runner's resolved assertion-failure banner + a non-zero failure count, exit 0 on meaningful red), never in the validate string; the LLM validator runs each validate entry as written, so a stray parenthesis or quote makes the check unrunnable.</rule>
    <rule critical="true">VERIFY EVERY GENERATED GATE BEFORE EMITTING IT (no vacuous gate): any gate THIS stage generates — the no-test-artifact guard (TESTS_MODE=off) or the red-phase gate (BE-logic) — is LOAD-BEARING, so `sh -n` (syntax) is NOT sufficient. BASELINE-RUN it to confirm it actually DISCRIMINATES — it goes RED on the violation it claims to detect AND GREEN when clean — BEFORE wiring it into a goal validate and dispatching. A generated gate that cannot go red on its own violation (or that reds unconditionally) is vacuous and must be fixed/regenerated and re-verified, never dispatched. The baseline-run is read-only / scratch-only (no project-source edit — it does NOT escape the flow); it mirrors the catalogue's "baseline-run every grep rule at plan time" and the daemon's `sh -n` pre-check at the BEHAVIORAL level.</rule>
  </substep>

  <substep n="4.3a" title="Compose each goal's gate set (data-driven) — Stage-0 quality-gates + conditional validators + Stage-1 code-rule gate">
    <action>This substep DEFINES the GATE_SET that the 4.3 impl branches reference when rendering each emitted goal's validate. Compose it data-driven from the upstream blocks consumed in 4.1 — never re-resolve gates, never re-run `tmux-cli rules match`. GATE_SET assembles, in order:</action>
    <action>1a. The Stage-0 resolved STATIC-ANALYSIS + LINT/STYLE gates — ALWAYS included, in BOTH test modes, carried forward VERBATIM and IN FULL — including the lint/style gate (e.g. the resolved `ecs` / `cs check`). NEVER drop the lint/style gate and NEVER re-narrow the static+lint set to a subset; the full resolved static+lint list is the FLOOR for every emitted goal's validate regardless of TESTS_MODE. These gates stay component/project-wide and VERBATIM (deterministic over the changed files).</action>
    <action>1b. The TEST gate (unit / integration / e2e command) — included ONLY when TESTS_MODE=required. When required, append the resolved test command CHANGE-SCOPED to the row's resolved Test path (ORTHOGONAL TARGET-SCOPING per task 197 — scopes WHAT the test gate runs, never WHICH gates run) in the RESOLVED RUNNER's scoping idiom (resolved from TOPOLOGY — a positional path for path-addressable runners, `--filter &lt;ClassName&gt;` for class-granular runners, or a suite/type selector + filter such as `--testsuite` / `--group` / `--component=&lt;c&gt; --type=&lt;suite&gt; --filter=&lt;FootprintToken&gt;` for suite-partitioned runners; NEVER assume a positional path works for every runner), emitting ONE invocation PER test suite/type the row's footprint touches with a footprint selector (`--filter`/equivalent) MANDATORY on any suite carrying pre-existing out-of-footprint reds, so the test gate reds only on a regression in the changed module's own path. be-checks parity: test paths OUTSIDE the row's scope are pre-existing debt — reported, NOT gated; a regression in the row's own test path reds the goal. When TESTS_MODE=off, OMIT the test gate entirely and instead append the generated no-test-artifact guard (4.3 off-branch, `sh {{generated no-test-artifact guard path}}`). Only the TEST gate's PRESENCE is conditioned on TESTS_MODE; gate-SET membership of the static/lint (1a), schema (2), and code-rule (3) gates is untouched in both modes.</action>
    <action>2. CONDITIONAL manifest/schema validators, appended only when the goal's footprint warrants: the resolved `mono-schema` validator when a manifest/schema file is in the goal footprint; the resolved `db-validate` when a DB schema/migration artifact is in the goal footprint. Artifact absent → omit that conditional validator (never fabricate it).</action>
    <action>3. The Stage-1 code-rule gate, sourced from the APPLICABLE RULES consumed in 4.1 (the `tmux-cli rules match` output fields, referenced BY NAME — id, paths, severity, validate_kind, validate_cmd — never re-matched here). For EACH matched rule with `validate_kind == machine`, append its `validate_cmd` (non-empty for machine-kind) to the goal's `validate` list. For EACH matched rule with `severity == must` AND `validate_kind == review` (its `validate_cmd` is empty), do NOT add a bare validate — instead add a `convention-audit` review-investigator (carrying the rule id + the footprint paths + a pass/fail verdict) to the emitted goal's `goal-create` investigation_config. A `should`-severity review rule is advisory, not a hard gate. An empty APPLICABLE RULES set (`{"rules":[]}`) contributes no code-rule gate — compose from the Stage-0 gates (+ conditional validators) alone.</action>
    <rule critical="true">`validate_kind` (machine|review) — NOT `severity` — decides routing: machine-kind → append validate_cmd to `validate`; review-kind → convention-audit review-investigator. `goal-create`'s investigation_config accepts 2–4 entries and the `convention-audit` type; the review-investigator slots in ALONGSIDE the auto-derived investigators — do NOT exceed 4 total. Stage 4 CONSUMES the match output; it never re-runs `rules match` (Stage 1 owns the match, Go owns WHICH rules apply).</rule>
    <rule critical="true">MANDATORY FUNCTIONAL REVIEW (RC-1): every behavior-bearing goal ALWAYS carries a reasoning `code-review` (functional acceptance) investigator — `goal-create` / WriteGoalMD auto-adds one whenever the goal's config would otherwise be ALL static analysis, so the validator can never roll up a pass on static checks alone. This is INDEPENDENT of TESTS_MODE: under TESTS_MODE=off the functional review is the ONLY behavioral gate, so the goal's acceptance MUST state the observable behavior explicitly — above all any AUTHORIZATION / DENY-PATH / DATA-ISOLATION criterion — for that review to have something concrete to check. Do not rely on static-analysis + lint + schema + code-rule gates to prove the feature WORKS; they prove only that it is clean and conformant.</rule>
    <rule critical="true">GATE_SET is RESOLVED-only: every command is carried forward from the Stage 0 TOPOLOGY verbatim — never a `src/` skeleton literal, project name, port, or hardcoded stack token. The portability mandate applies to the conditional validators and code-rule validate_cmds exactly as to the base quality gates.</rule>
  </substep>

  <substep n="4.3b" title="Pre-seed the plan step-3c spec cache per emitted goal (research artifact, NOT project source)">
    <objective>After each goal-create in 4.3, pre-seed the EMITTED goal's FLAT research dir with the plan-format spec fragment (plus a matching task context file and a `planning` tasks.yaml) so the daemon-dispatched downstream /tmux:plan enters INCREMENTAL mode (plan.xml step 0c), PRESERVES the pre-seeded task, and step 3c cache-HITS the fragment (its spec-validate + S5/S6/S9 gate still runs) — skipping the SELF_SPEC re-derivation round. This is a prompt-template composition only; it consumes ONLY already-resolved upstream context (the Stage-3 feature spec, the unit's Stage-3b Test Plan row, the Stage-3 APPROVED NAMING MANIFEST, and the 4.3a composed GATE_SET) and NEVER re-probes the filesystem, re-runs `tmux-cli rules match`, or re-resolves any gate.</objective>
    <action critical="true">RESEARCH ARTIFACT, NOT PROJECT SOURCE: every file written in this substep lives under `.tmux-cli/goals/&lt;id&gt;/research/` — the daemon/planner control plane, NOT the project's source tree. Writing these planning artifacts is NOT an "engine" action and does NOT violate the COMPOSER / NEVER-WRITE-PROJECT-SOURCE rule in &lt;execution-rules&gt; below: no project source file is created, scaffolded, or edited here. If you reach for a project-source path in this substep you have escaped scope — STOP and emit a goal instead.</action>
    <action>Run this for EACH emitted goal id captured in 4.3 — BOTH the tests-first goal A AND the impl goal B in the TESTS_MODE=required BE-logic branch, and the single impl goal in the non-BE and TESTS_MODE=off branches (one spec fragment PER emitted goal). Let `G` be the emitted goal id. Compute `SLUG` = a deterministic kebab-case slugify of the unit name — the SAME string passed as `G`'s `goal-create` description: lowercase it, replace every run of non-`[a-z0-9]` with a single `-`, trim leading/trailing `-`, and truncate to ≤40 chars. Reuse this ONE `SLUG` across all three files so plan.xml step 3c's `task-&lt;slug&gt;.md` → `execute-*-&lt;slug&gt;.md` slug match is deterministic (Design Notes: writing only `execute-1-&lt;slug&gt;.md` into a FRESH-mode planner's path would cache-MISS whenever the planner invents a different slug — the `planning` tasks.yaml + `task-&lt;slug&gt;.md` are what flip it to INCREMENTAL and pin the slug).</action>
    <action>`mkdir -p .tmux-cli/goals/G/research/` FIRST — the emitted goal's research dir may not exist at goal-create time. Target the FLAT `.tmux-cli/goals/G/research/` (plan.xml step 0b research-root), NEVER `research/cycle-N/` (that Go-created dir is for the daemon/investigate and is never scanned by the planner's step 3c spec-cache).</action>
    <action>Write THREE files under `.tmux-cli/goals/G/research/`, all keyed on the ONE `SLUG`:
      1. `execute-1-&lt;SLUG&gt;.md` — the FULL spec fragment in plan.xml's `&lt;spec-deliverable-template&gt;` format, containing EVERY mandatory section (## Intent, ## Boundaries &amp; Constraints, ## Dependencies, ## Code Map, ## Implementation Plan, ## Test Plan, ## Acceptance Criteria, and — only when `G` carries `must` code rules — ## Code Rules) so plan step 3c's spec-validate + S5/S6/S9 gate returns valid. Assemble it from the Stage-3 feature spec (this unit's slice → ## Intent / ## Implementation Plan), the unit's Stage-3b Test Plan row (→ ## Test Plan cases, each bullet LEADING with a bare `TestXxx`/`TC-N` token so spec-validate's S3 counts it), the APPROVED NAMING MANIFEST names + target paths VERBATIM (→ ## Code Map / ## Implementation Plan — never re-derive or rename a confirmed artifact), and the 4.3a composed GATE_SET (→ ## Verification). A COMPLETE fragment is MANDATORY: a stub cache-MISSES on spec-validate/S5/S6/S9 and re-fires SELF_SPEC — the exact waste being fixed.
      2. `task-&lt;SLUG&gt;.md` — the research-task context in plan.xml's `&lt;research-task-template&gt;` shape; its filename is what anchors the slug plan step 3c derives (strip `task-`/`.md`).
      3. `tasks.yaml` — `status: planning`, `cycle: 1`, and exactly one task `{name: "&lt;unit name&gt;", wid: "execute-1", status: pending, context: ".tmux-cli/goals/G/research/task-&lt;SLUG&gt;.md"}`; mirror `lane: solo` when `G` was created with lane solo. `status: planning` is the lever that flips the downstream planner into INCREMENTAL mode (plan step 0c) so it PRESERVES the pre-seeded task rather than re-deriving its own slug.</action>
    <action>The GATE_SET rendered into the fragment's ## Verification is carried forward VERBATIM and RESOLVED from the Stage-0 TOPOLOGY (the SAME resolved commands 4.3 wrote into `G`'s `goal-create` validate) — NEVER re-narrowed, NEVER dropped, and NEVER a `src/` skeleton literal.</action>
    <action>Best-effort and NON-FATAL: `mkdir -p` then write. If any single write fails, log the path + reason and CONTINUE the emission — the pre-seed is an optimization, and on any slug divergence, stale spec, or gate-fail the downstream planner safely cache-MISSES that task and falls back to SELF_SPEC (current behavior, no correctness loss). The forced blind audit on the downstream goal is UNAFFECTED — the pre-seed skips SELF_SPEC's re-derivation, not the audit.</action>
    <rule critical="true">4.3b is MANDATORY for every emitted goal in every 4.3 branch (BE pair → both A and B; non-BE and TESTS_MODE=off → the single impl goal) and runs AFTER each goal-create but BEFORE the 4.4 daemon hand-off. It is PURELY ADDITIVE: it NEVER alters the 4.3 goal-create/`depends_on` chaining or the 4.4 auto-start-taskvisor hand-off.</rule>
  </substep>

  <substep n="4.4" title="Hand off to autonomous execution (reuse auto-start-taskvisor)">
    <action>REUSE task-list.xml's auto-start-taskvisor substeps (task-list.xml:136-168) — do NOT re-implement them:
      1. Assess daemon state: PID_ALIVE (.tmux-cli/taskvisor.pid exists AND `kill -0 $(cat .tmux-cli/taskvisor.pid)` succeeds) and ACTIVE (.tmux-cli/taskvisor-active exists). If both hold, the emitted goals schedule on the next tick — skip to the reconcile reminder.
      2. If NOT PID_ALIVE, run `tmux-cli taskvisor restart`; on a no-session/no-window error print the named actionable reason ("Cannot auto-start: &lt;error&gt;. Start a session with tmux-cli start, then run: tmux-cli taskvisor restart — the queued goals will execute on activation.") and stop in a degraded-but-named state (goals stay queued, never silently idle).
      3. Call the taskvisor-start MCP tool (it validates pending goals exist and writes .tmux-cli/taskvisor-start), then poll for .tmux-cli/taskvisor-active every 3s up to 30s. On activation print "taskvisor ACTIVE — executing &lt;goal ids&gt;."; on timeout print the last ~10 lines of .tmux-cli/logs/taskvisor.log and the named reason.</action>
    <action>The daemon's per-goal dispatch runs /tmux:plan then /tmux:supervisor for each goal in the chain (delegation BY REFERENCE — this shard supplies the "what" = the DAG; the existing machinery supplies the "how"). The run ENDS with the daemon executing the chain, exactly as the /tmux:task-list consume contract requires (task-list.xml:179): "always ends with the daemon executing (or a named, actionable reason why not)" — queued-but-idle is a failure of this stage.</action>
    <check condition="zero goals were creatable (every unit was non-emittable)">
      <action>Do NOT silently finish. Print a named, actionable reason (which units were skipped and why) and STOP — never report success with an empty DAG.</action>
    </check>
    <action>Emit a one-line handoff to Stage 5: the emitted goal ids + the resolved validation commands, so stage-5-validation.xml can delegate verification to /tmux:investigate. Proceed to Stage 5.</action>
  </substep>

  <execution-rules>
    <rule>COMPOSER, NOT ENGINE: emit goals via goal-create chains and let the taskvisor daemon run /tmux:plan + /tmux:supervisor per goal — NEVER re-implement their planning, dispatch, or supervision logic here (feature.xml:24).</rule>
    <rule critical="true">NEVER WRITE PROJECT SOURCE IN THIS STAGE: Stage 4's outputs are GOAL DEFINITIONS (via goal-create) and the daemon hand-off — nothing else. Do NOT Write/Edit a single project source file, do NOT "scaffold" or "quickly implement" any artifact, even a trivial one — every file the feature needs is CREATED INSIDE a daemon-dispatched goal by /tmux:execute. Emitting the goal DAG IS the implementation; if you find yourself reaching for Write/Edit on a project file, you have escaped the flow — STOP and emit a goal instead. A Stage-4 run that edited project source, or that ended without goals emitted + the daemon executing, is a FAILED run.</rule>
    <rule critical="true">SPEC-CACHE PRE-SEED IS MANDATORY AND IS NOT PROJECT SOURCE (substep 4.3b): after EACH goal-create, pre-seed the emitted goal's FLAT `.tmux-cli/goals/&lt;id&gt;/research/` dir with `execute-1-&lt;slug&gt;.md` + `task-&lt;slug&gt;.md` + a `planning` tasks.yaml so the downstream /tmux:plan enters INCREMENTAL mode and step 3c cache-hits the pre-seeded spec (spec-validate + S5/S6/S9 still applies), skipping SELF_SPEC. These files live in the daemon/planner CONTROL PLANE, NOT the project source tree — writing them does NOT violate the NEVER-WRITE-PROJECT-SOURCE rule above and is NOT an engine action. The pre-seed is best-effort/non-fatal and PURELY ADDITIVE: it never alters the 4.3 goal-create/`depends_on` chaining or the 4.4 auto-start-taskvisor hand-off, and on any divergence the planner safely falls back to SELF_SPEC.</rule>
    <rule>PORTABILITY: every validate command, test path, and layer name is RESOLVED from the Stage 0 TOPOLOGY — never a `src/` skeleton literal, project name, port, or hardcoded stack token (feature.xml:25).</rule>
    <rule critical="true">VALIDATES STAY BARE, ENV PRE-RESOLVED: emit every validate / Investigation-Config command BARE, host-style per CMD-CONV — the daemon wraps PHP/Node toolchain commands into their container using the Stage-0-resolved EXEC ENVIRONMENT (RUN_TARGET + services from docs/architecture/test-environment.md); host/file commands (grep, sh, find) stay bare. Do NOT hand-prefix `docker compose exec`. This is SAFE ONLY because Stage 0 (0.3a) GUARANTEED the env is resolved — it hard-stops a containerized repo whose test-environment.md is missing/local, so if you reached Stage 4 the env is provided to every goal. NEVER emit goals into a containerized repo with an unresolved env: bare composer/vendor-bin would exit-127 on the host and red-fail every goal.</rule>
    <rule>TDD AS A PLAIN DEPENDENCY CHAIN (TESTS_MODE=required): a BE-logic unit yields a tests-first goal (validate asserts MEANINGFUL red) then an impl goal that `depends_on` it (validate asserts green + resolved static gates). No new daemon mechanics — the existing depends_on semantics ARE the red&#8594;green ordering.</rule>
    <rule>TESTS_MODE=off: NO tests-first goal — every unit is a single impl goal whose validate carries the static-analysis + lint/style gates, the conditional manifest/schema validators, AND the Stage-1 code-rule gate (every non-test gate still applies), PLUS a generated no-test-artifact guard. An ephemeral eval test is permitted ONLY if deleted before completion — the guard reds the goal if any new test file persists. Dropping tests NEVER drops a non-test gate.</rule>
    <rule>PHASE ORDERING reuses task-plan-generate.xml's PHASE_ORDER ranks; chaining uses goal-create(depends_on=[predecessor id]) as task-list.xml's chain-commit does — never goal-add-prerequisite for routine chaining.</rule>
    <rule>AUTONOMOUS STAGE: resolve every decidable fork to the highest-quality in-scope option and record the rationale; never block on the user (feature.xml is interactive ONLY at Stage 2).</rule>
    <rule>ENDS EXECUTING: the run finishes with the daemon executing the chain, or prints a named, actionable reason why not (the /tmux:task-list consume contract) — queued-but-idle or a silent empty DAG is a failure of this stage.</rule>
    <error-reporting>On a genuine harness/infra/spec defect (an MCP tool or `tmux-cli` command that errored after its own retries, a contradictory/under-specified goal spec, or a validator-error-class condition), follow the shared `error-reporting` procedure in `tmux/task-report.xml` — compose + submit autonomously, honoring api.enabled / DEDUP / RECURSION-guard. NEVER on expected work failures (red validate cycle, supervisor pushback, NEED_INPUT, unwritten-code test red) or daemon-owned goal-failures.</error-reporting>
  </execution-rules>

  <llm critical="true">
    <critical-rules>
      • COMPOSER, not engine — emit a goal DAG via goal-create chains; the daemon runs /tmux:plan + /tmux:supervisor per goal. Emitting goals IS the delegation; never re-implement them.
      • PRE-SEED THE SPEC CACHE (substep 4.3b, MANDATORY) — after each goal-create, write execute-1-&lt;slug&gt;.md + task-&lt;slug&gt;.md + a `planning` tasks.yaml into the emitted goal's FLAT .tmux-cli/goals/&lt;id&gt;/research/ dir so the downstream /tmux:plan hits step 3c's spec cache (spec-validate + S5/S6/S9 still runs) and skips SELF_SPEC. These are research/control-plane artifacts, NOT project source — they do NOT violate NEVER-WRITE-PROJECT-SOURCE; best-effort, purely additive, safe SELF_SPEC fallback on any divergence.
      • TDD is an ORDINARY depends_on chain (TESTS_MODE=required) — a tests-first goal (validate asserts MEANINGFUL red, an assertion failure not a collection/compile error) BEFORE its impl goal (depends_on it; validate asserts green + resolved static gates). NO new daemon mechanics, no red-phase enum.
      • TESTS_MODE=off — no tests-first goal; each unit is a single impl goal; validate keeps static-analysis + lint/style + schema validators + the Stage-1 code-rule gate (ALL non-test gates) PLUS a generated no-test-artifact guard; eval tests permitted ONLY if deleted. Dropping tests never drops a rule gate.
      • VERIFY EVERY GENERATED GATE before dispatch — the no-test-artifact guard and the red-phase gate are load-bearing; `sh -n` proves syntax, not behavior. Baseline-run each to confirm it goes RED on its own violation AND GREEN when clean; a vacuous guard (can't go red, or matches all tests not just NEW ones) is fixed/regenerated, never emitted. Read-only/scratch-only — does not escape the flow.
      • PORTABILITY IS MANDATORY — every validate renders the FULL Stage-0-resolved quality-gate commands (static-analysis + lint/style + tests, e.g. ecs / cs check for the lint/style gate) carried forward VERBATIM — never re-narrowed to a fixed static/unit/deptrac/e2e subset — PLUS the conditional manifest/schema validators and the Stage-1 code-rule gate, all RESOLVED from Stage 0 TOPOLOGY; never a `src/` skeleton literal, project name, or hardcoded stack token.
      • PHASE ordering reuses task-plan-generate.xml's PHASE_ORDER ranks; chaining uses goal-create(depends_on=[predecessor id]) like task-list.xml chain-commit — never goal-add-prerequisite for routine chaining; abort on a cycle (G-15).
      • USE THE APPROVED NAMING MANIFEST VERBATIM — every goal's description/acceptance/footprint references the user-confirmed concrete names + target paths from the Stage-3 manifest; never re-derive or rename a confirmed artifact.
      • HAND OFF to the autonomous daemon via the auto-start-taskvisor path (taskvisor-start MCP tool, poll .tmux-cli/taskvisor-active); the run ENDS with the daemon executing the chain or a named, actionable reason why not — never queued-but-idle, never a silent empty DAG.
      • AUTONOMOUS stage — resolve every decidable fork to the highest-quality in-scope option and record the rationale; never block on the user.
    </critical-rules>
  </llm>
</stage>
