<stage n="0" title="Capability + topology resolution" autonomous="true">
  <objective>Resolve everything the later stages need to stay portable: (a) preflight the invocation, (b) detect capability SIGNALS, (c) resolve the project TOPOLOGY and quality gates from the rules catalogue, and (d) emit a single resolved context block the downstream stages consume. ZERO project-shaped value is hardcoded — every one is resolved from `tmux-cli rules resolve` / `--signals` / manifests, or (in interactive context) ASKed; greenfield skeleton values are DEFAULTS only.</objective>

  <substep n="0.1" title="Preflight">
    <action>Tokenize $ARGUMENTS into the feature description. Trim whitespace.</action>
    <check condition="$ARGUMENTS is empty or whitespace-only">
      <action>Print exactly: "Usage: /tmux:feature &lt;feature description&gt; — describe the ONE feature to drive end-to-end."</action>
      <action>STOP.</action>
    </check>
    <action>Confirm the tmux-cli MCP precondition by calling a read-only MCP tool (e.g. windows-list).</action>
    <check condition="tmux-cli MCP not available">
      <action>Print exactly: "ERROR: tmux-cli MCP required but not available — enable it and retry."</action>
      <action>STOP.</action>
    </check>
    <action>Read .tmux-cli/setting.yaml from the project root (model the read on task-list.xml step 0). Record whether the file is present; capture any settings the later stages reference (it is NOT required to exist — record "absent" and proceed if missing).</action>
  </substep>

  <substep n="0.2" title="Capability signal resolution">
    <action>Run via Bash: `tmux-cli rules resolve --signals --json`. This short-circuits before the manifest load and ALWAYS exits 0 on a valid project (greenfield included, emitting unknowns). Parse the printed JSON object.</action>
    <action>Extract these SIGNALS fields verbatim from the JSON: `lang`, `framework`, `run_target`, `has_database`, `has_frontend`, `frontend_mode`, `n_auth_flows`. (The JSON also carries uses_jwt / has_mailer / has_messenger / has_http_client / n_bounded_contexts — carry them forward too if present, but the seven above are the required set.)</action>
    <check condition="the command exits non-zero">
      <action>Treat as a genuine tool defect — follow the shared error-reporting procedure (referenced from feature.xml's &lt;execution-rules&gt;), then STOP.</action>
    </check>
    <action>Identify UNKNOWN signals using the zero-value convention: empty string for `lang` / `framework` / `run_target` / `frontend_mode`; the literal "unknown" for the Tri fields `has_database` / `has_frontend`; `n_auth_flows == -1`.</action>
    <resolution-rule critical="true">For EACH unknown signal:
      • INTERACTIVE context (the stage is being run with a user present): ASK the user a single targeted question to resolve it, and record both the answer and a one-line rationale.
      • AUTONOMOUS context (no user available): apply the greenfield DEFAULT and record the default + rationale. Greenfield defaults: `lang`/`framework` = leave as detected/empty (do not invent a stack); `run_target` = "local"; `has_database` = no; `has_frontend` = no; `frontend_mode` = "none"; `n_auth_flows` = 0.
      • NEVER silently assume — every filled-in value carries a recorded rationale (ASKed vs greenfield-default).</resolution-rule>
    <action>Probe E2E_RUNNER_AVAILABLE SEPARATELY — it is NOT a Signals field. Check the project for an e2e runner config: look for a Playwright config (playwright.config.ts / playwright.config.js) or a Cypress config (cypress.config.ts / cypress.config.js / cypress.json) at the project root or under a frontend package. If found, E2E_RUNNER_AVAILABLE = true; if not found and interactive, ASK; otherwise default to false. Record the source (config path / ASKed / default).</action>
  </substep>

  <substep n="0.3" title="Topology + quality-gate resolution">
    <action>Run via Bash: `tmux-cli rules resolve --kind=convention` (append `--lang=&lt;LANG&gt; --framework=&lt;FRAMEWORK&gt;` when those signals are known, to override filesystem detection). It prints one convention rule-file path per line for THIS project's stack. Read EVERY printed file.</action>
    <action>Run via Bash: `tmux-cli rules resolve --kind=code-rules` (same `--lang`/`--framework` flags when known). It prints the project's code-rule file paths. Read EVERY printed file — these define implementation/review conventions the later stages honor.</action>
    <action>From the loaded convention packs, resolve the TOPOLOGY: SOURCE ROOTS (where production code lives), LAYER NAMES (the architectural layering the packs declare), ROOT NAMESPACE (the project's top-level namespace/module prefix), and the QUALITY-GATE COMMANDS (the static-analysis / lint / test commands the packs prescribe — emitted bare, host-style; the daemon wraps them at dispatch).</action>
    <check condition="`tmux-cli rules resolve` prints no convention files (empty catalogue / greenfield)">
      <action>Apply greenfield DEFAULTS and mark each as a default (not a detected value): SOURCE ROOTS = ["src"]; LAYER NAMES = none declared; ROOT NAMESPACE = empty; QUALITY-GATE COMMANDS = none. Record that these are skeleton defaults to be confirmed at Stage 2, NOT detected project facts.</action>
    </check>
    <rule critical="true">NEVER hardcode a source root, layer name, root namespace, quality-gate command, port, lang, or framework. Every such value is either resolved from the loaded packs/manifests above or is an explicitly-flagged greenfield default. No project name appears anywhere.</rule>
    <rule critical="true">READ EVERY RESOLVED PACK IN FULL — reading a SUBSET is a DEFECT. Count the files each `tmux-cli rules resolve` prints (convention + code-rules) and READ ALL of them; skimming two and skipping the rest silently drops the rules/conventions those files carry — the exact cause of "missed the rules dimension" failures. The emitted CODE RULES pointers MUST list EVERY printed code-rule path (never a chosen subset); Stages 1/3/4 gate on the FULL set, and the quality-gate command list must reflect every gate the packs prescribe.</rule>
  </substep>

  <substep n="0.3a" title="Strict execution-environment resolution — so every goal's validate runs where the toolchain lives">
    <action>Resolve the EXECUTION ENVIRONMENT the daemon uses to run each goal's validator/investigator commands. The daemon resolves it DETERMINISTICALLY from `docs/architecture/test-environment.md` (its ExecRuntime source: a `Run Target:` line + the published ports &#8594; the app / node container services) and threads it into EVERY goal.md, wrapping PHP/Node toolchain commands into their container when RUN_TARGET=docker (per CMD-CONV); host/file commands (grep, sh, find, curl-against-a-published-port) stay bare. Read that file and extract RUN_TARGET (docker | local), the APP service + any NODE service, and the published host ports.</action>
    <action>INDEPENDENTLY detect containerization — do NOT trust a missing/stale env file: a `docker-compose.yml` / `compose.yaml` is present, AND/OR the host LACKS the resolved toolchain (`command -v composer` / the resolved test runner / `node` returns nothing while the tool lives in a compose service). Either signal means the toolchain runs IN A CONTAINER, not on the host.</action>
    <check condition="the repo is containerized (compose present or host-tool-absent) BUT docs/architecture/test-environment.md is ABSENT, declares local, or carries no Run Target">
      <action>HARD STOP — do NOT proceed to emit goals. Print a named, actionable reason: "Containerized repo but docs/architecture/test-environment.md is missing/incomplete &#8212; the daemon will resolve RUN_TARGET=local and run each goal's validator/investigator commands VERBATIM ON THE HOST, where bare `composer` / `vendor/bin/*` exit-127, red-failing every goal before any real check runs. Create/fix docs/architecture/test-environment.md with `Run Target: docker` + the published ports (the daemon's ExecRuntime source) before emitting goals." Resolve this ONCE here &#8212; it is the exact environment defect the blind-audit otherwise catches per-goal as a SEV-1; never ship host-bare validate checks into a containerized repo.</action>
    </check>
    <rule critical="true">ENVIRONMENT IS STRICTLY PROVIDED TO EVERY GOAL: the resolved EXEC ENVIRONMENT (RUN_TARGET + container services + published ports) is emitted in the Stage-0 context block and is the env the daemon threads into EVERY emitted goal. Validates stay BARE (CMD-CONV &#8212; the daemon wraps PHP/Node toolchain commands into their container in docker mode; host/file commands stay bare) ONLY BECAUSE this stage GUARANTEED the env is resolved. NEVER emit goals when the env is unresolved in a containerized repo &#8212; that silently produces host-bare validates that exit-127 regardless of code correctness.</rule>
  </substep>

  <substep n="0.4" title="Emit resolved capability + topology context block">
    <action>Compose ONE structured context block carrying everything the later stages consume:</action>
    <emit>
      • FEATURE: the parsed $ARGUMENTS description.
      • SIGNALS: lang, framework, run_target, has_database, has_frontend, frontend_mode, n_auth_flows — each with its source (detected / ASKed / greenfield-default) and rationale for any filled-in unknown.
      • E2E_RUNNER_AVAILABLE: true/false + source (config path / ASKed / default).
      • TOPOLOGY: source roots, layer names, root namespace, quality-gate commands — each tagged detected-from-packs vs greenfield-default.
      • EXEC ENVIRONMENT: RUN_TARGET (docker | local) + the app / node container services + the published host ports, resolved (0.3a) from docs/architecture/test-environment.md and verified against containerization detection — the env the daemon threads into EVERY goal so its validate runs where the toolchain lives. (Validates stay bare per CMD-CONV; the daemon wraps toolchain commands into their container in docker mode.)
      • CODE RULES: the resolved code-rule file paths (pointers for the implementation/validation stages to read), or "none".
      • SETTINGS: relevant .tmux-cli/setting.yaml values, or "absent".
    </emit>
    <action>Hand this context block to Stage 1. Proceed to Stage 1.</action>
  </substep>
</stage>
