<stage n="1" title="Context mapping" autonomous="true">
  <objective>Map the EXISTING system's blast radius for the feature: locate the modules, layers, aggregates, handlers, controllers, and contracts it touches, and attach the resolved code-rule packs that govern those files. ALSO discover (REQUIRED) the nearest-analogue PRIOR ART — the 1–2 most behaviorally-similar already-implemented features — to model the new feature's architecture + naming on (PRIMARY: preserve that EXISTING code style even when imperfect, within the resolved gates), and locate ALL related GUIDANCE DOCS (AGENTS.md / CLAUDE.md / README / docs/architecture / ADRs / nearby `*.md`) that direct WHERE and HOW the feature should be built — then emit ONE "context dossier" block (blast radius + EXEMPLARS + GUIDANCE DOCS) for Stage 2. This shard is a COMPOSER over the investigate primitive: it spawns read-only investigator-* workers (reusing investigate.xml / investigate-worker.xml) and routes the same [EXECUTE:*] tag protocol, so verification, timeout, and read-only semantics are INHERITED, not duplicated. Research is FOOTPRINT-SIZED: under a small threshold (`&lt;=5 files AND &lt;=500 LOC` in the mapped footprint) the research runs INLINE in-window (read the footprint files + guidance docs directly, or via in-process sub-agent summaries) with the SAME required dossier sections and ZERO windows spawned; above the threshold the parallel investigator fan-out spawns exactly as today — same rationale as plan.xml step 3d ("a worker would re-load the exact context the supervisor already holds"). ZERO project-shaped value is hardcoded — every touched source root, layer, namespace, and applicable rule is resolved from Stage 0's emitted TOPOLOGY and `tmux-cli rules resolve` / `tmux-cli rules match`, never a path literal. The stage performs ZERO edits to project source; the spawned workers are strictly read-only.</objective>

  <substep n="1.1" title="Preflight + consume the Stage-0 context block">
    <action>Confirm the tmux-cli MCP precondition by calling a read-only MCP tool (windows-list).</action>
    <check condition="tmux-cli MCP not available">
      <action>Print exactly: "ERROR: tmux-cli MCP required but not available — enable it and retry."</action>
      <action>STOP. (fail closed — do not create any windows.)</action>
    </check>
    <action>Ingest Stage 0's emitted context block VERBATIM — do NOT re-probe the filesystem and do NOT re-run `tmux-cli rules resolve --signals`; every capability + topology value is already resolved upstream. Extract: FEATURE (the feature description); SIGNALS (lang, framework, run_target, has_database, has_frontend, frontend_mode, n_auth_flows); TOPOLOGY (source roots, layer names, root namespace, quality-gate commands — each tagged detected-from-packs vs greenfield-default); CODE RULES (the resolved code-rule file pointers, or "none"); SETTINGS (the relevant .tmux-cli/setting.yaml values, or "absent").</action>
    <action>Resolve this stage's research-root the SAME way plan.xml does, so worker reports land beside the goal's other artifacts: GOAL mode (a current goal is active — .tmux-cli/taskvisor-current-goal exists and is non-empty, or this stage was dispatched with a goal id) &#8594; research-root = .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/research/ (NO timestamp); STANDALONE &#8594; research-root = .tmux-cli/research/{y-m-d-hh}/ (current timestamp). Create the directory if absent. This is the ONLY directory this stage writes to — never project source.</action>
    <action>Identify STAGE_WID: the name of THIS stage's tmux window (the window /tmux:feature runs in). Pass it as the supervisorWid argument to every windows-spawn-worker call below so worker routing binds to this window.</action>
  </substep>

  <substep n="1.2" title="Derive the investigation set — blast radius + REQUIRED prior-art &amp; guidance">
    <action>From the FEATURE description + the resolved TOPOLOGY (source roots, layer names, root namespace), derive 2–4 READ-ONLY investigator definitions, each scoped to ONE touched source-root / layer footprint where the feature's existing code is likely to live (aggregates, handlers, controllers, contracts, persistence adapters). Worker count is a 2–4 RANGE, not a fixed number: scale breadth to the feature's resolved blast radius — a narrow single-layer feature warrants 2; a feature crossing domain + application + infrastructure + contract warrants 4. Record a one-line rationale for the chosen count.</action>
    <action critical="true">PRIOR ART + GUIDANCE are a REQUIRED responsibility of the investigation set (not optional). Within the SAME 2–4 budget, ensure ONE investigator owns prior-art &amp; guidance discovery: when the budget allows (blast radius needs ≤3 footprints) dedicate a standalone "prior-art &amp; guidance" investigator; when blast radius already needs 4 footprints, FOLD this responsibility into the broadest footprint investigator's scope — never exceed 4. Its charter:
      • EXEMPLAR (REQUIRED): across the resolved source roots, find the 1–2 ALREADY-IMPLEMENTED features most behaviorally similar to FEATURE (a sibling flow solving an analogous problem — e.g. the existing "confirm X" flow for a new "cancel X" feature). For each, extract the architecture SKELETON (which roles/layers it uses, by file) and its concrete NAMING pattern (class/file/method names by role), with file references. This is the template the new feature is modeled on.
      • STYLE (PRIMARY): record the exemplar's ACTUAL code style/structure/naming as authoritative to preserve EVEN WHEN IMPERFECT — every discretionary choice the resolved rule/lint gates leave open follows the exemplar, not an "ideal". Note explicitly any exemplar quirk that WOULD violate a resolved gate (that one is NOT replicated — the gate binds; "be creative + take the rules" there).
      • GUIDANCE DOCS (REQUIRED): locate ALL related markdown guidance governing WHERE/HOW to build in the touched area — AGENTS.md / CLAUDE.md / README.md, docs/architecture / ADR files, and any module-level `*.md` adjacent to the exemplar/footprint. Excerpt the build-location + convention guidance with file paths.</action>
    <action>For EACH derived footprint, attach the applicable code-rule packs by running, via Bash: `tmux-cli rules match --files &lt;footprint paths&gt; --json` (add `--phase` if the call distinguishes phases). The Go `rules match` predicate owns WHICH rules apply — never hand-glob a rule set and never re-derive Stage 0's resolved rule list. Carry the matched rule ids/paths into that investigator's scope so its dossier shard can report "rules applicable to this footprint".</action>
    <action>Resolve every touched location from the TOPOLOGY / `tmux-cli rules resolve` output — NEVER hardcode a source root, layer name, namespace, or path. If TOPOLOGY is greenfield-default (empty packs) the footprints fall back to the skeleton source roots flagged as defaults, not invented project paths.</action>
    <check condition="TOPOLOGY resolves no source roots and `rules match` returns no rules (greenfield / empty catalogue)">
      <action>Still derive at least 2 investigator definitions over the skeleton-default source roots; mark the dossier "no resolved rules / skeleton topology". Do NOT fabricate project-shaped paths.</action>
    </check>
  </substep>

  <substep n="1.2b" title="Footprint-sizing gate — inline vs spawn">
    <action>From the footprints derived in 1.2, collect the mapped candidate files (the concrete source files the feature's blast radius resolves to, across every footprint). Via Bash (non-mutating reads): count FILE_COUNT = the number of distinct candidate files, and LOC = the sum of `wc -l` over those files.</action>
    <action>Decide RESEARCH_MODE: if `FILE_COUNT &lt;= 5 AND LOC &lt;= 500` (BOTH bounds hold; inclusive `&lt;=`) &#8594; RESEARCH_MODE = inline; else RESEARCH_MODE = spawn.</action>
    <action critical="true">FAIL-SAFE: if any candidate file's LOC cannot be counted (`wc -l` errors, file unreadable/missing), treat the footprint as OVER threshold &#8594; RESEARCH_MODE = spawn. Never under-provision research by inlining a footprint you failed to measure.</action>
    <check condition="greenfield / no candidate files resolved (Stage-0 skeleton default)">
      <action>FILE_COUNT = 0 and LOC = 0, which is `&lt;= 5 AND &lt;= 500` &#8594; RESEARCH_MODE = inline; the inline branch still emits EXEMPLARS "none — net-new" + any project-level GUIDANCE DOCS. Informational, not a crash.</action>
    </check>
    <action critical="true">LOG (REQUIRED): emit exactly one line naming the chosen branch AND the driving counts, e.g. `Stage 1 research: inline branch (3 files / 130 LOC &lt;= 5 files / 500 LOC threshold)` or `Stage 1 research: spawn branch (7 files / 640 LOC > 5 files / 500 LOC threshold)`.</action>
  </substep>

  <substep n="1.3-inline" title="Inline research (RESEARCH_MODE == inline)" condition="RESEARCH_MODE == inline">
    <action>Perform ALL research in-window with NO investigator spawn: Read the mapped footprint files directly (or dispatch in-process sub-agent summaries per the existing EXPLORATION guidance) and read the guidance docs. Spawn ZERO windows; edit ZERO project source — the only writes remain the dossier under research-root.</action>
    <action>Produce the SAME dossier inputs the spawn branch collects (substeps 1.3 + 1.4 outputs), namely: the blast-radius module/layer map with each location RESOLVED from the TOPOLOGY (never hardcoded) + the `tmux-cli rules match` rule ids attached per footprint in 1.2; `EXEMPLARS / PRIOR ART` — the 1–2 nearest-analogue already-implemented features (architecture skeleton by role/file + concrete naming pattern + a STYLE note marking the existing style authoritative-even-if-imperfect, and any gate-violating quirk NOT to replicate), or "none — net-new; take the resolved conventions, best-effort" when no analogue exists; and `GUIDANCE DOCS` — ALL related AGENTS.md/CLAUDE.md/README/docs/architecture/ADR/nearby `*.md` paths + their where/how-to-build excerpts.</action>
    <action>Hand these inline research outputs to substep 1.5 exactly as the spawn branch hands its collected worker reports.</action>
    <rule critical="true">The inline branch spawns NO window and drops NO required dossier section — it is byte-for-byte the same dossier the spawn branch would produce, just gathered in-window because the footprint is small enough that a worker would only re-load the exact context this window already holds.</rule>
  </substep>

  <substep n="1.3" title="Spawn read-only investigators" condition="RESEARCH_MODE == spawn">
    <action>For EACH investigator definition, call windows-spawn-worker with: prefix: "investigator-" (reuse the investigate primitive's worker BY REFERENCE — this spawns the investigate-worker read-only agent, NOT an implement worker); supervisorWid: STAGE_WID; subtask: "Context map: &lt;footprint label&gt;"; scope: the footprint's source-root/layer + the `rules match` rule ids attached in 1.2 + an instruction to write its report to {research-root}/investigator-&lt;N&gt;-&lt;slug&gt;.md; context: FEATURE + the relevant SIGNALS/TOPOLOGY slice + the non-goal "READ-ONLY: locate existing code &amp; applicable rules, edit nothing"; deliverable: the read-only dossier shard (## VERDICT / ## FINDINGS / ## EVIDENCE) — never an implement deliverable.</action>
    <action>For the prior-art &amp; guidance investigator (or the footprint investigator the responsibility was folded into, per 1.2), its scope ALSO carries the EXEMPLAR + STYLE + GUIDANCE-DOCS charter, and its deliverable ADDITIONALLY reports: `## EXEMPLARS` (the 1–2 nearest analogous features — architecture skeleton by role/file + concrete naming pattern + a STYLE note marking the existing style as authoritative-even-if-imperfect, and any gate-violating quirk to NOT replicate) and `## GUIDANCE DOCS` (the related AGENTS.md/CLAUDE.md/README/docs/architecture/ADR/nearby `*.md` paths + their where/how-to-build excerpts). When no analogue exists, it reports `## EXEMPLARS: none — net-new surface; ground in resolved conventions (be creative + take the rules), best-effort` rather than fabricating one.</action>
    <rule critical="true">The workers are READ-ONLY: they Read files and run non-mutating Bash only. This stage itself writes NOTHING to project source — its only writes are the per-worker reports under research-root. Declare the read-only contract in every worker's scope.</rule>
    <rule>ALWAYS spawn via windows-spawn-worker with prefix: "investigator-" — never assemble the spawn manually via windows-create + windows-send, and never re-implement investigate.xml's orchestration. Record each workerName (investigator-N) for routing.</rule>
  </substep>

  <substep n="1.4" title="Idle, route, collect" condition="RESEARCH_MODE == spawn">
    <action>Do NOTHING but wait for windows-message from the investigators. NEVER use sleep — idle is the trigger. Stop-hook idle lines ("Idling …") are expected lifecycle output: do not REMIND, do not advance state, just keep waiting.</action>
    <branch tag="[EXECUTE:DONE wid=investigator-N sup=&lt;stage&gt; file=&lt;abs-path&gt;]">
      <action>Read the cited report file, extract its VERDICT/FINDINGS/EVIDENCE, record it for the dossier, then windows-kill the worker by NAME (e.g. "investigator-1") — never the @id. Continue until every spawned worker is terminal.</action>
    </branch>
    <branch tag="[EXECUTE:NEED_INPUT wid=investigator-N sup=&lt;stage&gt; &lt;reason&gt;]">
      <action>Answer the fact via windows-message to that investigator-N from FEATURE / SIGNALS / TOPOLOGY / files on disk; if unanswerable reply [SUPERVISOR:NARROW-SCOPE &lt;reduced footprint&gt;]. NEVER use windows-send and NEVER bounce a decidable technical fork to the user.</action>
    </branch>
    <branch tag="[EXECUTE:FAILED ...] or per-worker timeout (no report within the worker budget)">
      <action>Send [SUPERVISOR:KILL] via windows-message, then narrow the footprint and respawn ONCE; if it FAILs again, record a PARTIAL dossier note for that footprint and continue — degrade, never crash. windows-kill the dead worker by NAME.</action>
    </branch>
    <branch tag="worker emitted content with no [EXECUTE:...] header AND not a stop-hook idle line">
      <action>Reply ONCE via windows-message: [SUPERVISOR:REMIND] respond only with [EXECUTE:DONE file=&lt;abs-path&gt;] / [EXECUTE:NEED_INPUT] / [EXECUTE:FAILED]. Do not advance state.</action>
    </branch>
    <action>Continue routing until ALL spawned investigators have reached a terminal state (completed / failed / timeout).</action>
  </substep>

  <substep n="1.5" title="Emit the context dossier">
    <action>Synthesize the research into ONE context dossier block and hand it to Stage 2. The input source is the collected worker reports (RESEARCH_MODE == spawn) OR the inline research gathered in substep 1.3-inline (RESEARCH_MODE == inline) — the dossier requirements below are identical for both branches. The dossier lists: TOUCHED MODULES / LAYERS — the feature's blast radius, each location RESOLVED from the TOPOLOGY (never hardcoded); APPLICABLE RULES — the `rules match` rule ids/paths attached per touched footprint; and the existing aggregates/handlers/controllers/contracts each investigator located, with file references.</action>
    <action critical="true">The dossier MUST additionally carry two REQUIRED sections for Stage 2/3 to ground the delivered architecture in:
      • `EXEMPLARS / PRIOR ART` — the 1–2 nearest-analogue existing features (architecture skeleton by role/file + concrete naming pattern + file refs), and a STYLE MANDATE line: "PRIMARY — preserve the exemplar's existing code style/naming/structure even when imperfect for every discretionary choice; resolved rule/lint gates still bind; gate-violating quirks are NOT replicated." When no analogue exists, record "EXEMPLARS: none — net-new; be creative + take the resolved conventions, best-effort" (informational, never a crash).
      • `GUIDANCE DOCS` — the related markdown guidance files (AGENTS.md/CLAUDE.md/README/docs/architecture/ADR/nearby `*.md`) with paths + their where/how-to-build excerpts; "none found" if truly absent.</action>
    <check condition="the investigators found no existing code the feature touches">
      <action>Record "no existing blast radius — net-new surface" in the dossier and hand it to Stage 2 (informational, not an error). EXEMPLARS still records "none — net-new" and GUIDANCE DOCS still lists any project-level guidance (AGENTS.md/CLAUDE.md/README) that governs net-new placement.</action>
    </check>
    <check condition="`rules match` resolved no rules / TOPOLOGY was skeleton-default">
      <action>Record "no resolved rules / skeleton topology" in the dossier; still emit the module map. (greenfield path — no hardcoding.)</action>
    </check>
    <action>Hand the dossier to Stage 2. Proceed to Stage 2.</action>
  </substep>

  <execution-rules>
    <rule>READ-ONLY: this stage edits NO project source; the spawned investigators are read-only (Read + non-mutating Bash + windows-message/list only). The stage's only writes are the per-worker reports under research-root.</rule>
    <rule>COMPOSE, don't re-implement: reuse the investigate primitive BY REFERENCE — spawn investigate-worker via windows-spawn-worker with prefix: "investigator-", route [EXECUTE:*] tags via windows-message, kill via windows-kill (window NAME, never @id). Never duplicate investigate.xml's orchestration/verification/timeout logic.</rule>
    <rule>FOOTPRINT-SIZED RESEARCH (substep 1.2b): count the mapped footprint (FILE_COUNT + LOC via `wc -l`); `&lt;=5 files AND &lt;=500 LOC` (both bounds, inclusive) &#8594; INLINE research in-window (same required dossier sections, ZERO windows spawned); above the threshold &#8594; spawn the investigator fan-out exactly as today. Fail-safe to SPAWN when the footprint cannot be counted. Log the branch (inline vs spawn) AND the driving file/LOC counts. Neither branch drops a required dossier section.</rule>
    <rule>PORTABILITY: every touched source root, layer name, namespace, and applicable rule is resolved from the Stage-0 TOPOLOGY / `tmux-cli rules resolve` / `tmux-cli rules match --files … --json` — NEVER hardcoded. Greenfield skeleton values are flagged defaults only. No project name appears anywhere.</rule>
    <rule>CONSUME Stage 0, don't re-derive it: read the emitted SIGNALS/TOPOLOGY/CODE RULES block verbatim; never re-run `tmux-cli rules resolve --signals` or re-probe the filesystem for capability.</rule>
    <rule>PRIOR ART + GUIDANCE ARE REQUIRED, not optional: the investigation set MUST cover EXEMPLAR discovery (the 1–2 nearest-analogue existing features) and GUIDANCE-DOC discovery (all related AGENTS.md/CLAUDE.md/README/docs/architecture/ADR/nearby `*.md`), within the 2–4 worker budget (dedicate one investigator, or fold into the broadest footprint when blast radius needs 4). The dossier carries `EXEMPLARS / PRIOR ART` + `GUIDANCE DOCS` sections for Stage 2/3.</rule>
    <rule>STYLE PRESERVATION IS PRIMARY: record the exemplar's existing code style/naming/structure as authoritative to mirror EVEN WHEN IMPERFECT for every discretionary choice; the resolved rule/lint gates still bind (a gate-violating quirk is NOT replicated). No analogue → be creative + take the resolved conventions, best-effort (flagged net-new) — never fabricate a sibling.</rule>
    <rule>AUTONOMOUS stage: resolve every decidable fork (worker count 2–4, footprint boundaries) to the highest-quality in-scope option and record the rationale; NEVER use sleep and NEVER use AskUserQuestion — idle is the trigger, and Stage 2 is the sole interactive stage.</rule>
    <error-reporting>On a genuine harness/infra/spec defect (an MCP tool or `tmux-cli` command that errored after its own retries, a contradictory/under-specified goal spec, or a validator-error-class condition), follow the shared `error-reporting` procedure in `tmux/task-report.xml` — compose + submit autonomously, honoring api.enabled / DEDUP / RECURSION-guard. NEVER on expected work failures (red validate cycle, supervisor pushback, NEED_INPUT, unwritten-code test red) or daemon-owned goal-failures.</error-reporting>
  </execution-rules>

  <llm critical="true">
    <critical-rules>
      • READ-ONLY — the stage edits nothing; spawned investigate-worker agents are read-only; the only writes are per-worker reports under research-root.
      • COMPOSER, not engine — reuse the investigate primitive by reference (windows-spawn-worker prefix:"investigator-", windows-message, windows-kill by NAME); never re-implement investigate.xml.
      • FOOTPRINT-SIZED RESEARCH — count the mapped footprint (files + LOC); `&lt;=5 files AND &lt;=500 LOC` runs research INLINE in-window (zero windows, same required dossier sections); above threshold spawns the investigator fan-out as today. Fail-safe to spawn when uncountable. Log the branch + the file/LOC counts.
      • PORTABILITY IS MANDATORY — every touched location + applicable rule is resolved from Stage-0 TOPOLOGY / `tmux-cli rules resolve` / `tmux-cli rules match`; no hardcoded source root, layer, namespace, path, or project name.
      • CONSUME Stage 0's emitted block — never re-derive SIGNALS/TOPOLOGY or re-probe the filesystem.
      • AUTONOMOUS — resolve every fork to the highest-quality in-scope option with a recorded rationale; never sleep, never AskUserQuestion.
      • PRIOR ART + GUIDANCE REQUIRED — the investigation set MUST find the 1–2 nearest-analogue EXEMPLARS (skeleton + naming + style) and ALL related GUIDANCE DOCS (AGENTS.md/CLAUDE.md/README/docs/architecture/ADR/nearby *.md), within the 2–4 budget. No analogue → "none — net-new; take the resolved conventions, best-effort", never a fabricated sibling.
      • STYLE PRESERVATION IS PRIMARY — record the exemplar's existing code style/naming/structure to mirror even when imperfect (discretionary choices); resolved rule/lint gates still bind, gate-violating quirks not replicated.
      • Emit ONE context dossier (touched modules/layers + applicable resolved rules + EXEMPLARS / PRIOR ART + GUIDANCE DOCS) for Stage 2; net-new surface or greenfield/empty rules are informational notes, never a crash.
    </critical-rules>
  </llm>
</stage>
