    <step n="3.19a" title="Generate dev-env seed-admin goal (conditional, phase=seed)">
      <rule critical="true">Runs strictly AFTER step 3.19 so every phase=auth and phase=auth-bootstrap goal ID already exists in goals.yaml.</rule>
      <rule critical="true">CONDITIONAL — emit at most ONE goal, and only when seeding was requested AND at least one auth flow exists. NEVER fold this into the test-only fixtures goal (phase=fixtures, --env=test).</rule>
      <rule critical="true">Credentials are referenced by env-var name only (admin_identifier_env, admin_password_env) — NEVER inline a secret value in description, context, acceptance, or validate (GM-05). Seeds the dev environment ONLY — NEVER prod, NEVER --env=test.</rule>
      <rule critical="true">All inputs read from docs/architecture/* files on disk (G-16), never from conversation context.</rule>

      <substep n="3.19a.1" title="Read seed decision and gate">
        <action>Read docs/architecture/test-environment.md. Locate the `## Bootstrap / Seed Default Admin` block. Extract seed_default_admin and the env-var NAMES admin_identifier_env, admin_password_env.</action>
        <action>Read docs/architecture/cross-cutting.md auth flows (the SAME source used by step 3.19.1). Count N_auth_flows.</action>
        <branch condition="seed_default_admin != yes OR the Bootstrap / Seed Default Admin block is absent">
          <action>Print: "Seed default admin not requested — skipping Step 3.19a."</action>
          <action>SKIP — proceed to next step. Do NOT call goal-create.</action>
        </branch>
        <branch condition="seed_default_admin == yes AND N_auth_flows == 0">
          <action>Print WARNING: "Seed default admin was requested but no auth flows exist — there is no User entity to seed. Skipping Step 3.19a."</action>
          <action>SKIP — proceed to next step. Do NOT call goal-create.</action>
        </branch>
        <branch condition="seed_default_admin == yes AND N_auth_flows &gt;= 1">
          <action>Proceed to substep 3.19a.2.</action>
        </branch>
      </substep>

      <substep n="3.19a.2" title="Resolve depends_on">
        <action>Read goals.yaml from disk. Find the goal with phase=auth-bootstrap — store its ID as SEED_DEP. The auth-bootstrap goal (step 3.16a) owns the User entity + config/packages/security.yaml, so the seed must run after it.</action>
        <action>FALLBACK: if no phase=auth-bootstrap goal exists (D3 not present in this plan), resolve the first phase=auth goal (Register — owner of the User entity per step 3.19) and use its ID as SEED_DEP.</action>
        <check condition="neither a phase=auth-bootstrap goal nor any phase=auth goal resolves">
          <action>ABORT with error: "Cannot generate seed-admin goal: no auth-bootstrap or auth goal found in goals.yaml — the seed depends on the User entity owner."</action>
        </check>
        <action>Set SEED_DEPENDS_ON = [SEED_DEP].</action>
      </substep>

      <substep n="3.19a.3" title="Create the dev-env seed-admin goal via goal-create">
        <action>Resolve the seed command name: default to `app:seed-admin` (Symfony `app:` namespace). If a php-symfony overlay customizes the seed command, read it from the resolved template rather than hardcoding (mirror the fixtures-template resolution pattern at 3.17.3).</action>
        <action>Call the goal-create MCP tool with these parameters:</action>
        <params>
          <param name="description">Seed default admin in dev via bin/console app:seed-admin</param>
          <param name="acceptance">[
            "SA-01: app:seed-admin console command class exists (Symfony app: namespace command)",
            "SA-02: command reads the admin identifier and password from the named env-vars only (admin_identifier_env / admin_password_env from docs/architecture/test-environment.md) — referenced by env-var name only, never literal values",
            "SA-03: no literal secret value appears anywhere in the source — credentials are referenced by env-var name only (GM-05)",
            "SA-04: command is idempotent — a second run creates no duplicate admin and exits without error",
            "SA-05: bin/console app:seed-admin --env=dev exits 0 (NEVER --env=test)",
            "SA-06: an admin row is present in the dev database after the command runs"
          ]</param>
          <param name="validate">[
            "bin/console app:seed-admin --env=dev",
            "bin/console app:seed-admin --env=dev (second run — idempotent, exit 0, no duplicate)",
            "assert the seeded admin row exists in the dev database after the run (e.g. bin/console dbal:run-sql to count admin users --env=dev; adapt table/column to the resolved User entity) — NEVER --env=test"
          ]</param>
          <param name="context">
Seed a single default admin user into the DEV database so the running app is usable immediately after generation (the fixtures goal only seeds the --env=test database).
This goal runs `bin/console app:seed-admin --env=dev` — NEVER --env=test, NEVER prod, and is NEVER folded into the fixtures goal.
Admin credentials are read from the environment by NAME only: identifier from {{admin_identifier_env}}, password from {{admin_password_env}} (see docs/architecture/test-environment.md `## Bootstrap / Seed Default Admin`). Never hard-code credentials in source — referenced by env-var name only (GM-05).
The User entity and config/packages/security.yaml are provided by the auth-bootstrap dependency (SEED_DEP) — this goal consumes them, it does not create them.
          </param>
          <param name="investigation_config">[
            {name: "Seed command run", type: "command-run", paths: ["contexts/", "projects/"], commands: ["bin/console app:seed-admin --env=dev", "bin/console app:seed-admin --env=dev"], pass: "Command exits 0 on first AND second run (idempotent), and an admin row is present in the dev database afterward", fail: "Non-zero exit, duplicate admin row, or no admin row after the run"},
            {name: "No inlined secret", type: "file-check", paths: ["contexts/", "projects/"], commands: ["grep -rn 'app:seed-admin' contexts/ projects/ to locate the command class, then confirm it reads admin_identifier_env and admin_password_env via getenv/$_ENV and contains NO literal password/secret value"], pass: "Credentials referenced by env-var name only (admin_identifier_env / admin_password_env); no literal secret value in source", fail: "A literal credential value is hardcoded in the command or related source"}
          ]</param>
          <param name="not_in_scope">Production seeding; role/permission seeding beyond the single default admin; test fixtures (--env=test, the fixtures goal — this is NEVER folded into the fixtures goal); creating the User entity or config/packages/security.yaml (owned by the auth-bootstrap dependency).</param>
          <param name="depends_on">SEED_DEPENDS_ON = [SEED_DEP] from substep 3.19a.2</param>
          <param name="max_retries">2</param>
          <param name="phase">seed</param>
        </params>
        <rule>phase=seed on the created goal (a new phase value, distinct from fixtures).</rule>
        <rule>Description is 56 chars — within the 120-char limit (MaxGoalDescriptionLength). Detailed criteria live in acceptance and validate.</rule>
        <rule>2 investigators (GM-08 minimum): one command-run (runs --env=dev + asserts the admin row), one file-check (asserts no inlined secret). NEVER add a --env=test invocation.</rule>
        <rule>max_retries=2.</rule>
        <check condition="goal-create returns an error">
          <action>Print the error with full context and ABORT — do not leave a partial seed goal.</action>
        </check>
        <check condition="goal-create succeeds">
          <action>Print: "Seed-admin goal created: goal-{NNN} (phase=seed, depends_on=[{SEED_DEP}], max_retries=2) — runs bin/console app:seed-admin --env=dev, credentials by env-var name only."</action>
          <action>Proceed to next step.</action>
        </check>
      </substep>
    </step>
