<stage n="1" title="Violation detection" autonomous="true">
  <objective>Detect EVERY rule violation and EVERY failing quality gate on the resolved change set, then group them by CATEGORY into ONE violations dossier for Stage 2. This is the only genuinely new logic in /tmux:cr-apply-fixes: it COMPOSES `tmux-cli rules check` (the brownfield diff gate — the violation detector) for the catalogue, judges the agent_review rules with read-only convention-audit investigators (reusing the investigate primitive by reference), and runs the Stage-0 quality gates change-scoped to the footprint. ZERO project-shaped value is hardcoded — the scope, the catalogue, and the gate commands are all resolved upstream or by `tmux-cli rules check`. This stage performs ZERO edits to project source.</objective>

  <substep n="1.1" title="Preflight + consume the Stage-0 context block">
    <action>Confirm the tmux-cli MCP precondition by calling a read-only MCP tool (windows-list).</action>
    <check condition="tmux-cli MCP not available">
      <action>Print exactly: "ERROR: tmux-cli MCP required but not available — enable it and retry."</action>
      <action>STOP. (fail closed — do not create any windows.)</action>
    </check>
    <action>Ingest Stage 0's emitted context block VERBATIM — do NOT re-probe the filesystem and do NOT re-run `tmux-cli rules resolve --signals`. Extract: SCOPE (the raw $ARGUMENTS scope token); SIGNALS (lang, framework, run_target, has_database, has_frontend, frontend_mode, n_auth_flows); TOPOLOGY (source roots, layer names, root namespace, and the FULL quality-gate command list); CODE RULES (the resolved catalogue pointers, or "none"); SETTINGS (incl. cr.auto_approve / feature.auto_approve, or "absent").</action>
    <action>Resolve this stage's research-root the SAME way plan.xml does so worker reports land beside the goal's other artifacts: GOAL mode (a current goal is active — .tmux-cli/taskvisor-current-goal exists and is non-empty, or this stage was dispatched with a goal id) &#8594; research-root = .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/research/ (NO timestamp); STANDALONE &#8594; research-root = .tmux-cli/research/{y-m-d-hh}/ (current timestamp). Create the directory if absent. This is the ONLY directory this stage writes to — never project source.</action>
    <action>Identify STAGE_WID: the name of THIS stage's tmux window. Pass it as the supervisorWid argument to every windows-spawn-worker call below.</action>
  </substep>

  <substep n="1.2" title="Resolve the scope into rules-check flags">
    <action>Resolve the Stage-0 SCOPE token into `tmux-cli rules check` flags: empty &#8594; no flag (the default working tree vs HEAD); a git range (e.g. `main..HEAD`) &#8594; `--diff &lt;range&gt;`; a PR ref &#8594; resolve the PR to its merge-base range or its changed-file list via the host VCS, then pass `--diff &lt;range&gt;` (or `--files &lt;paths&gt;`); explicit paths &#8594; `--files &lt;paths&gt;`. Record the resolved flag form and a one-line rationale.</action>
    <action critical="true">INCLUDE UNTRACKED WORKING-TREE FILES — a committed-range diff (`BASE...HEAD`) MISSES untracked NEW files, so `rules check --diff &lt;range&gt;` over them evaluates an EMPTY diff and returns a FALSE "no rules apply" pass (the langflow-run footgun). Capture untracked paths via `git status --porcelain` (the `??` entries) PLUS the unstaged + staged diff, and when any exist pass the UNION as `--files &lt;paths&gt;` so the check sees the new files. NEVER trust a committed-range result when working-tree/untracked files are part of the change.</action>
    <action>Derive the CHANGED FOOTPRINT as the UNION of untracked + unstaged + staged + committed-range paths (e.g. `git status --porcelain` + `git diff --name-only`) — the full set of files the change touches, tracked or not — so substep 1.4 change-scopes the quality gates to exactly that footprint.</action>
    <check condition="the resolved scope yields zero changed files">
      <action>Emit an EMPTY violations dossier ("no changed files in scope — nothing to review") and hand it to Stage 2 ONLY after confirming there are genuinely NO working-tree changes (no untracked `??`, no unstaged/staged diff). An empty COMMITTED-range diff while untracked files EXIST is NOT clean — the untracked files ARE the change; re-scope via `--files` and proceed, never report a false pass. Do NOT crash.</action>
    </check>
  </substep>

  <substep n="1.3" title="Detect catalogue violations via `tmux-cli rules check`">
    <action>Run via Bash: `tmux-cli rules check &lt;resolved scope flags&gt; --json` (append `--phase &lt;phase&gt;` only if a phase filter is explicitly requested). Parse the printed CheckResult JSON. Go owns ALL glob/severity/signal routing — never hand-glob a rule set and never negate a signal yourself.</action>
    <action>From the CheckResult, partition the matched rules: (a) AUTOMATED-SIGNAL rules with a VIOLATED verdict — the anti-pattern FIRED on the diff (the determinate violations); (b) agent_review:true rules (signal-less / review / mixed) — Go never auto-fails these; they MUST be judged by an agent. For each agent_review rule, capture its id, category, severity, validate_kind, the source code-rule path(s), and the footprint paths it applies to.</action>
    <action>For the agent_review rules, judge compliance with READ-ONLY convention-audit investigators (reuse the investigate primitive BY REFERENCE — never re-implement it): call windows-spawn-worker with prefix: "investigator-"; supervisorWid: STAGE_WID; subtask: "convention-audit: &lt;rule id&gt;"; scope: the rule's footprint paths + the rule id + its source code-rule path + an instruction to write its verdict to {research-root}/investigator-&lt;N&gt;-&lt;rule-id&gt;.md; context: the rule text + the relevant SIGNALS/TOPOLOGY slice + the non-goal "READ-ONLY: judge whether the changed footprint VIOLATES this rule; edit nothing"; deliverable: a read-only verdict shard (## VERDICT compliant|violated / ## FINDINGS / ## EVIDENCE). Batch 2&#8211;4 rules per investigator where they share a footprint; never exceed the investigate primitive's worker budget. Idle for windows-message, route the [EXECUTE:*] tags exactly as investigate.xml does (NEVER sleep — idle is the trigger), Read each cited verdict, then windows-kill the worker by NAME. A "violated" verdict promotes that agent_review rule to a VIOLATION; "compliant" drops it.</action>
    <action critical="true">STANDALONE vs GOAL mode — make the audit path an EXPLICIT, sanctioned fork (never an improvisation). The daemon's investigate.xml ORCHESTRATOR is daemon-bound: it requires a goal.md, a daemon-created validator-{ns} window with UUID authorization, and terminates via goal-validation-done — NONE of which exist in a STANDALONE detection pass (1.1 resolved research-root to .tmux-cli/research/… with no active goal). Do NOT route the audit through that machinery in standalone mode. Two SANCTIONED read-only options — pick the highest-quality in-scope: (a) the windows-spawn-worker investigator path above, which is STANDALONE-CAPABLE — it routes the [EXECUTE:*] tags itself and NEVER calls goal-validation-done — use it when a tmux worker budget is available; (b) INLINE read-only convention audit performed by THIS orchestrator (Read + non-mutating Bash only; edits nothing — consistent with the stage's READ-ONLY mandate) when no worker budget is available. Both are read-only and emit the same `## VERDICT compliant|violated / ## FINDINGS / ## EVIDENCE`; 1.3b's guideline audit reuses whichever path is chosen. In GOAL mode the daemon-dispatched validator path is also available, as before.</action>
    <rule critical="true">COMPOSE, don't re-implement: violation detection for automated rules is `tmux-cli rules check`'s job (Go decides VIOLATED); violation detection for agent_review rules is a read-only convention-audit investigator's job (the agent decides from the JSON + footprint, the determinism boundary). NEVER negate a signal by hand and NEVER auto-fail an agent_review rule without an investigator verdict.</rule>
  </substep>

  <substep n="1.3b" title="Discover project guideline docs and audit the footprint against them">
    <action>Discover the project's MARKDOWN GUIDELINE DOCS portably (NEVER hardcode a path or project name): glob `**/*.md` under the repo, EXCLUDING vendor / node_modules / var / dist / build and any generated trees. The guideline set is the agent-instruction + written-convention docs the project ships — `AGENTS.md`, `CLAUDE.md`, `README.md`, `CONTRIBUTING.md`, and everything under a `docs/` tree (architecture / ADRs / code conventions). These are project rules even though they are NOT in the `.tmux-cli/rules/` catalogue.</action>
    <action>For EACH changed file in the footprint, resolve its APPLICABLE guidelines by NEAREST-WINS subtree precedence (the convention most repos declare — "an `AGENTS.md` in a subtree extends/overrides the parent within that subtree"): walk from the file's directory UP to the repo root, collecting every `AGENTS.md` / `CLAUDE.md` on the path (nearest = most specific), PLUS the repo-root entry doc, PLUS any `*.md` those docs explicitly link that bears on the changed path. Deduplicate; on conflict the nearest doc wins.</action>
    <action>Judge the changed footprint against its applicable guideline docs with the SAME read-only convention-audit investigators as 1.3 (reuse the investigate primitive BY REFERENCE — windows-spawn-worker prefix "investigator-"): pass the discovered guideline-doc paths + the footprint paths + the non-goal "READ-ONLY: judge whether the changed footprint BREACHES a written guideline in these docs; cite the doc path + line; edit nothing"; deliverable the same `## VERDICT compliant|violated / ## FINDINGS / ## EVIDENCE` shard. BATCH this audit with the 1.3 code-rule audit for the SAME footprint into ONE investigator where they share files — never double-spawn. A "violated" verdict is a VIOLATION in the SYNTHETIC `guidelines` category, tagged with the doc path + line it breaches.</action>
    <check condition="no guideline docs found in the project">
      <action>Record "no project guideline docs discovered" and contribute no guideline violations. (portable — never fabricate a doc.)</action>
    </check>
    <rule critical="true">PORTABILITY: guideline docs are DISCOVERED by glob + nearest-wins precedence, NEVER a hardcoded `docs/ai/PREVIO2.md` / `AGENTS.md` literal in this command — any markdown the project ships is a candidate. The catalogue (`tmux-cli rules check`) and the discovered guideline docs are COMPLEMENTARY rule sources: the catalogue is the machine-matchable rules, the docs are the project's written conventions the catalogue may not yet encode. Audit against BOTH.</rule>
  </substep>

  <substep n="1.4" title="Detect failing quality gates on the footprint">
    <action>Run EVERY Stage-0-resolved quality-gate command — the COMPLETE set (static-analysis, lint/style, tests, AND any architecture/boundary, manifest/schema, and db-schema gates the packs prescribe), never just the triad — SCOPED PER GATE KIND (scoping differs by kind — never blanket-scope every gate to the changed files):
      • TEST gate: render it in the RESOLVED RUNNER's scoping idiom (resolved from TOPOLOGY — a positional path for path-addressable runners, `--filter &lt;ClassName&gt;` for class-granular runners, or a suite/type selector + filter such as `--testsuite` / `--group` / `--component=&lt;c&gt; --type=&lt;suite&gt; --filter=&lt;FootprintToken&gt;` for suite-partitioned runners) — NEVER assume a positional path works for every runner. Emit ONE invocation PER test suite/type the footprint touches (never one selector that silently skips a touched suite); a footprint selector (`--filter`/equivalent) is MANDATORY on any suite whose full run carries pre-existing out-of-footprint reds, so the gate reds only on a real footprint regression.
      • LINT/STYLE gate: change-scope over the changed files (file-scoping is safe for formatters like ECS / eslint).
      • STATIC-ANALYSIS + architecture/boundary + manifest/schema + db-schema gates: run FULL via their resolved project-ENTRYPOINT command VERBATIM — NEVER reconstructed or file-scoped. A hand-built scoped static-analysis invocation (e.g. passing changed-file args to the raw analyzer binary) reports FALSE "ignored error pattern not matched" against the project baseline; the resolved entrypoint command is the only correct form.
      A gate that FAILS on the footprint is a VIOLATION in its OWN SYNTHETIC category named for the gate KIND (lint/style, static-analysis, tests, architecture, manifest/schema, db-schema — resolved, never hardcoded). Capture the failing command verbatim (resolved, never a `src/` literal) for Stage 2's GATE_SET.</action>
    <action>be-checks parity: failures OUTSIDE the changed footprint are pre-existing debt — reported as a note, NOT promoted to a violation; only a gate failing on the changed footprint counts.</action>
    <check condition="TOPOLOGY carried no quality-gate commands (greenfield / empty packs)">
      <action>Record "no resolved quality gates — skeleton topology"; contribute no quality-gate violations. (greenfield path — no hardcoding.)</action>
    </check>
  </substep>

  <substep n="1.5" title="Group by category + emit the violations dossier">
    <action>Group EVERY violation by CATEGORY: catalogue violations by their schema `category` field; failing quality gates by their synthetic per-gate-kind category (lint/style, static-analysis, tests, architecture, manifest/schema, db-schema); guideline-doc breaches (from 1.3b) by the synthetic `guidelines` category, recording the doc path + line per breach. For each category record: the violated rule ids / guideline citations (+ severity + validate_kind + source path per rule), the footprint paths, and any failing gate command(s). This per-category grouping is the unit Stage 2 turns into ONE goal per category.</action>
    <action>Emit ONE violations dossier block and hand it to Stage 2.</action>
    <check condition="zero violations across all categories (clean diff)">
      <action>Record "CLEAN — no catalogue violations, no failing quality gates, and no guideline-doc breaches on the changed footprint" in the dossier and hand it to Stage 2 (informational, not an error). Stage 2 will report clean and emit zero goals.</action>
    </check>
    <check condition="`tmux-cli rules check` resolved no rules / TOPOLOGY was skeleton-default">
      <action>Record "no resolved rules / skeleton topology" in the dossier; still report any failing quality-gate violations. (greenfield path — no hardcoding.)</action>
    </check>
    <action>Hand the dossier to Stage 2. Proceed to Stage 2.</action>
  </substep>

  <execution-rules>
    <rule>READ-ONLY: this stage edits NO project source; the convention-audit investigators are read-only (Read + non-mutating Bash + windows-message/list only). Its only writes are the per-investigator verdicts under research-root.</rule>
    <rule>COMPOSE, don't re-implement: detect catalogue violations with `tmux-cli rules check --json` (Go owns VIOLATED); judge agent_review rules with read-only convention-audit investigators via windows-spawn-worker (prefix "investigator-"), routing [EXECUTE:*] tags and killing by NAME — never duplicate investigate.xml's orchestration, and never negate a signal by hand.</rule>
    <rule>PORTABILITY: the scope flags, the catalogue, and the change-scoped quality-gate commands are all resolved from the Stage-0 block / `tmux-cli rules check` — NEVER a hardcoded source root, layer, namespace, runner, port, path literal, or project name.</rule>
    <rule>CONSUME Stage 0, don't re-derive it: read the emitted SCOPE/SIGNALS/TOPOLOGY/CODE RULES block verbatim; never re-run `tmux-cli rules resolve --signals` or re-probe the filesystem for capability.</rule>
    <rule>DETECTED, NOT ASSUMED: a category appears in the dossier only with a REAL violation (a fired automated signal, a judged agent_review failure, or a footprint-scoped failing gate); a clean diff yields an explicit CLEAN dossier and zero goals downstream.</rule>
    <rule>AUTONOMOUS stage: resolve every decidable fork (scope flag form, investigator batching) to the highest-quality in-scope option and record the rationale; NEVER use sleep and NEVER use AskUserQuestion — idle is the trigger, and the Stage 2 confirm gate is the sole interactive point.</rule>
    <error-reporting>On a genuine harness/infra/spec defect (an MCP tool or `tmux-cli` command that errored after its own retries, a contradictory/under-specified goal spec, or a validator-error-class condition), follow the shared `error-reporting` procedure in `tmux/task-report.xml` — compose + submit autonomously, honoring api.enabled / DEDUP / RECURSION-guard. NEVER on expected work failures (a clean diff, a NEED_INPUT, an agent_review "compliant" verdict) or daemon-owned goal-failures.</error-reporting>
  </execution-rules>

  <llm critical="true">
    <critical-rules>
      • READ-ONLY — the stage edits nothing; spawned convention-audit investigators are read-only; the only writes are per-investigator verdicts under research-root.
      • COMPOSER, not engine — detect catalogue violations with `tmux-cli rules check --json` (Go owns VIOLATED); judge agent_review rules with read-only convention-audit investigators (windows-spawn-worker prefix "investigator-", windows-message, windows-kill by NAME); never re-implement investigate.xml and never negate a signal by hand.
      • PORTABILITY IS MANDATORY — scope flags, catalogue, and change-scoped quality-gate commands are all resolved; no hardcoded source root, layer, namespace, runner, port, path literal, or project name.
      • CONSUME Stage 0's emitted block — never re-derive SIGNALS/TOPOLOGY or re-probe the filesystem.
      • DETECTED, NOT ASSUMED — a category enters the dossier only with a real violation; a clean diff emits an explicit CLEAN dossier and zero goals downstream.
      • Emit ONE violations dossier grouped by CATEGORY (catalogue `category` + synthetic per-gate categories: lint/style, static-analysis, tests, architecture, manifest/schema, db-schema + guidelines) for Stage 2 — greenfield / empty catalogue is an informational note, never a crash.
    </critical-rules>
  </llm>
</stage>
