<task id="elaborate" name="Tier-2 elaborator — just-in-time goal speccing against the live tree">
  <objective>Spec ONE roadmap-status skeleton goal against the LIVE worktree the instant its deps go satisfied. Read the goal's deliverable_area + the real tree its predecessors produced, author concrete validate / acceptance / scope / goal.md against what ACTUALLY exists (validate commands authored BARE so the daemon's wrapcmd.classify() wraps them for the container runtime), run [CODE-RULE-INJECTION] against the real deliverable paths, write the fields back via the goal-edit MCP tool, and flip the goal status roadmap → pending. This is the Tier-2 half of the two-tier director flow (docs/architecture/director-two-tier-design.md §6): concrete fields are authored at the moment of MOST information, not predicted up front.</objective>

  <input>
    <arg name="$ARGUMENTS">`&lt;dispatchPath&gt; &lt;goal-id&gt;` — the daemon's dispatchElaboration sends the per-goal dispatch.md path (`.tmux-cli/goals/goal-{ns}/dispatch.md`) followed by the goal id (`goal-{ns}`). Either token pins the goal; the dispatch path is per-goal-safe (never last-writer-wins). Resolve the goal in step 0b.</arg>
  </input>

  <output>
    <primary>The same goals.yaml goal row, rewritten via goal-edit from status: roadmap to status: pending with concrete `validate` / `acceptance` / `scope` (and a refined `deliverable_area`) authored against the real tree. The goal then flows through RunnableCandidates → implement → investigate → validate exactly as a Tier-1-born pending goal.</primary>
    <secondary>The goal's `goal.md` authored against real files (Description, Dependencies, Deliverables, Acceptance Criteria, Test Environment, Context, Not In Scope, Investigation Config, Validation Rules) — the same body the matching task-plan-generate phase shard authors, now reading real files instead of predicting them.</secondary>
    <secondary>On an unsatisfiable predecessor deliverable: a structured `unmet:` reason recorded for the director's self-healing pass (§8) — the goal is LEFT at status: roadmap, never half-specced.</secondary>
  </output>

  <requirements critical="true">
    <mcp>tmux-cli MCP server REQUIRED (for goal-edit and windows-list)</mcp>
    <known-dependency>The `goal-edit` MCP tool is built by a sibling task and referenced HERE by name only (no build coupling). It accepts `goal_id` plus the fields to write (`validate`, `acceptance`, `scope`, `deliverable_area`, `status`) — the same field names as goal-create's structured params. If goal-edit is genuinely absent at runtime, that is a harness/infra defect — follow the &lt;error-reporting&gt; procedure; never hand-edit goals.yaml as a workaround.</known-dependency>
    <foundation>Increment-1 Go foundation has landed: `GoalRoadmap` status, `Goal.DeliverableArea`, `GoalsFile.ElaborationCandidates()`. This skill is the Tier-2 worker dispatched against a goal those selectors admitted.</foundation>
  </requirements>

  <glossary>
    <term name="GOAL_ID">The roadmap goal being elaborated, e.g. "goal-014". Resolved in step 0b from $ARGUMENTS (the explicit goal-id token, or the `goal-{ns}` segment of the dispatch path). Pins every later goals.yaml / goal-edit reference in this flow.</term>
    <term name="GOAL_DIR">.tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/ — holds dispatch.md and the goal.md this skill authors.</term>
    <term name="deliverable_area">The COARSE deliverable footprint the Tier-1 roadmap generator recorded on the skeleton goal (e.g. `projects/api/src/Http/ErrorHandling/`). The seed for the live-tree read in step 3 and the basis the elaborator REFINES into precise `scope` globs in step 5.</term>
    <term name="BARE command">A validate command written with NO shell wrapper or chain (no `sh -c '…'`, no `&amp;&amp;` / pipes) so the daemon's wrapcmd.classify() can key off its first token (`bin/console`, `php`, `composer`, `npx`, …) and route it into the right container via `docker compose exec`. A pre-wrapped `sh -c '…'` classifies as a HOST command and defeats classify() — the exact goal-014 runner-missing defect (design §1, §7).</term>
    <term name="deliverable-pinning">≥1 authored `validate` that FAILS CLOSED when the goal's deliverable is absent (a presence grep / file-exists), not only a behavioral test that no-ops on an empty state. The structural fix for the 009–011 false-pass class (design §6.3, §7).</term>
    <term name="[CODE-RULE-INJECTION]">The shared code-rule → goal-field injection procedure authored ONCE in task-plan-generate.xml's &lt;rule-to-goal-injection&gt; block. This skill INVOKES it by reference against the real deliverable paths — it never re-derives the mechanic.</term>
    <term name="unmet reason">A structured `unmet: &lt;class&gt;: &lt;detail&gt;` string (e.g. `missing-deliverable: doctrine migrations`) the elaborator records when a needed predecessor deliverable is genuinely missing — the director consumes it to insert a follow-up roadmap node (§8). The elaborator NEVER inserts the node itself.</term>
  </glossary>

  <llm critical="true">
    <mandate>NEVER author a concrete field from prediction — read the REAL tree under deliverable_area first; if the file the field targets is not on disk, that is an unmet-dep escalation (step 7), not a guessed path</mandate>
    <mandate>NEVER pre-wrap a validate command in `sh -c '…'` or chain it with `&amp;&amp;`/pipes — author every toolchain validate BARE so wrapcmd.classify() wraps it for the container (the goal-014 fix). The ONLY pre-wrapped commands are the Go-rendered `validate_cmd`s you COPY VERBATIM from [CODE-RULE-INJECTION]</mandate>
    <mandate>ALWAYS include ≥1 deliverable-pinning validate that fails closed when the deliverable is absent — a goal whose validate set passes vacuously at baseline is a half-specced goal</mandate>
    <mandate>NEVER emit a half-specced goal or a doomed validate for a missing predecessor — record an `unmet:` reason and LEAVE status at roadmap (step 7)</mandate>
    <mandate>NEVER implement code, run migrations, or mutate the deliverable tree — this is a READ-MOSTLY worker; its only write is goal-edit (and goal.md). Reading the tree must not change it</mandate>
    <mandate>NEVER call goal-create / goal-add-prerequisite / goal-prune — roadmap-node insertion and DAG re-wiring are the director's job (§8). This worker writes ONLY the one goal it was dispatched for, via goal-edit</mandate>
    <mandate>Keep the spine STACK-AGNOSTIC: drive every stack specific (runtime, service names, file conventions, topology) from the resolved conventions/code-rules (the &lt;conventions&gt; block) exactly as task-plan-generate does — never hardcode php-symfony assumptions into the flow</mandate>
    <mandate>Default service access to the compose NETWORK (no host port publish); allocate a FREE host port only when one is genuinely required (design §9)</mandate>
    <mandate>Edit the EMBEDDED source only. NEVER hand-edit the regenerated .claude/commands/ copy</mandate>
  </llm>

  <decision-policy>
    <rule critical="true">Decision-resolution policy (quality-in-scope). When elaboration reaches a decision point — an "Ask First" item, a fork between a lower-effort waiver/shortcut and a higher-quality field, or a choice of validate form — autonomously choose the option that MAXIMIZES correctness (real runnable commands over asserted prose, fail-closed presence checks over vacuous behavioral ones, no waivers, no shortcuts) PROVIDED it does NOT expand the goal's scope (no new deliverables beyond deliverable_area / the goal's description). Record the chosen option + a one-line rationale in goal.md's Context. Escalate to a human ONLY for user-only knowledge no file or tree inspection can supply (credentials, business intent, out-of-band facts). A purely technical/architectural choice is NEVER user-only.</rule>
  </decision-policy>

  <conventions critical="true">
    <resolve critical="true">BINDING CONVENTIONS ARE EXTERNALIZED INTO THE RULES CATALOGUE — load them NOW, before authoring any field, exactly as task-plan-generate.xml does. Determine LANG/FRAMEWORK from the project manifest / docs/architecture/product-brief.md (never hardcode), then run via Bash: `tmux-cli rules resolve --kind=convention --lang=&lt;LANG&gt; --framework=&lt;FRAMEWORK&gt;` (omit a flag only when genuinely unknown). It prints one rule-file path per line, resolved from .tmux-cli/rules/ for THIS project's stack and capabilities (always _base; docker/database/frontend/frontend-auth packs when their signals hold; plus project-local rules under .tmux-cli/rules/local/). Read EVERY printed file. Each &lt;rule&gt; / &lt;scope-derivation&gt; / &lt;validate-acceptance-mandate&gt; element is BINDING on field authoring below — these conventions, not this skill, define the runtime form (host vs container), the service names, the stack-bring-up shape, and the emission topology. The ids CMD-CONV / HTTP-CONV / NODE-TOOL-CONV / ENSURE-STACK-CONV / HTTP-WAIT-CONV / DOCKER-RUNTIME-FRONTLOAD / E2E-* resolve to these loaded rules and govern the validate forms authored in step 4. This same resolved convention pack FEEDS the per-phase application set assembled in step 3c (reuse, do not re-resolve): step 3c layers the goal's phase criteria catalog on top of this pack, and phases with no dedicated catalog apply this pack alone.</resolve>
    <topology-binding critical="true">RESOLVED CONVENTIONS DEFINE THE EMISSION TOPOLOGY — but at elaboration the topology is VERIFIED against the real tree, not guessed: every authored deliverable path, acceptance-string path, scope glob, and investigator path MUST target the resolved topology AND exist on disk (or be the goal's own to-be-created deliverable). When the resolved set declares a DDD-monorepo topology, target it (contexts/&lt;bc&gt;/src/{Domain,Application,Bundle}, contexts/shared shared kernel, projects/&lt;app&gt;/src deployables) — but a path that the convention implies yet the tree does NOT contain is an unmet-dep escalation (step 7), never a committed guess. This is the design's "topology-binding enforced harder at elaboration" (§5): the flat-skeleton guess can no longer slip through because elaboration greps the actual tree.</topology-binding>
    <resolve-code-rules>ALSO run `tmux-cli rules resolve --kind=code-rules --lang=&lt;LANG&gt; --framework=&lt;FRAMEWORK&gt; --architecture=&lt;ARCHITECTURE&gt;` (drop --architecture when discovery recorded none). The returned files are the project's CODE RULES (severity must|should, applies_to globs; schema .tmux-cli/rules/SCHEMA.md). Do NOT inline their bodies — step 6 turns the rules whose globs match THIS goal's REAL deliverables into structured fields via [CODE-RULE-INJECTION].</resolve-code-rules>
    <code-rule-injection critical="true">The [CODE-RULE-INJECTION] mechanic is authored ONCE in task-plan-generate.xml's &lt;rule-to-goal-injection&gt; block (the shared procedure: run `tmux-cli rules match --files &lt;deliverables&gt; --phase &lt;phase&gt; --json`, then COPY pre-rendered `acceptance_line` / `validate_cmd` VERBATIM into acceptance[] / validate[], fold `review` cmds into ONE convention-audit investigator under the 2–4 cap, add the `Code rules: &lt;ids&gt; — read &lt;paths&gt;` pointer line). Step 6 INVOKES that procedure by reference against the REAL deliverable paths — do NOT restate or re-derive it here. Go owns ALL glob/severity/signal routing (internal/rules/coderules.go); copy fields, never re-render.</code-rule-injection>
    <fallback critical="true">If `tmux-cli rules resolve` fails or .tmux-cli/rules/ is missing, ABORT this elaboration with the diagnostic "rules catalogue missing — run `tmux-cli project init`, then re-dispatch" and follow the &lt;error-reporting&gt; procedure. NEVER author fields without the loaded conventions. Conservative-inclusion warnings on stderr are NOT failures — proceed with the extra packs loaded.</fallback>
  </conventions>

  <flow>
    <step n="1" title="MCP precondition">
      <action>Call windows-list.</action>
      <check condition="tmux-cli not available">
        <action>Print exactly: ERROR: tmux-cli MCP required but not available — enable it and retry.</action>
        <action>STOP. Do not author or write anything.</action>
      </check>
    </step>

    <step n="1b" title="Read project context">
      <action>Discover the APPLICABLE guideline docs for the goal's deliverable_area by NEAREST-WINS subtree precedence: from the deliverable_area directory walk UP to the repo root collecting every AGENTS.md / CLAUDE.md (nearest = most specific), plus the repo-root entry doc and any *.md they link that bears on the area. Read them ALL and internalize conventions, architecture, and constraints before authoring. If none exist on the path, proceed without project context.</action>
      <rule>This context MUST inform every authored field, the goal.md body, and the validate forms — alongside the resolved conventions from the &lt;conventions&gt; block.</rule>
    </step>

    <step n="0b" title="Resolve GOAL_ID and dispatch path">
      <action>Parse $ARGUMENTS into its two tokens: the dispatch path (`.tmux-cli/goals/goal-{ns}/dispatch.md`) and the goal id (`goal-{ns}`). Mirror plan.xml step 0b's dispatch-path binding: prefer the `goal-{ns}` segment of the DISPATCH PATH over the global .tmux-cli/taskvisor-current-goal marker (the daemon rewrites that marker on every dispatch, so under concurrency it is last-writer-wins and may name another goal; the dispatch path you were handed is per-goal-safe). Set GOAL_ID from that segment; if the explicit goal-id token disagrees with the path segment, TRUST the path segment and note the mismatch.</action>
      <check condition="no goal-{ns} can be resolved from either token">
        <action>This is a malformed dispatch (harness/spec defect) — follow the &lt;error-reporting&gt; procedure and STOP. Author nothing.</action>
      </check>
      <action>Set GOAL_DIR = .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/. Read the dispatch.md if present for any per-dispatch corrections (e.g. a prior unmet reason being re-attempted).</action>
    </step>

    <step n="2" title="Read the roadmap goal">
      <action>Read GOAL_ID's row from goals.yaml. Extract: id, description, phase, depends_on, deliverable_area, AND `validates`.</action>
      <rule critical="true">`validates` is the BRANCH DISCRIMINATOR for step 4's fork. When non-empty it names the PRIMARY implementation goal id this goal exists to validate, marking THIS goal a dedicated VALIDATION goal (Go: `Goal.Validates` ⇒ `IsValidationGoal()`, goals.go:191-202,506) — terminal-TO-ITSELF: it validates an already-Done cluster (its `depends_on` members) and `CascadeFailure` short-circuits on it so a red validation goal never blocks the implementer it validates nor any unrelated downstream impl goal (goals.go:791-800). Empty ⇒ an ordinary impl goal. Step 4 keys its heavy/light fork off this field; carry it forward.</rule>
      <check condition="goal status is not roadmap">
        <action>The goal was already elaborated (status pending/running/done) or is a legacy fully-specced pending goal — NOTHING to do. Log "goal {GOAL_ID} is status={status}, not roadmap — nothing to elaborate" and STOP. Re-elaborating a non-roadmap goal would clobber a live spec. (A daemon that dispatched a non-roadmap goal here is a wiring defect — &lt;error-reporting&gt;.)</action>
      </check>
      <check condition="deliverable_area is empty">
        <action>A roadmap goal with no deliverable_area cannot be seeded against the tree — record `unmet: missing-deliverable-area` (step 7) and STOP. Do NOT guess a footprint.</action>
      </check>
    </step>

    <step n="3" title="Read the live tree under deliverable_area">
      <action>Read the ACTUAL tree under deliverable_area and the wiring it touches, as the resolved conventions define that wiring for this stack (e.g. for a php-symfony docker stack: config/services.yaml, config/packages/doctrine.yaml, bin/ensure-test-stack.sh, routing — but drive WHICH files from the conventions, never hardcode). The worktree's predecessors are already merged in — that is the whole point of Tier-2 timing. Isolate deep reads in sub-agents (Agent tool) where available; instruct them to return DISTILLED summaries only (file paths, key symbols, service names, which deliverables already exist vs. are this goal's to create) — never load full file bodies into your own context.</action>
      <action>Establish the REAL runtime from the tree + conventions: is there a running/compose-defined app service? a db service? what are the service names? This determines the validate FORM in step 4 (container-exec vs host) — observed, not predicted.</action>
      <check condition="a predecessor deliverable this goal genuinely CONSUMES is absent from the tree">
        <action>Do NOT author a doomed validate against it — go to step 7 (escalate as a roadmap node) with a precise `unmet:` reason.</action>
      </check>
    </step>

    <step n="3c" title="Resolve the phase→criteria catalog &amp; convention pack">
      <objective>Resolve the goal's `phase` to the matching task-plan-generate criteria-catalog shard and combine its catalog with the conventions already resolved in the &lt;conventions&gt; block into ONE per-phase APPLICATION SET — the set steps 4/5/7 author from. This is the load-bearing half of the pre-rewrite all-at-once generator's per-phase fidelity, restored at dispatch: elaboration now CONSULTS the catalog of record instead of merely pointing at it. (Authored as a reusable, named sub-step: the F2 validates-branch work reuses this same resolve-then-apply machinery.)</objective>
      <rule critical="true">ADDITIVE, NEVER PREDICTIVE: the resolved catalog + convention pack is applied ON TOP OF the step-3 live-tree read — it never reintroduces up-front prediction and never collapses the real-tree authoring. The three inputs to every authored field are (1) the live tree (step 3), (2) the resolved conventions (the &lt;conventions&gt; block), and (3) this phase's criteria catalog. A catalog criterion is authored ONLY when its trigger holds in the live tree; criteria ADD coverage, they never weaken or replace a real-tree-derived field.</rule>
      <action>Map the goal's `phase` (from step 2) to its catalog shard via the &lt;phase-catalog-map&gt; table below. The catalog of record is the ALREADY-INSTALLED task-plan-generate shard set, reachable at runtime under `.claude/commands/tmux/task-plan-generate/step-3.NN-*.xml` (command templates install to `.claude/commands/tmux/` per AGENTS.md). The installed shards ARE the catalog — there is no separate spec doc and no copy to maintain.</action>
      <action>Read the mapped installed shard with a plain Read and extract its criteria catalog (the phase's PD-/AU-/EV-/EH-/SA-/FG- criteria with their triggers and acceptance/validate intent). Combine those criteria with the conventions already resolved in the &lt;conventions&gt; block into the per-phase application set carried into steps 4 (validate), 5 (acceptance/scope), and 7 (goal.md).</action>
      <action>If the goal's `phase` has NO dedicated catalog shard (any phase not in the table), DO NOT invent or guess a shard path — fall through to applying ONLY the generic resolved convention pack from the &lt;conventions&gt; block. The live-tree read (step 3) plus that generic pack are the full application set for such phases; no broken shard reference is ever authored.</action>
      <phase-catalog-map>
        | goal `phase` value            | installed catalog shard (runtime: `.claude/commands/tmux/task-plan-generate/`) | catalog id prefix |
        |-------------------------------|--------------------------------------------------------------------------------|-------------------|
        | `domain` / persistence        | `step-3.14-domain.xml`                                                         | PD-*              |
        | `auth`                        | `step-3.19-auth-flows.xml`                                                     | AU-*              |
        | `auth-bootstrap`              | `step-3.16a-auth-bootstrap.xml`                                                | AU-*              |
        | `event_listener`              | `step-3.20-event-listeners.xml`                                                | EV-*              |
        | `error_handling`              | `step-3.21-error-handling.xml`                                                 | EH-*              |
        | `seed`                        | `step-3.19a-seed-admin.xml`                                                    | SA-*              |
        | `final_gate`                  | `step-3.29-final-gates.xml`                                                    | FG-*              |
        | *(any other phase)*           | — (no dedicated shard)                                                         | apply resolved convention pack only |
      </phase-catalog-map>
    </step>

    <step n="4" title="Author validate[] against reality (BARE + deliverable-pinned)">
      <branch on="goal carries validates: (Goal.Validates non-empty ⇒ IsValidationGoal, from step 2)">
        <arm name="heavy" when="validates non-empty — THIS is a dedicated VALIDATION goal">
          <action>HEAVY arm. This goal exists to validate an ALREADY-DONE cluster, so author a CLUSTER-WIDE validate stack spanning the UNION of the real deliverables of EVERY cluster member — applying F1's resolved per-phase criteria (step 3c) across ALL members, not only this goal's own coarse `deliverable_area`.</action>
          <rule critical="true">CLUSTER ENUMERATION uses `depends_on` (the AUTHORITATIVE full cluster: step-3.30 guarantees a validation goal `depends_on` EVERY cluster impl goal), NOT `validates:` — `validates:` names only the PRIMARY_IMPL goal and would UNDER-SCOPE the gate to a single member. For each `depends_on` member, read its REAL deliverables from the LIVE tree (isolate deep reads in sub-agents returning DISTILLED summaries: paths, key symbols, which deliverables exist) — author-against-reality, never predicted. The cluster commonly spans multiple distinct `deliverable_area` paths; the heavy stack MUST cover that union.</rule>
          <rule critical="true">APPLY F1's per-phase application set (step 3c) across the cluster: for EACH cluster member, for EACH resolved phase-catalog criterion (PD-/AU-/EV-/EH-/SA-/FG-) whose TRIGGER holds in that member's live tree, author a matching validate. Heavy validates are BROADER/behavioral over the already-Done cluster, but that latitude does NOT waive the floor: they obey the SAME BARE-command, deliverable-pinning, port-occupancy, and catalog-application rules authored in the LIGHT arm below (ONE source of truth — do not restate or duplicate the BARE/runtime preamble here), MUST stay concrete + BARE + runnable, and MUST retain ≥1 fail-closed presence check PER member-area (a cluster gate that passes vacuously is the 009–011 false-pass class re-introduced at cluster scope).</rule>
          <rule critical="true">TERMINAL-TO-ITSELF / NO-CASCADE (Go ground truth goals.go:791-800, IsValidationGoal goals.go:506): the validation goal validates an implementer it `depends_on`; `CascadeFailure` short-circuits on it so a red validation goal never blocks the implementer it validates nor any unrelated downstream impl goal. The authored heavy validates MUST PRESERVE that isolation in their FORM — they run in THIS goal's own supervising cycle over an already-Done cluster; NEVER author a validate that re-couples to, mutates, or blocks the implementer (e.g. no validate that the implementer's cycle must wait on). The XML must not re-introduce coupling the Go layer deliberately severs.</rule>
          <check condition="a `depends_on` cluster member's real deliverable is absent from the live tree">
            <action>Do NOT author a doomed/vacuous validate against it — record an `unmet:` reason and LEAVE status roadmap (step 9). The director inserts the follow-up node; this worker never half-specs the cluster gate.</action>
          </check>
        </arm>
        <arm name="light" when="validates empty — an ordinary impl goal (the EXISTING step-4 body, unchanged)">
          <action>LIGHT arm. Author the goal's `validate[]` as ONLY commands runnable in THIS worktree against the runtime observed in step 3, each a BARE command (per the &lt;glossary&gt; BARE-command rule and the resolved CMD-CONV / ENSURE-STACK-CONV conventions), pinned over the goal's own `deliverable_area`:</action>
          <rule>Runtime form is observed, not guessed: when the resolved runtime is docker, emit toolchain commands BARE (`bin/console …`, `composer …`, `npx playwright …`) so wrapcmd.classify() routes them into the container via `docker compose exec`. NEVER emit a host `bin/console` when no host toolchain exists, and NEVER pre-wrap in `sh -c` — that is the goal-014 runner-missing + classifier-defeat defect.</rule>
          <rule critical="true">DELIVERABLE-PINNING (kills the 009–011 false-pass class, design §6.3): include ≥1 validate that FAILS CLOSED when the goal's deliverable is absent — a presence grep / file-exists over the REAL deliverable path (e.g. a fail-on-absent `grep -rqE '&lt;the deliverable's defining signal&gt;' &lt;real path&gt;`, a host command authored BARE), not only a behavioral test that no-ops on an empty state. At least one validate in the set MUST transition pass→fail purely by deleting the deliverable.</rule>
          <rule>Port-occupancy (design §9): default every service access to the compose NETWORK — no host port published (`docker compose exec` for toolchain, `db:5432` for DB reach). Only when a host port is genuinely required (e.g. a browser-reachable dev server for E2E) probe the host for a FREE port (respecting occupied ports via the daemon's port-alloc helper where available), write that distinct non-colliding port into the worktree compose + the goal's HTTP-wait validate, and record the claim. Ports are allocated against the LIVE host at elaboration time so a collision can never be baked into the roadmap.</rule>
          <rule>CATALOG APPLICATION (additive, from the step-3c application set): for EACH criterion in the resolved phase catalog (PD-/AU-/EV-/EH-/SA-/FG-) whose TRIGGER holds in the step-3 live tree, ALSO author a matching validate. These catalog-derived validates obey the SAME BARE-command and deliverable-pinning mandates above (no `sh -c`, no chaining; observed runtime form) — they ADD coverage on top of the live-tree-derived set, they NEVER weaken or replace it. A catalog criterion whose trigger does NOT hold in the real tree authors NO validate (no doomed/vacuous commands).</rule>
        </arm>
      </branch>
    </step>

    <step n="5" title="Author acceptance[], scope, and refine deliverable_area">
      <action>acceptance[]: objective Given/When/Then criteria derived from the goal description + the real deliverables — each independently checkable.</action>
      <action>scope: precise file/namespace globs derived from the REAL footprint discovered in step 3 (per the resolved &lt;scope-derivation&gt; convention), REFINING the coarse deliverable_area into the actual paths this goal creates/modifies. Refine deliverable_area itself if the real tree narrowed it.</action>
      <action>Fold the step-3c catalog's acceptance lines into acceptance[]: for each applicable phase-catalog criterion (PD-/AU-/EV-/EH-/SA-/FG-), restate its acceptance intent as an objective Given/When/Then criterion made CONCRETE against the goal's REAL deliverables (the actual paths/symbols from step 3), not against the shard's placeholder names. These ADD to the description-derived criteria above; they never replace the real-footprint scope derivation.</action>
    </step>

    <step n="6" title="Inject code rules [CODE-RULE-INJECTION]">
      <action>Invoke the shared [CODE-RULE-INJECTION] procedure (task-plan-generate.xml's &lt;rule-to-goal-injection&gt;, referenced via the &lt;conventions&gt; block) with `--files` = THIS goal's REAL deliverable paths (from steps 3/5) and `--phase` = the goal's phase: run `tmux-cli rules match --files &lt;real deliverables&gt; --phase &lt;phase&gt; --json`, then COPY the pre-rendered fields VERBATIM — each NON-EMPTY `acceptance_line` into acceptance[], each `automated`/`mixed` NON-EMPTY `validate_cmd` into validate[], `review` cmds folded into ONE convention-audit investigator under the 2–4 cap, and the single `Code rules: &lt;ids&gt; — read &lt;paths&gt;` pointer line into goal.md/context. Empty `rules` ⇒ inject nothing. Do NOT re-glob, re-derive severity, or re-render a command — Go owns that.</action>
      <rule>These Go-rendered `validate_cmd`s are the ONLY pre-wrapped (`sh -c '! grep …'`) commands allowed in validate[] — they are host greps that classify as host commands and are copied verbatim, distinct from the BARE toolchain-command rule in step 4.</rule>
    </step>

    <step n="7" title="Author goal.md">
      <action>Author GOAL_DIR/goal.md by APPLYING the step-3c-resolved catalog (the phase's installed shard read in step 3c, e.g. EH-* from `step-3.21-error-handling.xml`) against the REAL files — not merely "the same way the shard would author it" in the abstract, but by walking that shard's catalog and binding each applicable criterion to the actual deliverables discovered in step 3. Reuse that shard's section structure: Description, Dependencies, Deliverables, Acceptance Criteria, Test Environment reference, Context, Not In Scope, Investigation Config, and a `## Validation Rules` section listing the deterministic validate commands (the gate execute.xml step 4c runs).</action>
      <action>For a phase with no dedicated catalog shard (step-3c fall-through), author goal.md from the live tree + the generic resolved convention pack alone — same section structure, no shard reference.</action>
      <rule>Keep the two skills CONVERGENT — elaboration is "the same authoring, deferred to dispatch against real files," not a new format. The shard remains the single catalog of record; this step reads it and applies it, so a shard edit propagates to elaboration without a second source.</rule>
    </step>

    <step n="8" title="Write back via goal-edit and flip status">
      <action>Call the `goal-edit` MCP tool with goal_id={GOAL_ID} and the authored fields: `validate`, `acceptance`, `scope`, refined `deliverable_area`, and `status: pending`. This single write IS the elaboration completion: the goal now carries concrete fields and re-enters RunnableCandidates for normal implement → investigate → validate flow. (The daemon-side phaseElaborating completion detection is a SEPARATE Increment-2 task; this skill's contract is "fields written + status flipped to pending".)</action>
      <check condition="goal-edit errors after its own retries">
        <action>A genuine MCP/infra defect — follow the &lt;error-reporting&gt; procedure. Do NOT hand-edit goals.yaml. Leave the goal at roadmap; the elaboration retries per the daemon's bounded spec_retries.</action>
      </check>
    </step>

    <step n="9" title="Unsatisfiable dep → escalate as a roadmap node" condition="a needed predecessor deliverable is genuinely missing (from step 3 / step 7 triggers)">
      <rule critical="true">When a needed predecessor deliverable is genuinely missing (no migration, an absent service, a topology path the conventions imply but the tree lacks), do NOT emit a doomed validate and do NOT flip status to pending. RECORD a structured `unmet: &lt;class&gt;: &lt;detail&gt;` reason (e.g. `unmet: missing-deliverable: doctrine migrations`) where the daemon/director reads elaboration outcomes, and LEAVE the goal at status: roadmap.</rule>
      <rule critical="true">The director (§8) — NOT this worker — diagnoses the gap, authors a properly-wired follow-up roadmap node (skeleton: id, description, phase, depends_on, deliverable_area), and re-wires the DAG so depinfer/G-04/plan-audit re-run. This worker NEVER calls goal-create/goal-add-prerequisite; it only surfaces the precise, buildable `unmet:` reason so the director can insert the one missing node and continue. A vague gripe ("env broken") is useless — name the missing deliverable concretely.</rule>
    </step>

    <step n="10" title="Failure handling">
      <rule>An elaboration that cannot proceed (can't read the tree, contradictory resolved rules, goal-edit hard-fails) routes like a SPEC failure: it is retried under the daemon's bounded spec_retries, then parked blocked / owner=human. It NEVER produces a half-specced goal — on any unrecoverable condition, leave status at roadmap and record the reason (an `unmet:` for a missing prerequisite per step 9, or follow &lt;error-reporting&gt; for a harness/infra/spec defect). A goal whose validate set would pass vacuously at baseline is a half-specced goal — never write it.</rule>
    </step>
  </flow>

  <execution-rules>
    <rule>goal-edit: the SINGLE structured write-back per elaboration (validate/acceptance/scope/deliverable_area + status: pending) — referenced by name; the sibling task owns its schema</rule>
    <rule>goal-create / goal-add-prerequisite / goal-prune: NEVER — roadmap-node insertion and DAG re-wiring are the director's job (§8); this worker writes only the one dispatched goal</rule>
    <rule>The tree read is READ-ONLY — never run migrations, build artifacts, or mutate the deliverable footprint to make a validate pass; author validate against the tree as it is</rule>
    <rule>Every validate authored here is BARE (no sh -c / no chaining) EXCEPT the Go-rendered `validate_cmd`s copied verbatim from [CODE-RULE-INJECTION] — wrapcmd.classify() owns container routing</rule>
    <rule>≥1 deliverable-pinning validate per goal — non-negotiable; it is the structural false-pass fix</rule>
    <rule>Stack specifics flow from resolved conventions/code-rules, never hardcoded — the spine stays stack-agnostic like task-plan-generate</rule>
    <rule>Edit the embedded source (cmd/tmux-cli/embedded/commands/tmux/elaborate.xml) only — never the regenerated .claude/commands/ copy</rule>
    <rule>Phase→catalog resolution (step 3c) reads the ALREADY-INSTALLED task-plan-generate shards under `.claude/commands/tmux/task-plan-generate/` as the catalog of record — never a separate relocated spec doc (none exists), never a copy. The catalog application is ADDITIVE to the step-3 live-tree read; it never reintroduces prediction</rule>
    <rule>Validate authoring (step 4) FORKS on `validates:` (goals.go IsValidationGoal): a VALIDATION goal (validates non-empty) authors a HEAVY cluster gate spanning the real deliverables of EVERY `depends_on` cluster member (depends_on is the authoritative cluster, NOT validates: which names only PRIMARY_IMPL) and stays terminal-to-itself — never cascade-failing/blocking the implementer (goals.go:791-800); an ordinary impl goal (validates empty) authors the LIGHT deliverable-pinning presence validate over its own deliverable_area. NEVER an impl goal authoring a heavy cluster gate, nor a validation goal authoring only a light presence validate</rule>
    <error-reporting>On a genuine harness/infra/spec defect (an MCP tool or `tmux-cli` command that errored after its own retries, a contradictory/under-specified goal spec, or a validator-error-class condition), follow the shared `error-reporting` procedure in `tmux/task-report.xml` — compose + submit autonomously, honoring api.enabled / DEDUP / RECURSION-guard. NEVER on expected work failures (red validate cycle, supervisor pushback, NEED_INPUT, unwritten-code test red) or daemon-owned goal-failures.</error-reporting>
  </execution-rules>

  <llm final="true">
    <critical-rules>
      • Author concrete fields against the REAL tree, never from prediction — a missing path is an unmet-dep escalation (step 9), not a guess
      • Validate commands are BARE so wrapcmd.classify() wraps them — never pre-wrap toolchain commands in sh -c (the goal-014 fix); the only pre-wrapped validates are the verbatim [CODE-RULE-INJECTION] greps
      • ≥1 deliverable-pinning validate that fails closed when the deliverable is absent — kills the 009–011 false-pass class
      • Default to the compose network; allocate a free host port only when genuinely required (design §9)
      • Write back via goal-edit (status roadmap → pending) — never hand-edit goals.yaml; never call goal-create
      • Unsatisfiable predecessor → record a concrete `unmet:` reason and LEAVE status roadmap for the director to insert a follow-up node (§8) — never emit a doomed/half-specced goal
      • Keep the spine stack-agnostic — drive every stack specific from the resolved conventions/code-rules, exactly as task-plan-generate does
      • READ-MOSTLY: the only writes are goal-edit and goal.md; reading the tree must not mutate it
      • Edit the embedded source only — never the regenerated .claude/commands/ copy
    </critical-rules>
  </llm>
</task>
