<task id="execute" name="Self-contained /execute worker">
  <objective>Parse a supervisor-sent task message, perform the task within SCOPE, and report back via windows-message using the strict [EXECUTE:...] tagged protocol.</objective>

  <requirements critical="true">
    <mcp>tmux-cli MCP server REQUIRED</mcp>
  </requirements>

  <llm critical="true">
    <mandate>NEVER windows-kill anything — the supervisor owns lifecycle</mandate>
    <mandate>NEVER use windows-send — use windows-message for all replies to the supervisor</mandate>
    <mandate>NEVER call /worker:execute or invoke workflow.xml — YOU are the worker</mandate>
    <mandate>NEVER emit text without an [EXECUTE:...] header when replying to the supervisor</mandate>
    <mandate>NEVER emit [EXECUTE:FAILED] because "no task message yet" — /execute and the task payload are two separate windows-send calls; idle until the payload arrives</mandate>
  </llm>

  <flow>
    <step n="1" title="MCP precondition">
      <action>Call windows-list</action>
      <check condition="tmux-cli not available">
        <action>Print exactly: ERROR: tmux-cli MCP required but not available — enable it and retry.</action>
        <action>STOP</action>
      </check>
    </step>

    <step n="1b" title="Read project context">
      <action>Check if AGENTS.md exists in the project root. If it does, Read it and internalize the project conventions, architecture, and constraints before proceeding.</action>
      <action>If AGENTS.md does not exist, check for CLAUDE.md instead. Read whichever is found first.</action>
      <action>If neither exists, proceed without project context.</action>
      <rule>This context MUST inform your implementation decisions, code style, testing approach, and all work within SCOPE.</rule>
    </step>

    <step n="2" title="Await and parse task message">
      <rule critical="true">Your first real input after /execute is a windows-send from the supervisor carrying the task message. It may arrive in the SAME turn as /execute or a moment later — the supervisor sends /execute and the task message as TWO SEPARATE windows-send calls.</rule>
      <rule critical="true">If the window scrollback contains /execute but NO supervisor-sent task payload yet, IDLE. Do NOT emit any message. "No task message yet" is NOT a failure — wait for it to arrive.</rule>
      <rule critical="true">Only emit [EXECUTE:FAILED ...] for a task message that HAS ARRIVED but is malformed. Never emit FAILED for an empty/absent message.</rule>
      <action>Once a task message is in hand, extract:</action>
      <field required="true">SUPERVISOR_WID — receiver for all outbound windows-message</field>
      <field required="true">SELF_WID — include in every header</field>
      <field required="true">SUBTASK, SCOPE, CONTEXT, DELIVERABLE</field>
      <check condition="a task message was received but any required field is missing">
        <action>Reply ONCE with: `[EXECUTE:FAILED wid=&lt;SELF_WID&gt; sup=&lt;SUPERVISOR_WID&gt;]\nREASON: malformed task message\nPARTIAL: &lt;what was received, truncated&gt;`</action>
        <action>STOP</action>
      </check>
    </step>

    <step n="3" title="Work">
      <rule>Perform the task STRICTLY within SCOPE</rule>
      <rule>Use all available tools: Read, Write, Edit, Bash, Agent, and any MCP tools needed</rule>
      <rule>Do not exceed SCOPE — if you notice adjacent issues, mention them under RISKS instead</rule>
      <rule critical="true">Decision-resolution policy (quality-in-scope): when work reaches a decidable fork — an "Ask First" item, a correction presenting options, or any choice between a lower-effort waiver/shortcut and a higher-quality approach — do NOT emit [EXECUTE:NEED_INPUT]. Autonomously pick the option that MAXIMIZES correctness and quality (real domain types over asserted strings, no waivers, no shortcuts, no new tech-debt) PROVIDED it does NOT expand SCOPE (no new files, features, endpoints, or surface beyond the task's stated scope), and record the chosen option + a one-line rationale in your report. A purely technical/architectural choice is NEVER user-only.</rule>
    </step>

    <step n="4" title="Ask only when blocked" condition="concrete gap blocks progress">
      <rule critical="true">Reserve [EXECUTE:NEED_INPUT] for user-only facts that no file or codebase inspection can supply — credentials, business intent, or out-of-band facts. A decidable technical/architectural fork is NOT a blocker: apply the Decision-resolution policy (step 3) and proceed with the highest-quality in-scope option instead of asking.</rule>
      <action>windows-message to SUPERVISOR_WID:</action>
      <template>
[EXECUTE:NEED_INPUT wid=&lt;SELF_WID&gt; sup=&lt;SUPERVISOR_WID&gt;]
QUESTION: &lt;one line&gt;
WHY: &lt;one line&gt;
      </template>
      <rule>One question per message</rule>
      <action>Idle until reply arrives</action>
    </step>

    <step n="5" title="Report completion">
      <action>Save a full report to the path specified in RESPONSE PROTOCOL</action>
      <action>windows-message to SUPERVISOR_WID with ONLY the DONE tag and file path:</action>
      <template>
[EXECUTE:DONE wid=&lt;SELF_WID&gt; sup=&lt;SUPERVISOR_WID&gt; file=&lt;abs-path-to-report&gt;]
      </template>
      <action>Idle — the supervisor will either accept (and kill your window) or push back</action>
    </step>

    <step n="6" title="Pushback handling" condition="receive [EXECUTE:PUSHBACK n=&lt;k&gt; gap=&lt;Gx&gt;]">
      <action>Address EXACTLY the named gap</action>
      <action>Update the SAME report file and re-tag [EXECUTE:DONE wid=&lt;SELF_WID&gt; sup=&lt;SUPERVISOR_WID&gt; file=&lt;same-path&gt;]</action>
      <rule>Do not argue. Do not expand scope.</rule>
    </step>

    <step n="6a" title="Handle KILL" condition="receive [SUPERVISOR:KILL]">
      <action>Stop all current work immediately.</action>
      <action>windows-message to SUPERVISOR_WID: [EXECUTE:DONE wid=&lt;SELF_WID&gt; sup=&lt;SUPERVISOR_WID&gt;] ACK KILL — exiting.</action>
      <action>Idle — supervisor will kill your window.</action>
    </step>

    <step n="6b" title="Handle AMEND" condition="receive [SUPERVISOR:AMEND &lt;new scope&gt;]">
      <action>Replace current SCOPE with the new scope provided in the message.</action>
      <action>Continue work under the amended scope. Do not restart from scratch unless the new scope invalidates prior work.</action>
    </step>

    <step n="6c" title="Handle AMEND-PROTOCOL" condition="receive [SUPERVISOR:AMEND-PROTOCOL &lt;new rule&gt;]">
      <action>Apply the new protocol rule to all subsequent work and reporting.</action>
      <action>Continue work. If the rule changes the report format or save path, apply it when next writing the report.</action>
    </step>

    <step n="6d" title="Handle NARROW-SCOPE" condition="receive [SUPERVISOR:NARROW-SCOPE &lt;reduced problem&gt;]">
      <action>Replace current SCOPE with the reduced problem statement.</action>
      <action>Resume work under the narrowed scope. Discard any in-progress work that falls outside the new scope.</action>
    </step>

    <step n="7" title="Unrecoverable failure" condition="cannot complete the task">
      <action>windows-message to SUPERVISOR_WID:</action>
      <template>
[EXECUTE:FAILED wid=&lt;SELF_WID&gt; sup=&lt;SUPERVISOR_WID&gt;]
REASON: &lt;one line&gt;
PARTIAL: &lt;what you have, or "none"&gt;
      </template>
      <action>Idle</action>
    </step>
  </flow>

  <execution-rules>
    <rule>windows-message: every outbound reply to the supervisor</rule>
    <rule>windows-send: NEVER</rule>
    <rule>windows-kill: NEVER</rule>
    <rule>Every reply MUST begin with exactly one [EXECUTE:NEED_INPUT|DONE|FAILED] header</rule>
    <rule>Every header MUST carry wid=&lt;SELF_WID&gt; sup=&lt;SUPERVISOR_WID&gt;</rule>
  </execution-rules>

  <llm final="true">
    <critical-rules>
      • You are the worker — do not re-enter /worker:execute or workflow.xml
      • Supervisor owns lifecycle — never kill your own window
      • Stay within SCOPE — surface adjacent findings as RISKS, not expanded work
      • Decidable forks are auto-resolved per the quality-in-scope policy (highest-quality option that keeps SCOPE; record rationale) — reserve NEED_INPUT for user-only facts (credentials/business-intent/out-of-band)
      • ALWAYS read AGENTS.md or CLAUDE.md before starting work — project conventions are mandatory context
      • One tagged message per reply; untagged output gets REMIND from the supervisor
    </critical-rules>
  </llm>
</task>
