<task id="feature" name="Brownfield feature-development orchestrator">
  <objective>Drive ONE feature through an EXISTING system end-to-end — context discovery, architecture recommendation, docs + test strategy, implementation, and validation — by COMPOSING the existing plan/supervisor/investigate primitives. The brownfield analogue of the greenfield project-discovery &#8594; task-plan-generate pair. Six stages (0&#8211;5); interactive ONLY at Stage 2; fully autonomous before and after. This file is the SPINE: Stage 0 (capability + topology resolution) is loaded here; Stages 1&#8211;5 are loaded sub-step seams whose shard files SHIP with the install.</objective>

  <input>
    <note>$ARGUMENTS = the feature description / name (a free-text statement of the ONE feature to drive end-to-end). Empty $ARGUMENTS is a hard stop in Stage 0 preflight.</note>
  </input>

  <requirements critical="true">
    <mcp>tmux-cli MCP server REQUIRED (for the plan/supervisor/investigate composition the later stages delegate to).</mcp>
  </requirements>

  <glossary>
    <term name="STAGE 0">Capability + topology resolution (this file's loaded sub-step). Preflight + `tmux-cli rules resolve --signals` capability detection + `tmux-cli rules resolve --kind=convention|code-rules` topology/quality-gate resolution. Autonomous.</term>
    <term name="STAGE 1">Context mapping — locate the existing code, contracts, and seams the feature touches (F2). Autonomous.</term>
    <term name="STAGE 2">Architecture recommendation — present options and confirm the approach WITH the user (F3). The SOLE interactive stage.</term>
    <term name="STAGE 3">Docs + test strategy — record the decision and define the test approach (F4). Autonomous.</term>
    <term name="STAGE 4">Implementation — delegate to /tmux:plan + /tmux:supervisor (F5). Autonomous.</term>
    <term name="STAGE 5">Validation — delegate to /tmux:investigate (F6). Autonomous.</term>
    <term name="CAPABILITY SIGNALS">The `tmux-cli rules resolve --signals --json` fields carried forward from Stage 0: LANG, FRAMEWORK, RUN_TARGET, HAS_DATABASE, HAS_FRONTEND, FRONTEND_MODE, N_AUTH_FLOWS. E2E_RUNNER_AVAILABLE is NOT a Signals field — Stage 0 probes it separately.</term>
    <term name="TOPOLOGY">The resolved source roots, layer names, root namespace, and quality-gate commands read from the convention/code-rule packs `tmux-cli rules resolve` loads for THIS project's stack. Greenfield defaults only when the packs are empty.</term>
    <term name="TESTS_MODE">Whether tests are a DELIVERABLE for THIS feature run: `required` (default) or `off`. Resolved at Stage 2 from `.tmux-cli/setting.yaml` `feature.tests` (absent &#8594; `required`), overridable at the Stage 2 approval reply (`--no-tests` / `--tests`), and carried forward in the Stage 2 approved-decision block to Stages 3b, 4, and 5. `off` drops ONLY the test deliverable + the test gate &#8212; every NON-test gate (static-analysis, lint/style, manifest/schema validators, the Stage-1 code-rule gate) STILL applies to every emitted goal; an ephemeral eval test is permitted ONLY if deleted before completion (no test artifact persists, hard-gated).</term>
    <term name="EXEMPLAR (PRIOR ART)">The nearest-analogue ALREADY-IMPLEMENTED feature(s) &#8212; the 1&#8211;2 existing flows most behaviorally similar to the requested feature &#8212; discovered (REQUIRED) in Stage 1 and used as the TEMPLATE for the new feature's architecture skeleton + naming pattern. PRIMARY MANDATE: preserve the exemplar's EXISTING code style, naming, and structure even when imperfect, for every discretionary choice the resolved rule/lint gates leave open. A sibling quirk that would VIOLATE a resolved gate is NOT replicated (the gate still binds). When NO analogue exists: be creative, take the resolved convention/code-rule packs, best-effort &#8212; flagged "net-new / no analogue".</term>
    <term name="GUIDANCE DOCS">ALL related markdown guidance files governing WHERE and HOW the feature is built &#8212; AGENTS.md / CLAUDE.md / README.md, docs/architecture / ADRs, and any nearby module-level `*.md` next to the target code. Stage 1 locates and excerpts them (REQUIRED) and carries them in the dossier so the build LOCATION + conventions follow the documented guidance, never a guess.</term>
    <term name="EXEC ENVIRONMENT">WHERE the validator/investigator commands the daemon runs for each emitted goal execute and how their toolchain commands are wrapped &#8212; RUN_TARGET (docker | local), the app / node container services, and the published host ports. The daemon resolves it DETERMINISTICALLY from `docs/architecture/test-environment.md` (its ExecRuntime source) and threads it into EVERY goal, wrapping PHP/Node toolchain commands into their container when RUN_TARGET=docker (CMD-CONV); host/file commands (grep, sh, curl-against-a-published-port) stay bare. Stage 0 (0.3a) STRICTLY resolves + verifies it and HARD-STOPS a containerized repo whose `test-environment.md` is missing/local &#8212; never emitting host-bare validate checks that exit-127.</term>
    <term name="NAMING MANIFEST">The enumerated, CONCRETE per-artifact names proposed BEFORE development &#8212; one row per NEW artifact: {DDD role, proposed name, the EXEMPLAR counterpart it mirrors, target file path}. Derived in Stage 2 from the exemplar's observed naming pattern + the resolved naming conventions (the EXISTING code LEADS the naming; conventions are KEPT), presented at the Stage 2 approval gate so the user can CONFIRM or correct names (`approve` / `approve --rename Old=New`) before any code is written, then FROZEN into the ADR + the approved-decision block so Stages 3&#8211;4 use the approved names VERBATIM. Test-artifact rows appear only when TESTS_MODE=required.</term>
  </glossary>

  <boundary>
    <note>BOUNDARY vs neighbours — /tmux:feature is NOT a fifth full-cycle worker. It is the
      BROWNFIELD composer over the existing /tmux:plan + /tmux:supervisor + /tmux:investigate
      primitives, interactive only at Stage 2 (architecture).</note>
    <vs name="task-plan-generate">GREENFIELD goal synthesis from docs/architecture discovery
      (the project-discovery &#8594; task-plan-generate pair builds a project from scratch);
      /tmux:feature drives ONE feature through an ALREADY-EXISTING system.</vs>
    <vs name="/worker:* (MR cycles)">/worker:quick-dev, /worker:tech-spec, /worker:pipeline and the
      Redmine/GitLab MR workers operate a diff&#8594;spec&#8594;MR cycle on an external ticket; /tmux:feature
      orchestrates taskvisor goals end-to-end and never opens an MR.</vs>
    <vs name="bmad-dev-story">a single sprint-loop story implemented via red-green-refactor;
      /tmux:feature is the orchestrator that DELEGATES implementation, never the per-story implementer.</vs>
  </boundary>

  <llm critical="true">
    <mandate>COMPOSER, NOT ENGINE: /tmux:feature orchestrates the EXISTING primitives — it delegates implementation to /tmux:plan + /tmux:supervisor and validation to /tmux:investigate. NEVER re-implement their planning, dispatch, or verification logic here; reference them.</mandate>
    <mandate critical="true">ENVIRONMENT IS STRICTLY PROVIDED TO EVERY GOAL: Stage 0 (0.3a) resolves the EXEC ENVIRONMENT (RUN_TARGET + container services + published ports, from `docs/architecture/test-environment.md`) and HARD-STOPS if a containerized repo lacks it; the daemon then threads that env into every goal so each validate runs where the toolchain lives. NEVER emit goals into a containerized repo with an unresolved environment &#8212; bare `composer` / `vendor/bin/*` exit-127 on the host and red-fail every goal regardless of code correctness. Validates stay BARE (CMD-CONV; the daemon wraps) ONLY because the env is guaranteed resolved.</mandate>
    <mandate critical="true">NEVER ESCAPE THE FLOW — ORCHESTRATE, DON'T IMPLEMENT: the ONLY files /tmux:feature writes are the Stage-1 research dossiers and the per-stage persisted context blocks (Stage 0's feature-context.md, Stage 4's feature-goals.md — the HANDOFFS SURVIVE COMPACTION mandate below) under research-root, the Stage-2 ADR, the Stage-3 feature spec `.md`, and Stage-4 goal definitions (via the goal-create MCP tool). It MUST NOT Write/Edit ANY project source file, run a build/fix, or hand-implement the feature — EVERY project-source change happens INSIDE daemon-dispatched goals (/tmux:plan &#8594; /tmux:supervisor &#8594; /tmux:execute), validated by /tmux:investigate. If you are ever about to Write/Edit a project source file (or "just quickly scaffold" one), STOP: that is escaping the flow and is a FAILED run. Research is delegated to PARALLEL read-only investigators (Stage 1); implementation is delegated to taskvisor GOALS (Stage 4) — never to your own hands.</mandate>
    <mandate>PORTABILITY IS MANDATORY: NEVER hardcode any project-shaped value — source roots, layer names, root namespace, quality-gate commands, lang/framework, ports. Resolve every such value from `tmux-cli rules resolve` / `--signals` / project manifests, or ASK at Stage 2. Greenfield skeleton values are DEFAULTS only. Emit no project name anywhere in this command.</mandate>
    <mandate>INTERACTIVE ONLY AT STAGE 2: Stage 2 (architecture recommendation) is the SOLE stage that may prompt the user. Stages 0, 1, 3, 4, and 5 run autonomously — within them, resolve every decidable fork to the highest-quality in-scope option and record the rationale; never block on the user.</mandate>
    <mandate>NEVER skip a stage or run them out of order — the sequence 0 &#8594; 5 is strict; each stage consumes the prior stage's emitted context block.</mandate>
    <mandate>HANDOFFS SURVIVE COMPACTION: EVERY stage that emits a context block ALSO PERSISTS it to disk in the flow's research/dossier directory, per each shard's specifics (Stage 0's block as feature-context.md, Stage 4's handoff as feature-goals.md). A stage whose upstream in-conversation context block is missing (compacted away — Stage 4's asynchronous daemon run spans hours — or a resumed session) MUST re-read the persisted file rather than re-deriving or improvising the handoff; ONLY when BOTH the in-conversation block AND the persisted file are absent does the stage STOP with its named error. This is the spine-level rule — the concrete file writes live in the shards.</mandate>
    <mandate>TASK-CONFINED CHANGES: every quality gate AND every code edit is scoped to the TASK's OWN changed files — the intersection of the task diff with the resolved rules, taken over the 3-dot merge-base (`tmux-cli rules check --diff &lt;base&gt;...HEAD`, `rules match --files &lt;changed&gt;`), NEVER a 2-dot tip-to-tip diff that drags in unrelated divergence. NEVER edit, refactor, reformat, or "fix" pre-existing/unchanged code outside the task footprint — pre-existing rule violations and failing gates are REPORTED, never fixed and never gated. The delivered diff stays minimal and confined to the feature's scope.</mandate>
  </llm>

  <flow>
    <stage n="0" title="Capability + topology resolution" autonomous="true">
      <load file=".claude/commands/tmux/feature/stage-0-capability.xml">READ stage-0-capability.xml NOW and execute its content as this stage. If the shard file is NOT present, print 'ERROR: shard .claude/commands/tmux/feature/stage-0-capability.xml is missing — the tmux-cli install is incomplete or stale. Run "tmux-cli start" to regenerate .claude/commands, then re-run /tmux:feature.' and STOP; additionally treat it as a genuine harness/infra defect per the shared error-reporting procedure in &lt;execution-rules&gt; — a controlled stop, NEVER an improvised stage body.</load>
    </stage>

    <!-- ================================================================
         FAST-PATH TRIAGE — fires in the SPINE after Stage 0, before Stage 1.
         A PRECISE brief that already names a file + symbol + concrete edit
         does NOT need the full Stages 1-5 + goal-DAG pipeline; one worker can
         land it in ~20-30 min WITHOUT dropping the three quality carriers
         (rules enforcement, independent review, context isolation). This
         triage reuses the already-shipped `tmux-cli research-mode` (JSON) Go
         helper to DECIDE precision (determinism boundary, task 473; the model
         extracts the brief facts, Go emits `.precise`; the XML NEVER re-judges
         precision in prose) and, on precise + deterministic-gate-exists +
         not-e2e-driven, jumps to the XML-only feature/stage-fast-path.xml
         shard, SKIPPING Stages 1-4 + goal dispatch. Any research-mode error /
         unparseable JSON / missing gate / orchestrator env FAIL-SAFES to the
         FULL pipeline (Stage 1). This is NOT a numbered stage; the strict
         0-to-5 order below is UNCHANGED for the full path.
         ================================================================ -->
    <triage n="0.5" title="Fast-path triage — precise-brief short-circuit" autonomous="true">
      <action>EXTRACT the brief facts EXACTLY as stage-1-context.xml substep 1.2b does (the model extracts, the Go helper decides — determinism boundary, task 473): NAMED_FILES = the concrete file(s) $ARGUMENTS names; NAMED_SYMBOLS = the concrete symbol(s) (types/functions/methods) it names; CONCRETE_EDIT = whether the brief describes a specific edit to make. Do NOT estimate implied lines and do NOT judge precision here — precision is the Go helper's output, never this prose.</action>
      <action>Run via Bash: `tmux-cli research-mode --json` passing the extracted facts as flags — one `--named-file &lt;f&gt;` per NAMED_FILE, one `--named-symbol &lt;s&gt;` per NAMED_SYMBOL, and `--concrete-edit` when CONCRETE_EDIT holds. Parse the printed JSON and read the `.precise` field (Go OWNS the decision; the XML consumes `.precise` and NEVER re-judges it in prose). Keep `.reason` for the LOG line.</action>
      <action critical="true">FAIL-SAFE: if `tmux-cli research-mode` errors, is uninvocable, or emits unparseable JSON, force the verdict FALSE and take the FULL pipeline. Under-provisioning is always safe; a false fast-path is not.</action>
      <action>Compute DETERMINISTIC_GATE_EXISTS: from the Stage-0 context block's TOPOLOGY, TRUE iff Stage 0 resolved AT LEAST ONE quality-gate / test command (a bare deterministic command the fast path can hand the worker as its `## Validation Rules` and re-run as its suite gate). Greenfield / empty quality-gate set &#8594; FALSE.</action>
      <action>Compute E2E_DRIVEN via Bash: `test -n "$TMUX_CLI_ORCHESTRATOR_PANE"` — TRUE when the env var is set (an e2e-evaluator-driven run, e2e.go:230 setenv -g / :151 read). An e2e run MUST force the full pipeline so the self-healing loop keeps its exercise.</action>
      <action>VERDICT = (`.precise` == true) AND DETERMINISTIC_GATE_EXISTS AND (NOT E2E_DRIVEN). Any research-mode error/unparseable JSON already forced VERDICT FALSE (fail-safe). LOG exactly one line naming the verdict AND the helper's reason, e.g. `Fast-path triage: FAST PATH (&lt;.reason&gt;) — loading stage-fast-path.xml` or `Fast-path triage: FULL pipeline (precise=&lt;b&gt; deterministic-gate=&lt;b&gt; e2e-driven=&lt;b&gt;: &lt;.reason&gt;)`.</action>
      <check condition="VERDICT is FALSE">
        <action>Announce exactly: "Fast-path triage: FULL pipeline — proceeding to Stage 1." Proceed to Stage 1 below (the full pipeline). Do NOT load the shard.</action>
      </check>
      <check condition="VERDICT is TRUE">
        <action>Announce (mirroring stage-0-capability.xml's VALIDATION-RESUME announce&#8594;skip&#8594;jump idiom, lines 15-21): "FAST-PATH: precise brief + resolved deterministic gate + not e2e-driven — skipping Stages 1-4 + goal dispatch; loading feature/stage-fast-path.xml." Carry the extracted NAMED_FILES + NAMED_SYMBOLS + CONCRETE_EDIT + the resolved deterministic quality-gate command(s) + FEATURE + the Stage-0 context block forward as the shard's input.</action>
        <load file=".claude/commands/tmux/feature/stage-fast-path.xml">READ feature/stage-fast-path.xml NOW and execute its content as the fast path, then STOP the run at its terminal outcome — do NOT fall through to Stage 1. If the shard file is NOT present, print 'ERROR: shard .claude/commands/tmux/feature/stage-fast-path.xml is missing — the tmux-cli install is incomplete or stale. Run "tmux-cli start" to regenerate .claude/commands, then re-run /tmux:feature.' and STOP; additionally treat it as a genuine harness/infra defect per the shared error-reporting procedure in &lt;execution-rules&gt; — a controlled stop, NEVER an improvised stage body. THE ONE EXCEPTION to "do not fall through": if the shard signals FAST-PATH-ABORT (its escalation valve — a diff escaping the named scope, suite fallout outside it, a twice-FAILED / ESCALATE-ing worker, or an unresolvable finding), RESUME the spine at Stage 1 and run the FULL Stages 1-5 pipeline in strict order, consuming the shard's feature-goals.md-compatible abort handoff.</load>
      </check>
    </triage>

    <stage n="1" title="Context mapping" autonomous="true">
      <load file=".claude/commands/tmux/feature/stage-1-context.xml">READ feature/stage-1-context.xml NOW and execute its content as this stage. If the shard file is NOT present, print 'ERROR: shard .claude/commands/tmux/feature/stage-1-context.xml is missing — the tmux-cli install is incomplete or stale. Run "tmux-cli start" to regenerate .claude/commands, then re-run /tmux:feature.' and STOP; additionally treat it as a genuine harness/infra defect per the shared error-reporting procedure in &lt;execution-rules&gt; — a controlled stop, NEVER an improvised stage body.</load>
    </stage>

    <stage n="2" title="Architecture recommendation" interactive="true">
      <load file=".claude/commands/tmux/feature/stage-2-architecture.xml">READ feature/stage-2-architecture.xml NOW and execute its content as this stage. If the shard file is NOT present, print 'ERROR: shard .claude/commands/tmux/feature/stage-2-architecture.xml is missing — the tmux-cli install is incomplete or stale. Run "tmux-cli start" to regenerate .claude/commands, then re-run /tmux:feature.' and STOP; additionally treat it as a genuine harness/infra defect per the shared error-reporting procedure in &lt;execution-rules&gt; — a controlled stop, NEVER an improvised stage body. This is the SOLE interactive stage: it may prompt the user to confirm the architecture approach.</load>
    </stage>

    <stage n="3" title="Docs + test strategy" autonomous="true">
      <load file=".claude/commands/tmux/feature/stage-3-docs.xml">READ feature/stage-3-docs.xml NOW and execute its content as this stage. If the shard file is NOT present, print 'ERROR: shard .claude/commands/tmux/feature/stage-3-docs.xml is missing — the tmux-cli install is incomplete or stale. Run "tmux-cli start" to regenerate .claude/commands, then re-run /tmux:feature.' and STOP; additionally treat it as a genuine harness/infra defect per the shared error-reporting procedure in &lt;execution-rules&gt; — a controlled stop, NEVER an improvised stage body.</load>
    </stage>

    <stage n="4" title="Implementation (delegates to /tmux:plan + /tmux:supervisor)" autonomous="true">
      <load file=".claude/commands/tmux/feature/stage-4-implementation.xml">READ feature/stage-4-implementation.xml NOW and execute its content as this stage. If the shard file is NOT present, print 'ERROR: shard .claude/commands/tmux/feature/stage-4-implementation.xml is missing — the tmux-cli install is incomplete or stale. Run "tmux-cli start" to regenerate .claude/commands, then re-run /tmux:feature.' and STOP; additionally treat it as a genuine harness/infra defect per the shared error-reporting procedure in &lt;execution-rules&gt; — a controlled stop, NEVER an improvised stage body. REUSE /tmux:plan + /tmux:supervisor by reference — never re-implement them.</load>
    </stage>

    <stage n="5" title="Validation (delegates to /tmux:investigate)" autonomous="true">
      <load file=".claude/commands/tmux/feature/stage-5-validation.xml">READ feature/stage-5-validation.xml NOW and execute its content as this stage. If the shard file is NOT present, print 'ERROR: shard .claude/commands/tmux/feature/stage-5-validation.xml is missing — the tmux-cli install is incomplete or stale. Run "tmux-cli start" to regenerate .claude/commands, then re-run /tmux:feature.' and STOP; additionally treat it as a genuine harness/infra defect per the shared error-reporting procedure in &lt;execution-rules&gt; — a controlled stop, NEVER an improvised stage body. REUSE /tmux:investigate by reference — never re-implement it.</load>
    </stage>

    <!-- ================================================================
         Stages 0&#8211;5 are <load> seams. ALL seven stage shards SHIP with the
         install (feature/stage-N-*.xml under .claude/commands/tmux/); a
         shard missing on disk means the tmux-cli install is incomplete or
         stale. The stage prints its named install ERROR, files an error
         report per the shared error-reporting procedure, and STOPS in a
         controlled way (never an improvised stage body). The <load>
         directive is an LLM instruction, not an XML include — the embedded
         well-formed walk touches only files that exist on disk.
         ================================================================ -->
  </flow>

  <execution-rules>
    <rule>Stage sequence is strict and one-way: 0 &#8594; 1 &#8594; 2 &#8594; 3 &#8594; 4 &#8594; 5. Never re-order, never skip.</rule>
    <rule>Stage 2 is the ONLY interactive stage; all other stages are autonomous and resolve forks per the highest-quality in-scope option, recording rationale.</rule>
    <rule>COMPOSE existing primitives — delegate implementation to /tmux:plan + /tmux:supervisor and validation to /tmux:investigate; never duplicate their logic.</rule>
    <rule>PORTABILITY: every project-shaped value is resolved from `tmux-cli rules resolve` / `--signals` / manifests or ASKed at Stage 2 — never hardcoded; greenfield defaults only.</rule>
    <rule>TESTS_MODE is OPTIONAL per run: `feature.tests=off` (or a Stage 2 `--no-tests` reply) emits NO tests-first goals and NO test gate, but EVERY non-test gate STILL applies to every goal (static-analysis, lint/style, manifest/schema validators, the Stage-1 code-rule gate); an ephemeral eval test is permitted ONLY if deleted before completion. Default is `required` (test-first TDD — current behavior). Dropping tests NEVER drops a rule gate.</rule>
    <rule>PRIOR ART + GUIDANCE ARE REQUIRED INPUTS: Stage 1 MUST discover the nearest-analogue EXEMPLAR (the most similar already-implemented feature) and ALL related GUIDANCE DOCS (AGENTS.md/CLAUDE.md/README/docs/architecture/ADRs/nearby *.md), and Stages 2–3 MUST ground the delivered architecture, naming, and build-location in them. PRIMARY: preserve the exemplar's existing code style even when imperfect, for every discretionary choice the resolved rule/lint gates leave open. No analogue → be creative, take the resolved conventions, best-effort (flagged net-new).</rule>
    <rule>NAMING IS CONFIRMABLE BEFORE DEV: Stage 2 derives a CONCRETE NAMING MANIFEST led by the existing exemplar code (keeping the resolved naming conventions) and presents it at the approval gate for confirm/override (`approve --rename Old=New`); the approved names FREEZE into the ADR + spec so Stages 3–4 use them verbatim. The user can always set correct naming before any code is written; an override is checked against the resolved naming-convention rules (flagged, not silently dropped) and the Stage-4/5 code-rule gate still binds.</rule>
    <rule>A MISSING stage shard is an INSTALL DEFECT, never an expected state — all seven stage shards ship with the install. Print the stage's named ERROR ("the tmux-cli install is incomplete or stale &#8594; run `tmux-cli start` to regenerate .claude/commands"), STOP in a controlled way, and file it as a genuine harness/infra defect per the shared &lt;error-reporting&gt; procedure below — never crash, never improvise the stage body.</rule>
    <rule>HANDOFF PERSISTENCE: EVERY stage that emits a context block ALSO persists it to disk in the flow's research/dossier directory (per each shard's specifics — Stage 0's block as feature-context.md, Stage 4's handoff as feature-goals.md; the concrete file writes live in the shards). A stage whose upstream in-conversation context block is missing (compacted away — e.g. across the hours-long Stage 4 daemon run — or a resumed session) MUST re-read the persisted file rather than re-derive or improvise it; ONLY when BOTH the in-conversation block AND the persisted file are absent does the stage stop with its named error.</rule>
    <rule>TERMINAL SELF-CHECK (never-escape): a /tmux:feature run is COMPLETE only when Stage 4 EMITTED goals via goal-create AND the taskvisor daemon is executing them (or a named, actionable reason why not), and Stage 5 surfaced the /tmux:investigate verdict. A run that produced ANY project-source edit outside a daemon goal, or finished without emitting goals / starting the daemon, is a FAILED run — report it as failed with the reason, never as success. NEVER report "all gates green" from a partial manual check (read EVERY resolved pack; an empty-diff rule check is not a pass — see Stage 0/1).</rule>
    <rule>TASK-CONFINED: gates and edits intersect the TASK diff (3-dot `&lt;base&gt;...HEAD`) with the resolved rules — `tmux-cli rules check` / `rules match` over the changed files ONLY. Pre-existing violations or failing gates in code the task did not change are REPORTED, never fixed and never gated; no opportunistic edits to unchanged files.</rule>
    <error-reporting>On a genuine harness/infra/spec defect (an MCP tool or `tmux-cli` command that errored after its own retries, a contradictory/under-specified goal spec, or a validator-error-class condition), follow the shared `error-reporting` procedure in `tmux/task-report.xml` — compose + submit autonomously, honoring api.enabled / DEDUP / RECURSION-guard. NEVER on expected work failures (red validate cycle, supervisor pushback, NEED_INPUT, unwritten-code test red) or daemon-owned goal-failures.</error-reporting>
  </execution-rules>

  <llm final="true">
    <critical-rules>
      * COMPOSER, not engine — delegate to /tmux:plan, /tmux:supervisor, /tmux:investigate; never re-implement them
      * NEVER ESCAPE THE FLOW — orchestrate, don't implement; the ONLY writes are the ADR, the spec .md, research dossiers + the persisted context blocks (feature-context.md, feature-goals.md) under research-root, and goal definitions; ALL project-source changes happen inside daemon GOALS; research is PARALLEL read-only investigators, implementation is taskvisor goals; a run that hand-edits source, skips goal emission, or reports a partial manual check as "green" is a FAILED run
      * PORTABILITY — resolve every project-shaped value from `tmux-cli rules resolve`/`--signals`/manifests or ASK; greenfield defaults only; no project name anywhere
      * Interactive ONLY at Stage 2 — Stages 0/1/3/4/5 are autonomous
      * TESTS_MODE is optional per run — `feature.tests=off` / a Stage 2 `--no-tests` reply drops the test deliverable + test gate ONLY; every non-test gate (static-analysis, lint/style, schema, code-rule) STILL applies; eval tests allowed ONLY if deleted. Default `required` (test-first TDD)
      * PRIOR ART + GUIDANCE REQUIRED — Stage 1 finds the nearest-analogue EXEMPLAR + all GUIDANCE DOCS; Stages 2–3 model the delivered architecture/naming/build-location on them. PRIMARY: preserve the exemplar's existing code style even when imperfect (resolved gates still bind); no analogue → take the resolved conventions, best-effort
      * NAMING MANIFEST confirmable BEFORE dev — Stage 2 proposes concrete per-artifact names led by the existing exemplar code (keeping conventions), the user confirms/overrides (`approve --rename Old=New`) at the gate, and the approved names freeze into the ADR + spec for Stages 3–4 to use verbatim
      * Strict stage order 0 &#8594; 5 — each stage consumes the prior stage's emitted context block
      * TASK-CONFINED — gates + edits scoped to the task's own changed files (3-dot diff intersected with rules); never edit/fix pre-existing unchanged code; pre-existing issues reported, not gated
      * A missing stage shard = a NAMED install error ("the tmux-cli install is incomplete or stale" &#8594; run `tmux-cli start`, re-run /tmux:feature) + an error report per the shared error-reporting procedure — still a controlled STOP; never crash, NEVER improvise the stage body
      * Stage handoffs PERSIST to disk — every emitted context block is also written to the research/dossier directory (Stage 0 &#8594; feature-context.md, Stage 4 &#8594; feature-goals.md); a stage missing its upstream in-conversation block re-reads the persisted file, never re-derives; stop with the named error only when BOTH are absent
    </critical-rules>
  </llm>
</task>
