<task id="plan" name="Planning supervisor — parallel spec-writing orchestrator">
  <objective>Spawn N parallel /tmux:execute workers via tmux-cli to produce implementation-ready specification files. Read a plan/spec file, decompose it into modules, create research-task context files, decide via the dispatch gate (step 3d) whether spawning workers pays for itself — single-task plans are self-specced inline by the supervisor — spawn spec-writing workers when it does, verify spec quality against the S1–S9 pushback catalogue, present specs for interactive user approval, and finalize approved specs into tasks.yaml for /tmux:supervisor.</objective>

  <input>
    <arg name="$ARGUMENTS">Path to a plan/spec file OR inline task description. The planning supervisor reads it, derives module decomposition, and spawns parallel spec-writing workers.</arg>
  </input>

  <output>
    <primary>A finalized tasks.yaml at tasks-path (resolved in step 0b: .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/tasks.yaml in GOAL_MODE, else .tmux-cli/tasks.yaml) with status: ready and N implementation tasks, each pointing to an approved spec .md file. Ready for /tmux:supervisor consumption.</primary>
    <secondary>Spec .md files in research-root (resolved in step 0b) — one per module, with Intent, Boundaries &amp; Constraints, I/O &amp; Edge-Case Matrix, Dependencies, Code Map, Implementation Plan, Test Plan, Acceptance Criteria, Design Notes, Implementation Notes, Verification, and Spec Change Log.</secondary>
    <secondary>Research-task context .md files in research-root (resolved in step 0b) — one per module, describing what the worker should research.</secondary>
  </output>

  <requirements critical="true">
    <mcp>tmux-cli MCP server REQUIRED</mcp>
    <directory>research-root is resolved in step 0b (relative to project working directory; create if absent):
      • Standalone (no active goal): .tmux-cli/research/{y-m-d-hh}/ — {y-m-d-hh} expands to current timestamp, e.g. 2026-05-11-20.
      • Goal mode (.tmux-cli/taskvisor-current-goal exists): .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/research/ — NO timestamp subfolder.</directory>
    <constraint>The planning-queue tasks.yaml path is resolved once in step 0b as `tasks-path`: goal-scoped (.tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/tasks.yaml) in GOAL_MODE, else the top-level .tmux-cli/tasks.yaml. The taskvisor daemon and /tmux:supervisor both read the PER-GOAL file in goal mode (retry: exists/reset/inject), so writing top-level there would orphan the plan AND leave a stale `ready` landmine for the NEXT goal's planner. Only research-task and spec .md files live under research-root; tasks-path holds the queue and its context: fields point at the (possibly goal-scoped) files.</constraint>
  </requirements>

  <glossary>
    <term name="PLAN_WID">Name of the planning supervisor's tmux window (e.g. "supervisor"). Stable for whole session.</term>
    <term name="SELF_WID">Name of a spec-writing worker's tmux window (e.g. "execute-3"). Each worker gets unique N.</term>
    <term name="research-root">Primary directory for context and spec files. Resolved in step 0b: .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/research/ when a goal is active (no timestamp), else .tmux-cli/research/{y-m-d-hh}/ (timestamped). Defined in &lt;requirements&gt; / step 0b.</term>
    <term name="tasks-path">Path to the planning-queue tasks.yaml, resolved in step 0b: .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/tasks.yaml in GOAL_MODE (the per-goal file the taskvisor daemon and /tmux:supervisor read), else the top-level .tmux-cli/tasks.yaml. EVERY tasks.yaml read/write/archive/status-flip in this flow uses tasks-path.</term>
    <term name="research-task context file">Markdown file the planning supervisor writes FOR a worker, telling it what to research and how to produce the spec. Named task-&lt;slug&gt;.md in research-root.</term>
    <term name="spec file">Markdown file a worker produces as its deliverable. Contains implementation-ready specification with mandatory sections (Intent through Spec Change Log). Named execute-&lt;N&gt;-&lt;slug&gt;.md in research-root.</term>
    <term name="AUTO_APPROVE">Internal flag set when plan.auto_approve=true in setting.yaml. Causes steps 9-10 to be skipped.</term>
    <term name="AUTO_EXECUTE">Internal flag set when plan.auto_execute=true in setting.yaml. Causes step 11 to auto-invoke /tmux:supervisor after finalization.</term>
    <term name="SELF_SPEC">Internal flag set by the dispatch gate (step 3d) when exactly ONE task is pending. The planning supervisor writes that spec inline — no worker spawn — through the same validation gates (spec-validate + S5/S6/S9, max 3 self-revision rounds). Forces the blind audit (step 11a) regardless of supervisor.unplanned_audit, because author == verifier. Step 3d additionally records the solo-lane gate verdict as a top-level `lane` key in tasks-path; lane=solo SLIMS the forced audit to the daemon's-eye validate evaluation — it never skips it.</term>
    <term name="FRESH mode">No usable tasks.yaml exists — derive everything from scratch.</term>
    <term name="INCREMENTAL mode">tasks.yaml exists with status: planning — preserve existing tasks, append new spec tasks. Inherited in_progress tasks whose worker window is dead are reset to pending by the step 0c recovery so step 4 respawns them.</term>
    <term name="ranking heuristic">Priority ordering for decomposition: (1) closest to user-facing surface or critical path, (2) closest to impact target, (3) smallest budget before completion, (4) overturns prior assumption if confirmed. Break ties by lowest budget.</term>
    <term name="pushback catalogue">The S1–S9 taxonomy in step 6 used to gate spec quality before acceptance.</term>
  </glossary>

  <message-tags>
    <note>Same tagged protocol as /tmux:supervisor. Workers use [EXECUTE:...] tags, planning supervisor uses [SUPERVISOR:...] and [EXECUTE:PUSHBACK] tags. Semantics below are the source of truth.</note>
    <tag name="[EXECUTE:DONE wid=... sup=... file=&lt;abs-path&gt;]" from="worker">Worker reports spec completion. Body carries NO inline content — the .md at file= IS the spec.</tag>
    <tag name="[EXECUTE:NEED_INPUT wid=... sup=... &lt;short reason&gt;]" from="worker">Worker cannot proceed without a fact. Reason ≤ 200 chars inline. Planning supervisor answers via windows-message, or replies [SUPERVISOR:NARROW-SCOPE].</tag>
    <tag name="[EXECUTE:FAILED wid=... sup=... reason=&lt;short&gt;]" from="worker">Worker hit terminal failure. Reason ≤ 200 chars inline. Planning supervisor respawns with narrowed scope (first attempt) or escalates (second).</tag>
    <tag name="[SUPERVISOR:REMIND &lt;what to do&gt;]" from="plan-supervisor">Protocol reminder to worker. Does not advance state.</tag>
    <tag name="[EXECUTE:PUSHBACK n=&lt;1|2|3&gt; gap=&lt;S1..S9&gt;]" from="plan-supervisor">Spec quality gap per pushback catalogue. Worker updates the SAME .md and re-tags DONE.</tag>
    <tag name="[SUPERVISOR:AMEND &lt;new scope&gt;]" from="plan-supervisor">Amend a running worker's scope mid-run.</tag>
    <tag name="[SUPERVISOR:AMEND-PROTOCOL &lt;new rule&gt;]" from="plan-supervisor">Amend response protocol mid-run.</tag>
    <tag name="[SUPERVISOR:KILL]" from="plan-supervisor">Instruct worker to exit cleanly — scope now pointless.</tag>
    <tag name="[SUPERVISOR:NARROW-SCOPE &lt;reduced problem&gt;]" from="plan-supervisor">Narrow a NEED_INPUT-blocked worker's scope instead of escalating.</tag>
  </message-tags>

  <autonomy-policy>
    <rule>The planning supervisor operates AUTONOMOUSLY during the SPEC-WRITING PHASE (steps 0–8): spawning workers, routing messages, pushing back on gaps, replanning. No user gates during worker management.</rule>
    <rule>The planning supervisor is INTERACTIVE during the APPROVAL PHASE (steps 9–10): the user reviews, edits, adds, removes, or re-specs modules before finalization.</rule>
    <rule>NEVER finalize (step 11) without explicit user "approve" from step 10 — UNLESS AUTO_APPROVE is true.</rule>
    <rule>When AUTO_APPROVE is true, the planning supervisor operates FULLY AUTONOMOUSLY — no user interaction at any step. Specs are accepted after S1-S9 verification and immediately finalized.</rule>
    <rule>For ambiguity during spec-writing: pick the highest-yield interpretation per &lt;ranking&gt; and record the chosen rationale so the user can redirect in step 10.</rule>
    <rule>Escalate to user ONLY for: (a) zero executable workers constructable from input, (b) user-only knowledge (credentials, intent, out-of-band facts), or (c) the mandatory approval phase (steps 9–10).</rule>
    <rule>The planning supervisor does NOT have autonomy to change the number or boundaries of tasks when working from a user-approved decomposition. The user approved the structure; the planner fills in the detail.</rule>
  </autonomy-policy>

  <decision-policy>
    <rule critical="true">Decision-resolution policy (quality-in-scope). When planning or implementation reaches a decision point — an "Ask First" item, a verdict/correction presenting options, or any fork between a lower-effort waiver/shortcut and a higher-quality approach — do NOT halt for a human by default. Autonomously choose the option that MAXIMIZES correctness and quality (e.g. real domain types over asserted strings, no waivers, no shortcuts, no new tech-debt) PROVIDED it does NOT expand the goal's stated scope (no new files, features, endpoints, or surface beyond the goal's intent / acceptance criteria). Record the chosen option + a one-line rationale. Escalate to a human ONLY when the decision needs user-only knowledge no file or codebase inspection can supply — credentials, business intent, or out-of-band facts. A purely technical/architectural choice is NEVER user-only.</rule>
    <rule>When a spec produces option-forks, the planner applies this policy: name the RECOMMENDED (highest-quality in-scope) option in the spec's Ask First / Boundaries so the implementation worker auto-applies it rather than halting. This is consistent with &lt;autonomy-policy&gt; rule (b) — escalate only for user-only knowledge.</rule>
  </decision-policy>

  <llm critical="true">
    <mandate>NEVER implement code — produce specs only</mandate>
    <mandate>NEVER set tasks.yaml status to "ready" before user approves (step 11 only) — UNLESS AUTO_APPROVE is true (plan.auto_approve setting)</mandate>
    <mandate>NEVER skip user review (steps 9–10 are mandatory) — UNLESS AUTO_APPROVE is true</mandate>
    <mandate>When AUTO_EXECUTE is true, ALWAYS send /clear + /tmux:supervisor to PLAN_WID after finalization — this is the handoff to the implementation supervisor</mandate>
    <mandate>ALWAYS use windows-spawn-worker for spawning — never assemble manually via windows-create + windows-send</mandate>
    <mandate>ALWAYS verify spec quality against S1–S9 before accepting a worker's DONE</mandate>
    <mandate>Default to MAXIMUM parallelism for spec workers when dispatching (2+ pending tasks after the step 3d gate) — implementation dependency does NOT block spec-writing</mandate>
    <mandate>NEVER spawn a worker for a single pending task — the step 3d dispatch gate self-specs it inline; a worker would re-load the exact context the supervisor already holds, buying no parallelism for pure overhead. SOLE EXCEPTION: step 11b audit-fail replans DISPATCH a real worker even for a single task — a self-written spec that failed independent review must never be self-specced again</mandate>
    <mandate>NEVER spawn a worker before tasks.yaml is written and verified (step 3b gate)</mandate>
    <mandate>NEVER call /worker:execute — use /tmux:execute which is the correct skill name</mandate>
    <mandate>NEVER use sleep — idle is the trigger for incoming windows-message</mandate>
    <mandate>NEVER kill your own PLAN_WID</mandate>
    <mandate>windows-kill takes the window NAME (e.g. "execute-3"), not an @id. windows-send accepts @N; kill does not.</mandate>
    <mandate>Execute steps ONE BY ONE in EXACT ORDER</mandate>
    <mandate>NEVER use AskUserQuestion — all interaction is via text output and waiting for user messages (ensures compatibility inside tmux windows)</mandate>
    <mandate>NEVER use batch Bash scripts to validate, revalidate, or process multiple specs — ALWAYS use the proper agent flow: spawn workers, route messages, call MCP tools (spec-validate, tasks-validate) per-file. Batch shortcuts bypass quality gates and miss context-dependent gaps. Token cost is irrelevant — precision is the goal.</mandate>
    <mandate>NEVER merge, squash, or recompose tasks when the input references a user-approved task breakdown — preserve the exact count and boundaries. You may add detail and context to each task but not change the decomposition structure.</mandate>
  </llm>

  <spec-deliverable-template>
    <note>This is the custom deliverable format passed to windows-spawn-worker via the deliverable parameter. It REPLACES the standard FINDINGS/RISKS/RECOMMENDATION/FILES format. Workers produce spec files with these mandatory sections.</note>
    <template>
DELIVERABLE (write these sections INSIDE the spec .md; do NOT paste them into tmux):
- ## Intent: Restate the module's purpose from the research-task context file. Two fields:
  **Problem:** ONE_TO_TWO_SENTENCES — what is broken or missing.
  **Approach:** ONE_TO_TWO_SENTENCES — the high-level "what", not the "how".
  This is the anchor — the rest of the spec must serve this intent.
- ## Boundaries &amp; Constraints: Three tiers:
  **Always:** invariant rules this module must obey (e.g. "all public functions must have tests").
  **Ask First:** decisions the implementation worker AUTO-RESOLVES per the Decision-resolution policy (quality-in-scope) — choose the highest-quality option that does NOT expand the goal's scope and record a one-line rationale; halt and ask ONLY for user-only facts (credentials / business intent / out-of-band) that no file or codebase inspection can supply.
  **Never:** explicit non-goals and forbidden approaches (e.g. "never modify the executor interface").
- ## I/O &amp; Edge-Case Matrix (optional — DELETE entirely if no meaningful I/O interfaces exist, do NOT write "N/A"):
  Table with columns: Scenario | Input / State | Expected Output / Behavior | Error Handling.
  Cover: happy path, error cases, boundary conditions. Each row must be specific enough to become a test case.
- ## Dependencies: Which modules must be complete first and what they provide. Write "none" if independent.
- ## Code Map: Annotated file paths that prevent blind codebase searching during implementation. Format: `FILE:LINE` — ROLE_OR_RELEVANCE. Each entry answers: what does the implementation worker need this file for? MUST cite specific files, functions, and line numbers from the source code.
  For files being MODIFIED (listed under Files to Modify), also annotate: `FILE:LINE` — CURRENT: &lt;what it does now&gt; | CHANGE: &lt;what this spec changes&gt; | PRESERVE: &lt;what must not break&gt;.
- ## Implementation Plan:
  - ### Files to Create/Modify: path and purpose for each file. For MODIFIED files, state what the file does today and what changes. One task per file preferred; group tightly-coupled changes when splitting would be artificial.
  - ### Key Classes/Functions: name, purpose, signature, key logic.
  - ### API Endpoints (if applicable): method, path, description, request/response format.
  - ### Frontend Pages (if applicable): template name, description, key UI elements.
- ## Test Plan: Specific unit test cases with expected behavior (not just "write tests"). Integration test scenarios describing what to test against real services/hardware. If an I/O Matrix is present, include test cases covering its edge cases.
- ## Acceptance Criteria: Given/When/Then format. Each criterion must be independently testable AND checkbox-formatted:
  - [ ] Given PRECONDITION, when ACTION, then EXPECTED_RESULT
- ## Design Notes (optional — DELETE entirely if the approach is straightforward, do NOT write "N/A"):
  Architectural rationale and golden examples only when non-obvious. Keep examples to 5–10 lines.
- ## Implementation Notes: Tricky parts, gotchas, edge cases, performance considerations. Do NOT mix design rationale here — that belongs in Design Notes.
- ## Verification: How the implementation worker confirms its own work. Prefer CLI commands with expected output. When no CLI check applies, state what to inspect manually. DELETE entirely if no verifiable claims exist.
- ## Spec Change Log: Initially empty. Populated during pushback rounds. Append-only — never delete existing entries. Each entry records: what gap was cited, what was changed, what known-bad state was avoided, and KEEP instructions (what worked well and must survive the fix).

SELF-REVIEW (mandatory before tagging DONE):
Verify the spec against the Ready for Development standard:
- Actionable: every task in Implementation Plan has a file path and specific action
- Logical: tasks are ordered by dependency — no task references something created by a later task
- Testable: all Acceptance Criteria use Given/When/Then format
- Complete: no placeholders, no TBDs, no "to be determined", no empty sections (except optional ones marked DELETE)
- Preservation-safe: every MODIFIED file in Code Map has CURRENT/CHANGE/PRESERVE annotations
If any criterion fails, fix before submitting DONE.

EXPLORATION:
Isolate deep codebase exploration in sub-agents where available. Instruct sub-agents to return distilled summaries only — file paths, key functions, signatures, relevant constants. Do not load full file contents into your own context when a sub-agent summary suffices. This prevents context snowballing during spec writing.

SCOPE:
Target 900–1600 tokens for the spec body (excluding Code Map file listings). Below 900 risks ambiguity for implementation workers. Above 1600 risks context rot — the implementation worker loads this spec alongside other context. If your spec exceeds 1600, tighten prose or split sub-modules. Neither limit blocks submission — they are quality signals for self-review.
    </template>
  </spec-deliverable-template>

  <research-task-template>
    <note>Template the planning supervisor uses when creating research-task context files for workers in step 3. Each file tells one worker WHAT to research and HOW to produce the spec. Adapt the template to each module — some fields may be empty or expanded.</note>
    <template>
# Spec Task: &lt;module name&gt;

## Research Instructions

Produce an implementation-ready spec for this module. Read the source files listed below, analyze the existing code, and write a comprehensive spec following the DELIVERABLE format in your task message. Self-review against the Ready for Development standard before submitting.

## Source Files to Analyze
- `path/to/file` — what to look for
- `path/to/another` — what protocol/logic to extract

## Module Description
&lt;from the plan file — what this module does, its scope, its boundaries&gt;

## Known Dependencies
- Module X: &lt;what it provides to this module&gt;
(or "none" if independent)

## Constraints &amp; Boundaries
Always: &lt;invariant rules from the plan/project context — conventions, patterns that MUST be followed&gt;
Never: &lt;explicit non-goals for this module — what is OUT of scope, forbidden approaches&gt;
Ask First: &lt;decisions to auto-resolve preferring the highest-quality in-scope option (record rationale); escalate ONLY user-only facts (credentials/business-intent/out-of-band)&gt;
&lt;additional project conventions, architecture patterns, technology choices&gt;

## Prior Learnings
&lt;distilled insights from previous planning cycles relevant to this module — patterns, problems, decisions, gotchas&gt;
(or "none — first planning cycle" if no prior research exists)
    </template>
  </research-task-template>

  <flow>
    <step n="0" title="Audit guard">
      <action>Remove .tmux-cli/audit-done guard file if it exists.</action>
      <action>Remove prior audit verdict files for clean-slate audit runs. Check $ARGUMENTS for a `.tmux-cli/goals/goal-{ns}/` path segment; if found, use that ns as an early GOAL_ID. Else check if `.tmux-cli/taskvisor-current-goal` exists and is non-empty and read GOAL_ID from it. If a GOAL_ID was found: `rm -f .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/research/plan-audit-*.md .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/research/plan-approval.md`. Else (standalone): `rm -f docs/architecture/plan-audit-*.md docs/architecture/plan-approval.md`.</action>
      <note>The clean-slate gate runs in step 0c — AFTER step 0b, because it operates on tasks-path, which requires GOAL_ID/GOAL_MODE to be resolved first.</note>
    </step>

    <step n="0b" title="Resolve research-root">
      <action>Inspect $ARGUMENTS for a goal-scoped dispatch path: the taskvisor daemon's first-cycle dispatch sends `/tmux:plan &lt;abs&gt;/.tmux-cli/goals/goal-{ns}/dispatch.md`. If $ARGUMENTS contains a `.tmux-cli/goals/goal-{ns}/` path segment, extract goal-{ns} as ARG_GOAL_ID (empty when $ARGUMENTS carries no such path).</action>
      <branch condition="ARG_GOAL_ID is set (a .tmux-cli/goals/goal-{ns}/ segment in $ARGUMENTS) — HIGHEST PRECEDENCE">
        <action>GOAL mode (dispatch-path binding). Set GOAL_ID = ARG_GOAL_ID. Prefer this over the global .tmux-cli/taskvisor-current-goal marker: the daemon writes that marker GLOBALLY on every dispatch, so under concurrent dispatch it is last-writer-wins and may name ANOTHER goal, whereas the dispatch path you were handed is per-goal-safe. Set research-root = .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/research/ (NO timestamp). Set tasks-path = .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/tasks.yaml (the per-goal planning queue the daemon and supervisor read). Create the goal dir / research-root if absent. Set internal flag GOAL_MODE=true. Log: "Goal mode (dispatch-path binding): GOAL_ID={GOAL_ID}, research-root=.tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/research/, tasks-path=.tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/tasks.yaml".</action>
      </branch>
      <branch condition="ARG_GOAL_ID is NOT set">
        <action>Check whether .tmux-cli/taskvisor-current-goal exists and is non-empty.</action>
        <branch condition="exists and non-empty">
          <action>GOAL mode. Read GOAL_ID from the file (trim whitespace). Set research-root = .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/research/ (NO timestamp). Set tasks-path = .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/tasks.yaml (the per-goal planning queue the daemon and supervisor read). Create the goal dir / research-root if absent. Set internal flag GOAL_MODE=true. Log: "Goal mode: GOAL_ID={GOAL_ID}, research-root=.tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/research/, tasks-path=.tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/tasks.yaml".</action>
        </branch>
        <branch condition="absent or empty">
          <action>STANDALONE mode. Set research-root = .tmux-cli/research/{y-m-d-hh}/ ({y-m-d-hh} = current timestamp). Set tasks-path = .tmux-cli/tasks.yaml. Create research-root if absent. Set internal flag GOAL_MODE=false. Log: "Standalone mode: research-root=.tmux-cli/research/{y-m-d-hh}/, tasks-path=.tmux-cli/tasks.yaml".</action>
        </branch>
      </branch>
      <rule>Every later reference to research-root AND tasks-path in this flow uses the values resolved here. Every tasks.yaml read/write/archive/status-flip means tasks-path — never hardcode the top-level .tmux-cli/tasks.yaml in GOAL_MODE.</rule>
    </step>

    <step n="0c" title="Clean slate">
      <action>Check if tasks-path (resolved in step 0b) exists:</action>
      <branch condition="exists AND status=planning">
        <action>INCREMENTAL mode — existing tasks preserved. Inform user: "Existing plan found with N tasks (status: planning). Entering incremental mode — existing tasks preserved."</action>
        <action>IN_PROGRESS RECOVERY (deadlock guard): collect every task with status=in_progress from tasks-path. If none exist, skip this action. Otherwise call windows-list once and classify each: a task whose wid has a live window of that exact name is a LIVE worker — leave it in_progress (its messages still route to this supervisor window name in step 5); a task whose wid has NO live window is an ORPHAN — its worker died with the previous planner. Reset each orphan to status=pending in tasks-path and log "Recovered {wid} (in_progress, no live window) → pending — step 4 respawns it". If the windows-list call fails, reset NOTHING (fail-safe — liveness cannot be verified; step 1's MCP precondition will STOP the flow). Without this recovery, inherited in_progress tasks with dead workers deadlock the flow: step 4 spawns only pending tasks and step 5 idles forever on [EXECUTE:*] messages that can never arrive.</action>
        <action>Proceed to step 1.</action>
      </branch>
      <branch condition="exists AND status=ready AND GOAL_MODE is true">
        <action>LIVENESS CHECK — verify no live execution is bound to tasks-path before archiving: (1) derive {ns} from GOAL_ID (strip the `goal-` prefix); read tasks-path collecting every task wid and the subset with status=in_progress; read `.tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/supervisor-window` as OWN_WID if present (the daemon wrote it for THIS dispatch — it names this planner's own window). (2) Call windows-list. Liveness signals: (a) a live window named equal to any wid from tasks-path; (b) any task with status=in_progress (conservative — counts even without a matching window); (c) a supervisor-{ns} window NOT attributable to OWN_WID. A supervisor-{ns} entry equal to OWN_WID is the planner itself — never a signal. (3) If the windows-list call fails, treat the goal as live (fail-safe: liveness cannot be verified, so archiving is forbidden; include the error in the decline log).</action>
        <branch condition="any liveness signal fired">
          <action>DECLINE the re-plan: log "Declined re-plan for {GOAL_ID}: live execution bound to tasks-path (signals: {fired signals}) — leaving the plan untouched; the original supervisor's workers continue unaffected." If the only signal is an in_progress entry with no matching window, append the remediation hint: "archive manually if the supervisor is known dead". STOP the entire flow — do not proceed to step 1, leave tasks-path byte-untouched, kill no windows, message no agents.</action>
        </branch>
        <branch condition="no liveness signal fired (truly stale)">
          <action>Auto-archive WITHOUT user confirmation: move tasks-path to .tmux-cli/tasks/{y-m-d-hh}/tasks-{mm}.yaml (create directory if needed), log "Archived stale finalized plan for {GOAL_ID} (status: ready) — daemon re-dispatch implies re-plan", then proceed in FRESH mode. A daemon-dispatched planner has NO human to answer a confirmation prompt — waiting would burn the goal's entire cycle timeout and get misclassified as a code defect. A `ready` file here is NOT always stale — the liveness check above distinguishes a truly stale plan (this goal's prior cycle superseded by this re-dispatch, or a leftover the daemon already consumed) from one under live supervision.</action>
        </branch>
      </branch>
      <branch condition="exists AND status=ready AND GOAL_MODE is false">
        <action>Warn user: "Tasks already finalized (status: ready). Re-planning will archive the current plan."</action>
        <action>Wait for user confirmation. On confirmation: archive to .tmux-cli/tasks/{y-m-d-hh}/tasks-{mm}.yaml (create directory if needed), then proceed in FRESH mode.</action>
        <action>On rejection: STOP.</action>
      </branch>
      <branch condition="exists AND all tasks have status=done">
        <action>Archive to .tmux-cli/tasks/{y-m-d-hh}/tasks-{mm}.yaml, remove original.</action>
        <action>Proceed in FRESH mode.</action>
      </branch>
      <branch condition="does not exist">
        <action>FRESH mode. Proceed to step 1.</action>
      </branch>
      <action condition="GOAL_MODE is true">Legacy-landmine sweep: if the TOP-LEVEL .tmux-cli/tasks.yaml ALSO exists (pre-fix planners wrote the queue there in goal mode and nothing ever cleaned it), archive it to .tmux-cli/tasks/{y-m-d-hh}/tasks-{mm}.yaml WITHOUT user confirmation and log "Archived legacy top-level planning queue (pre-per-goal-tasks-path leftover)". It cannot belong to this plan — tasks-path is per-goal — and leaving it would re-trigger this gate for every future standalone run.</action>
    </step>

    <step n="1" title="MCP precondition">
      <action>Call windows-list.</action>
      <check condition="tmux-cli not available">
        <action>Print exactly: ERROR: tmux-cli MCP required but not available — enable it and retry.</action>
        <action>STOP. Do not create any windows.</action>
      </check>
    </step>

    <step n="1b" title="Read project context">
      <action>Check if AGENTS.md exists in the project root. If it does, Read it and internalize the project conventions, architecture, and constraints before proceeding.</action>
      <action>If AGENTS.md does not exist, check for CLAUDE.md instead. Read whichever is found first.</action>
      <action>If neither exists, proceed without project context.</action>
      <action>Read .tmux-cli/setting.yaml. Check for plan.auto_approve and plan.auto_execute keys:</action>
      <check condition="plan.auto_approve is true">
        <action>Set internal flag AUTO_APPROVE=true. Log: "Auto-approve mode enabled (plan.auto_approve=true)."</action>
      </check>
      <check condition="plan.auto_execute is true">
        <action>Set internal flag AUTO_EXECUTE=true. Log: "Auto-execute mode enabled (plan.auto_execute=true)."</action>
      </check>
      <check condition="supervisor.unplanned_audit is true (default true if absent)">
        <action>Set internal flag AUDIT_ENABLED=true. Log: "Blind audit gate enabled (supervisor.unplanned_audit=true)."</action>
      </check>
      <check condition="supervisor.unplanned_audit is false">
        <action>Set internal flag AUDIT_ENABLED=false. Log: "Blind audit gate disabled (supervisor.unplanned_audit=false)."</action>
      </check>
      <action>Standalone mode only: scan .tmux-cli/research/ for prior cycle directories ({y-m-d-hh}/ that are NOT the current session's research-root). In goal mode skip this scan — there is a single goal research/ dir and prior corrections arrive via the dispatch file in $ARGUMENTS.</action>
      <check condition="prior research directories exist">
        <action>Read up to 3 most recent directories (newest first). For each, scan spec files (execute-*.md) and extract: module names (## Intent), patterns (## Design Notes), gotchas (## Implementation Notes), decisions made. Distill into a prior-learnings summary (max 500 tokens).</action>
        <action>Store prior-learnings summary for use in step 3.</action>
      </check>
      <rule>This context MUST inform your decomposition decisions, task scoping, and research-task context file content throughout the session.</rule>
    </step>

    <step n="2" title="Identify PLAN_WID">
      <action>When GOAL_ID is known (GOAL_MODE, resolved in step 0b): read .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/supervisor-window and use its content VERBATIM (trim only the trailing newline/whitespace) as PLAN_WID. The daemon wrote this per-goal marker byte-exact before the plan command was sent, so it names the real plan/supervisor window — ALWAYS the namespaced supervisor-{ns} (at every MaxGoals, including 1); bare `supervisor` is window-0/standalone only, never a goal window. Do NOT probe the tmux window name and do NOT re-derive it.</action>
      <fallback>If GOAL_MODE but the .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/supervisor-window marker is absent: derive {ns} from GOAL_ID (strip the `goal-` prefix, e.g. goal-002 → 002) and PREFER a window named supervisor-{ns} in windows-list over the bare `supervisor`; if neither namespaced nor bare match exists, fall back to bare `supervisor` last.</fallback>
      <fallback>In STANDALONE mode (no GOAL_ID): from windows-list, pick the entry with active: true if present. If the tmux-cli implementation does not expose active:true (e.g. returns only {"name":...}), and exactly one window exists, treat its NAME as PLAN_WID. If multiple windows exist and none is marked active: if a window named "supervisor" exists in windows-list, that is your PLAN_WID — use it without asking.</fallback>
      <action>Store PLAN_WID (name form, e.g. "supervisor" or "supervisor-002") for the whole session.</action>
    </step>

    <step n="3" title="Analyze plan file → decompose into modules">
      <action>Read $ARGUMENTS — if it is a file path, read that file. If inline text, use directly.</action>
      <action>Identify N modules/aspects/components from the plan.</action>
      <action>For each module determine: name, scope summary, source files to analyze, dependencies on other modules.</action>
      <action>Respect the dependency graph if present in the plan — record it for tasks.yaml and the final dependency ordering in step 11.</action>
      <rule critical="true">When $ARGUMENTS references a user-approved task decomposition (numbered list, table, explicit breakdown from prior conversation), PRESERVE the exact task count and boundaries. Create research-task context files and add implementation detail for each task, but NEVER merge, squash, split, or recompose the approved tasks. The user approved the structure; the planner fills in the detail.</rule>
      <parallelism>
        <rule critical="true">Default to MAXIMUM parallelism for spec-writing. Implementation dependencies do NOT block parallel spec-writing. Each spec worker reads source code independently — it does not need another module to be IMPLEMENTED first.</rule>
        <rule>Serialize spec-writing ONLY when a later worker's research scope is literally unconstructable without the prior worker's spec output (rare — usually only for meta-modules that define shared conventions).</rule>
        <rule>Example: M5–M7 depend on M4 for implementation, but their SPECS can be written in parallel because each worker reads the existing source code independently.</rule>
      </parallelism>
      <action>Create research-root directory if it does not exist.</action>
      <action>For each module, create a research-task context file in research-root using the &lt;research-task-template&gt;. File path: {research-root}/task-&lt;slug&gt;.md (research-root resolved in step 0b). Populate with module-specific source files, description, dependencies, and constraints from the plan and project context.</action>
      <action>If prior-learnings summary exists (from step 1b), include relevant learnings in each research-task context file under "## Prior Learnings". Filter by relevance: matching file paths, module names, or technology overlap with the current module.</action>
      <incremental condition="INCREMENTAL mode">
        <action>Load existing tasks from tasks.yaml. New modules from $ARGUMENTS are derived and added alongside existing ones.</action>
        <action>Assign wid values starting after the highest existing execute-N.</action>
      </incremental>
    </step>

    <step n="3b" title="Write and verify tasks.yaml" critical="true">
      <action>Write or update tasks-path (resolved in step 0b — per-goal .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/tasks.yaml in GOAL_MODE, top-level .tmux-cli/tasks.yaml in standalone) with the following structure:</action>
      <format>
status: planning
cycle: 1
tasks:
  - name: "&lt;module name&gt;"
    wid: "execute-N"
    status: pending
    context: "{research-root}/task-&lt;slug&gt;.md"
    depends_on: ["execute-M"]  # implementation dependency — from plan's dependency graph. Optional.
      </format>
      <rule>The literal value written for context: is the RESOLVED research-root path (step 0b) — goal-scoped (.tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/research/task-&lt;slug&gt;.md) in goal mode, timestamped (.tmux-cli/research/{y-m-d-hh}/task-&lt;slug&gt;.md) in standalone mode. The file itself is written at tasks-path (also step 0b) — per-goal in GOAL_MODE, top-level in standalone.</rule>
      <action>Verify all context files referenced in tasks.yaml exist on disk.</action>
      <check condition="any context file is missing">
        <action>STOP. Create missing context files per step 3, then re-verify.</action>
      </check>
      <action>Call tasks-validate MCP tool. In GOAL_MODE pass goal_id={GOAL_ID} so it validates the per-goal file (tasks-path); in standalone call it with no goal_id so it validates the top-level queue. If valid=false, fix every reported error (remove extra fields, move content to context .md file) and re-run until valid=true.</action>
      <check condition="all context files exist AND tasks-validate returns valid=true AND tasks-path contains all planned tasks">
        <action>Proceed to step 4.</action>
      </check>
      <rule>Set status to "planning" — NOT "ready". Only step 11 sets "ready" after user approval.</rule>
      <rule critical="true">BLOCKING GATE. No worker may be spawned (step 4) until tasks.yaml is written, verified, tasks-validate passes, and all context files exist.</rule>
      <incremental condition="INCREMENTAL mode">
        <action>Preserve existing tasks. Append new tasks. Preserve existing cycle number.</action>
      </incremental>
    </step>

    <step n="3c" title="Spec cache check (GOAL_MODE only)">
      <condition>GOAL_MODE is true — skip this step entirely in standalone mode (standalone uses timestamped research dirs, so prior specs are unreachable).</condition>
      <action>Scan {research-root} for existing spec files matching the pattern execute-*.md. If none found, fall through to step 3d.</action>
      <action>For each pending task in tasks-path, derive the task slug from its context path: strip the task- prefix and .md suffix from the filename (e.g. task-foo-bar.md → foo-bar).</action>
      <action>For each pending task slug, search for cached spec files matching execute-*-{slug}.md in research-root. If multiple matches exist (from different worker cycles), pick the one with the highest execute-N number (most recent worker).</action>
      <action>For each matched cached spec file: call spec-validate MCP tool with the file path (the tool checks S0–S4, S7, S8 automatically — same call pattern as step 6), then run the manual S5/S6/S9 checks from step 6 on it. A cached spec faces the SAME full gate as a fresh worker spec — cached specs are the ones most likely to carry stale dependencies (S5), so they must not get a weaker gate.</action>
      <branch condition="spec-validate returns valid=true AND the manual S5/S6/S9 checks pass for a matched spec">
        <action>Spec cache hit: reuse the existing spec. Mark the task as status=done in tasks-path. Update the task context field to point to the cached spec file path. Log: "Spec cache hit: reusing {filename} for task {name} (spec-validate + S5/S6/S9 passed)".</action>
      </branch>
      <branch condition="spec-validate returns valid=false OR any manual S5/S6/S9 check fails OR no matching cached spec found for a task">
        <action>Spec cache miss: task stays pending for the dispatch gate (step 3d). Log: "Spec cache miss: {filename} failed spec-validate or S5/S6/S9 — will re-spec" (or "no cached spec found for task {name}").</action>
      </branch>
      <check condition="all tasks in tasks-path now have status=done after cache reuse">
        <action>All specs cached and valid — skip spec worker phase. Log: "All specs cached and valid — skipping to coverage verification". Proceed directly to step 8b (coverage verification).</action>
      </check>
      <check condition="some tasks still pending after cache check">
        <action>Fall through to step 3d — the dispatch gate decides whether the remaining pending tasks warrant worker spawning.</action>
      </check>
      <rule>Only check pending tasks — tasks already marked done (e.g. from INCREMENTAL mode) are not rechecked.</rule>
      <rule>Slug matching: task context path task-{slug}.md maps to cached spec execute-*-{slug}.md in research-root. When multiple execute-*-{slug}.md files match, pick the highest execute-N number (most recent worker).</rule>
    </step>

    <step n="3d" title="Dispatch decision gate">
      <condition>Pending tasks remain after steps 3b/3c (in standalone mode step 3c is skipped — arrive here directly from 3b). Count tasks with status=pending in tasks-path.</condition>
      <branch condition="exactly ONE task is pending">
        <action>SELF_SPEC mode — do NOT spawn a worker. A spec worker would re-load the exact context this supervisor already holds (the plan, the module scope, the source files); for one module the spawn/route/kill cycle buys zero parallelism and no extra context capacity — one agent's context is enough. Set internal flag SELF_SPEC=true. Log: "Dispatch gate: 1 pending task — self-speccing inline (no worker spawn)".</action>
        <action title="solo-lane gate (LANE GATE G1–G5)">Apply the LANE GATE by REFERENCE: evaluate the canonical `solo-lane` block — &lt;lane-gate name="solo-lane"&gt; in .claude/commands/tmux/task-list.xml (tracked source: cmd/tmux-cli/embedded/commands/tmux/task-list.xml) — against this single pending task. Its G1–G5 criteria and plan-3d evaluation sources live ONLY in that block; NEVER restate them here. Standalone mode (GOAL_MODE=false — no goal.md / goals.yaml entry): the gate fails closed to full and NO lane key is ever written. Log the per-criterion verdict line. Verdict solo → write top-level `lane: solo` to tasks-path. Verdict NOT solo AND goal.md `## Lane` == solo (a stale inherited solo this run does not affirm) → write explicit top-level `lane: full` to tasks-path — the demotion override for the downstream lane-resolution fallback (tasks.yaml lane → goal.md → full), and the ONLY case where `lane: full` is ever written. Otherwise write NOTHING (absent lane = full).</action>
        <action>Write the spec yourself, exactly as a worker would: read the task's research-task context file and the source files it lists (isolate deep codebase exploration in sub-agents per the EXPLORATION guidance in &lt;spec-deliverable-template&gt; — distilled summaries only), then produce {research-root}/execute-{N}-{slug}.md — {N} from the task's wid, {slug} from its context filename — containing every mandatory section of &lt;spec-deliverable-template&gt;. Run the template's SELF-REVIEW before submitting your own spec to validation.</action>
        <action>Validate your own spec through the SAME gates a worker faces: call spec-validate MCP tool on the file, then manually check S5/S6/S9 (definitions in step 6). On any failure, revise the spec and record the round in ## Spec Change Log (gap cited, what changed, KEEP instructions). Cap: 3 self-revision rounds — after the 3rd, accept as-is and log the unresolved gap(s) for the step 9 summary, mirroring the worker pushback cap.</action>
        <action>On acceptance: mark the task status=done in tasks-path and update its context field to the spec file path (same mechanics as a step 3c cache hit). Proceed directly to step 8b (coverage verification) — steps 4–7 are skipped entirely.</action>
        <rule critical="true">SELF_SPEC forces the blind audit: step 11a runs even when supervisor.unplanned_audit=false. With author == verifier, the audit sub-agent is the only independent review of the spec — skipping it would leave the plan with no external gate at all.</rule>
      </branch>
      <branch condition="2 or more tasks are pending">
        <action title="solo-lane stale-solo demotion">2+ pending tasks can never be solo (G1 miss by construction — the gate itself is not evaluated): if GOAL_MODE and goal.md `## Lane` == solo, write explicit top-level `lane: full` to tasks-path (demotes the stale inherited solo); otherwise write nothing.</action>
        <action>Dispatch normally — parallel spec workers amortize their spawn cost and keep per-module context isolated. Proceed to step 4.</action>
      </branch>
      <rule>The gate counts PENDING tasks only — tasks already done via the step 3c spec cache or INCREMENTAL mode do not count toward the dispatch threshold.</rule>
      <rule>The gate decides HOW specs get written, never how many — it must not merge, split, or re-scope tasks (that authority stays with step 3 and the user-approved decomposition).</rule>
    </step>

    <step n="4" title="Spawn spec workers (sequentially within your turn)">
      <action>For each pending task in tasks.yaml, call windows-spawn-worker with:</action>
      <params>
        - supervisorWid: your PLAN_WID name
        - subtask: task name (one-line label for this spec worker)
        - contextFile: path to the research-task context .md file
        - scope: derived from the context .md file (read it and summarize key scope points)
        - context: derived from the context .md file (dependencies, constraints, prior findings)
        - deliverable: custom spec format from &lt;spec-deliverable-template&gt;
      </params>
      <action>The tool atomically: picks the next execute-N name, creates the window, sends /tmux:execute, assembles and sends the task message with the custom DELIVERABLE + RESPONSE PROTOCOL.</action>
      <action>Record from the response: workerName, window.tmuxWindowId, taskMessage (for tracking).</action>
      <action>Update task status to in_progress in tasks.yaml after each successful spawn.</action>
      <critical>ALWAYS use windows-spawn-worker — never assemble spawn steps manually via windows-create + windows-send.</critical>
    </step>

    <step n="5" title="Idle and route">
      <action>Do NOTHING. Wait for windows-message from workers.</action>
      <rule>NEVER use sleep. NEVER poll windows-list while idle.</rule>
      <rule>Stop-hook idle notifications ("Idling — awaiting supervisor task payload" / "Report delivered to supervisor. Idling for accept or pushback") are expected /tmux:execute lifecycle output. Do not REMIND, do not advance state — wait for the next real message.</rule>
      <branch tag="[EXECUTE:DONE ...]">
        <action>Proceed to step 6 — Read the spec file and verify against S1–S9.</action>
      </branch>
      <branch tag="[EXECUTE:NEED_INPUT ...]">
        <action>Answer with windows-message to that wid, drawing from (a) the task's SCOPE/CONTEXT, (b) prior accepted specs in research-root, (c) files on disk. If still unanswerable, reply [SUPERVISOR:NARROW-SCOPE] with a reduced problem statement. Escalate to user ONLY for user-only knowledge.</action>
      </branch>
      <branch tag="[EXECUTE:FAILED ...]">
        <action>Read REASON. First attempt: kill and respawn with narrowed scope. If a second respawn on the same module FAILs with the same reason, escalate to user with the failure chain + a proposed pivot. NEVER silently retry the same prompt.</action>
      </branch>
      <branch tag="worker emitted spec content inline without a file= tag">
        <action>Reply via windows-message: [SUPERVISOR:REMIND] Use the file= response protocol. Save your spec to {research-root}/execute-&lt;N&gt;-&lt;slug&gt;.md (research-root resolved in step 0b) and reply with only [EXECUTE:DONE file=&lt;abs-path&gt;].</action>
        <action>Do not advance state; wait for the file-form reply.</action>
      </branch>
      <branch tag="no [EXECUTE:...] header AND not a stop-hook idle line">
        <action>Reply ONCE via windows-message: REMIND: respond only with [EXECUTE:NEED_INPUT|DONE|FAILED] headers (DONE must include file=&lt;abs-path&gt;).</action>
        <action>Do not advance state for that worker.</action>
      </branch>
    </step>

    <step n="5a" title="Continuous effectivity check">
      <condition>A spec has been accepted in step 6, AND other workers are still running or queued.</condition>
      <action>Before moving on, re-evaluate every running and queued worker against the new spec:
        - REFUTED: if the accepted spec reveals that a running worker's module is unnecessary or duplicated → send [SUPERVISOR:KILL]; remove the task entry from tasks-path and log the reason (leave wid gaps — never renumber).
        - NARROWED: if the accepted spec identifies constraints that tighten another worker's focus → send [SUPERVISOR:AMEND] with narrowed scope.
        - NEW-SURFACE: if the accepted spec reveals a new module not in the original plan → create context file, add to tasks.yaml, spawn immediately alongside remaining workers.</action>
      <when>Fire this check after EVERY accepted DONE. Do not skip.</when>
    </step>

    <step n="6" title="Verify spec quality — pushback catalogue S1–S9">
      <action>If the file= path cited in the DONE tag does not exist, reply [SUPERVISOR:REMIND] file= path does not exist — resave and re-tag, and wait.</action>
      <action>Call spec-validate MCP tool with the file= path. The tool checks S0 (Intent), S1 (Code Map), S2 (Implementation Plan), S3 (Test Plan), S4 (Acceptance Criteria), S7 (Boundaries), S8 (RFD/placeholders) automatically.</action>
      <action>After spec-validate, also check these gaps manually (they require judgment the tool cannot perform):</action>
      <gap id="S5">Dependencies not specified when the module clearly depends on others (check the plan's dependency graph)</gap>
      <gap id="S6">I/O Matrix missing when module has meaningful interfaces (APIs, CLI commands, message protocols, file formats) — if module has no I/O interfaces, this gap does not apply</gap>
      <gap id="S9">Modified files in Code Map lack current-state annotations (CURRENT/CHANGE/PRESERVE) — implementation worker needs to know what exists before changing it</gap>
      <note>ID collision: spec-validate can ALSO emit an "S9" gap, but with a different meaning — subjective validation gates (gate objectivity, fires only on Validation Rules / Investigation Config sections, which worker tech-specs lack). If the tool ever returns S9, push back using the tool's message text, not the manual S9 definition above.</note>
      <rule>Pushback at most 3x per worker. Each pushback MUST cite exactly one gap.</rule>
      <action>Pushback format: windows-message to that wid with [EXECUTE:PUSHBACK n=&lt;1|2|3&gt; gap=&lt;S1..S9&gt;]\n&lt;one-sentence specific ask tied to the gap&gt;\nUpdate the same .md file, then re-tag [EXECUTE:DONE file=&lt;same-path&gt;].</action>
      <check condition="spec-validate returns valid=true AND S5/S6/S9 manual checks pass">
        <action>Accept. Proceed to step 7.</action>
      </check>
      <check condition="3 pushbacks already sent to this worker">
        <action>Accept as-is. Log the unresolved gap(s) for the step 9 summary table. Proceed to step 7.</action>
      </check>
    </step>

    <step n="7" title="Kill window, update task state">
      <action>Mark the corresponding task as status=done in tasks-path (resolved in step 0b — NEVER the hardcoded top-level .tmux-cli/tasks.yaml in GOAL_MODE).</action>
      <action>Call windows-kill with windowId = the NAME (e.g. "execute-3"), not the @id.</action>
      <critical>NEVER kill PLAN_WID.</critical>
      <critical>If windows-kill returns "invalid window ID format: window IDs not allowed", you passed @N — retry with the name.</critical>
    </step>

    <step n="8" title="Findings-driven replan">
      <condition>An accepted spec materially changes the plan — reveals a new module, invalidates a queued module, or exposes a missed dependency.</condition>
      <action>Update the queue autonomously:
        - If a queued worker is now pointless, remove its task entry from tasks-path + log reason.
        - If a queued worker needs broader/narrower scope, rewrite its research-task context file.
        - If a new module emerged, create context file, add to tasks.yaml, and spawn.</action>
      <action>If new workers were spawned, loop back to step 5 (idle and route).</action>
      <action>If no changes needed, continue to check if all workers are done.</action>
    </step>

    <step n="8b" title="Coverage verification">
      <condition>All tasks status=done — either all workers completed (step 8 produced no new workers), or a direct jump from step 3c (full cache hit) / step 3d (SELF_SPEC accepted), or a re-entry from step 11b (audit replan — fresh coverage-pass budget; gates return to 11b's re-finalize, not step 9).</condition>
      <action>Re-read the original input ($ARGUMENTS — plan file or inline description).</action>
      <action>Extract all identifiable requirements, goals, or deliverables. Number them as a checklist.</action>
      <action>For each requirement, check whether at least one accepted spec's ## Intent addresses it. Build mapping: requirement → spec file(s).</action>
      <check condition="all requirements covered">
        <action>Log coverage map. Proceed to step 8c.</action>
      </check>
      <check condition="uncovered requirements exist AND coverage-pass &lt; 2">
        <action>For each gap: create research-task context file, add to tasks.yaml, spawn new spec worker.</action>
        <action>Loop back to step 5 (idle and route). After new workers complete, re-run step 8b.</action>
      </check>
      <check condition="uncovered requirements exist AND coverage-pass = 2">
        <action>Log remaining gaps for step 9 summary. Proceed to step 8c.</action>
      </check>
      <rule>Coverage verification runs at most 2 times per session to prevent loops.</rule>
    </step>

    <step n="8c" title="File-overlap detection">
      <condition>Coverage verification (step 8b) complete.</condition>
      <action>Read all accepted spec files. Extract file paths from "### Files to Create/Modify" sections.</action>
      <action>Build mapping: file_path → [spec1, spec2, ...]. Flag paths appearing in 2+ specs.</action>
      <check condition="no overlaps">
        <action>Proceed to step 8d.</action>
      </check>
      <check condition="overlaps found">
        <action>For each overlap, read both specs' Code Map and Implementation Plan to classify:
          - NON-CONFLICTING (different functions/sections) → add depends_on between tasks in tasks.yaml (earlier wid first). Log ordering.
          - CONFLICTING (same function/section) → flag for step 9 summary with recommendation (consolidate or re-spec one).
          - CONSOLIDATION-CANDIDATE (specs so coupled they should merge) → merge context files, remove redundant task, re-validate merged spec.</action>
      </check>
      <action>Proceed to step 8d.</action>
    </step>

    <step n="8d" title="Post-plan sanity check">
      <condition>File-overlap detection (step 8c) complete. All specs accepted.</condition>
      <action>Run three advisory sanity checks against the accepted specs. Findings are categorized as CRITICAL or INFO and fed into the step 9 summary.</action>

      <check id="1" title="Goal validation-rule alignment" condition="GOAL_MODE is true">
        <action>Read .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/goal.md. Extract the ## Validation Rules section.</action>
        <action>Parse file paths from grep/test/stat-style shell commands in each rule (e.g. `grep -q '...' path/to/file` → extract `path/to/file`). Skip rules with no explicit file path (e.g. `go build ./...`, shell globs, `./...` patterns).</action>
        <action>Collect all file paths from every accepted spec's ### Files to Create/Modify sections.</action>
        <action>Flag each validation-rule file path that does NOT appear in any spec's file list as a MISALIGNMENT warning (CRITICAL).</action>
        <action>If no misalignments: log "Check 1 passed — all validation-rule paths covered by specs".</action>
      </check>

      <check id="2" title="Code Map path existence">
        <action>For each accepted spec, extract file:line references from ## Code Map.</action>
        <action>For each reference, verify the file portion exists on disk (ignore line numbers — files may have shifted).</action>
        <action>Flag missing files as STALE_REF warnings (CRITICAL).</action>
        <action>If no stale refs: log "Check 2 passed — all Code Map paths exist on disk".</action>
      </check>

      <check id="3" title="Dependency consistency">
        <action>For each accepted spec, read ## Dependencies text.</action>
        <action>Compare against the corresponding task's depends_on array in tasks-path.</action>
        <action>Flag mismatches: spec declares "none" but task has depends_on entries, or spec lists dependencies but task has no depends_on (INFO).</action>
        <action>If consistent: log "Check 3 passed — spec dependencies match tasks.yaml depends_on".</action>
      </check>

      <branch condition="any CRITICAL findings AND AUTO_APPROVE is true">
        <action>Replan affected spec(s): for each spec with a CRITICAL finding, kill its old task entry in tasks-path, create a new research-task context file in research-root with the finding appended as a constraint, spawn a fresh spec worker via windows-spawn-worker, and loop back to step 5 (idle and route). Cap at 1 replan per spec to prevent infinite loops.</action>
      </branch>
      <branch condition="any findings AND AUTO_APPROVE is false">
        <action>Append all findings to the step 9 summary under a "Sanity Check" section. User decides whether to act in step 10.</action>
      </branch>
      <branch condition="no findings">
        <action>Log: "Sanity check passed — no misalignments".</action>
      </branch>
      <action>Proceed to step 9 (on a step 11b re-entry: return to step 11b's re-finalize action instead).</action>
    </step>

    <step n="9" title="All specs collected → present to user">
      <condition>All workers have completed (all tasks status=done, all windows killed).</condition>
      <check condition="AUTO_APPROVE is true">
        <action>Auto-approve mode enabled (plan.auto_approve=true in setting.yaml). Skipping interactive review.</action>
        <action>Log spec summary table (same as normal) for audit trail, but do NOT wait for user input.</action>
        <action>Proceed directly to step 11 (finalize).</action>
      </check>
      <action>Read all accepted spec files. Compile a summary table:</action>
      <format>
| # | Module | Spec File | Files to Create | Test Cases | Unresolved Gaps | Coverage |
|---|--------|-----------|-----------------|------------|-----------------|----------|
| 1 | ...    | {research-root}/execute-N-slug.md | N | M | none / S2 | R1,R3 |
      </format>
      <action>Print: Uncovered Requirements: [list] or none</action>
      <action>Print the dependency graph from the plan (if applicable), showing implementation order.</action>
      <action>Print file overlap report:</action>
      <format>
File Overlaps:
| File | Specs | Resolution |
|------|-------|------------|
(or "No file overlaps detected.")
      </format>
      <action>Print instructions:</action>
      <template>
Reply: **approve** | **edit &lt;N&gt;** | **add &lt;description&gt;** | **remove &lt;N&gt;** | **re-spec &lt;N&gt;** [feedback]
      </template>
      <rule>Do NOT use AskUserQuestion — print text and wait for user message.</rule>
    </step>

    <step n="10" title="User interaction loop">
      <check condition="AUTO_APPROVE is true">
        <action>Skip — already bypassed by step 9 auto-approve.</action>
      </check>
      <action>Wait for user message. Parse the command:</action>
      <branch command="approve">
        <action>Proceed to step 11 (finalize).</action>
      </branch>
      <branch command="edit &lt;N&gt;">
        <action>Print the full path to the Nth spec file. Tell user: "Edit the file and reply 'done' when finished."</action>
        <action>On user reply: re-read the spec file and return to step 9 (re-present summary).</action>
      </branch>
      <branch command="add &lt;description&gt;">
        <action>Create a new research-task context file for the described module.</action>
        <action>Add entry to tasks.yaml (next available execute-N wid).</action>
        <action>Spawn a new spec worker (step 4 for this one task).</action>
        <action>Return to step 5 for that worker, then back to step 9 when all workers done.</action>
      </branch>
      <branch command="remove &lt;N&gt;">
        <action>Remove the Nth module from tasks.yaml. Do NOT renumber existing wids — leave gaps.</action>
        <action>Return to step 9 (re-present updated summary).</action>
      </branch>
      <branch command="re-spec &lt;N&gt;">
        <action>Re-spawn a spec worker for the Nth module. If user included feedback after the number, include it as additional context in the worker's task message.</action>
        <action>Reset the task status to in_progress in tasks.yaml.</action>
        <action>Return to step 5 for that worker, then back to step 9 when all workers done.</action>
      </branch>
      <rule>Loop until user replies "approve".</rule>
      <rule>For unrecognized input, print the valid commands and wait again.</rule>
    </step>

    <step n="11" title="Finalize">
      <action>Convert accepted spec files into implementation tasks in tasks.yaml:</action>
      <format>
status: ready
cycle: 1
tasks:
  - name: "&lt;from spec ## Intent — concise module name&gt;"
    wid: "execute-N"
    status: pending
    context: "&lt;path to the accepted spec .md file&gt;"
    depends_on: ["execute-M"]  # from spec ## Dependencies, mapped to wids. Optional.
      </format>
      <action>Respect the dependency graph from the specs — use depends_on fields or order tasks by implementation wave (prerequisites first).</action>
      <action>Set the top-level status field in tasks-path to "ready".</action>
      <rule>Preserve any existing top-level `lane` key in tasks-path verbatim when rewriting (written by the step 3d solo-lane gate) — dropping it would silently disable the slim audit and the supervisor's solo read.</rule>
      <action condition="GOAL_MODE is true">Append a research-file index to .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/goal.md so the goal records its plan artifacts. Use a section titled "## Research Files" with two subsections grouped by category, using markdown links RELATIVE to the goal dir:

## Research Files

### Specs
- [&lt;module name&gt;](research/execute-&lt;N&gt;-&lt;slug&gt;.md)
- ... one per accepted spec file ...

### Context
- [&lt;module name&gt;](research/task-&lt;slug&gt;.md)
- ... one per research-task context file ...

If a "## Research Files" section already exists in goal.md (re-plan), REPLACE that section in place rather than appending a duplicate. List every generated file in its category (all files, grouped). Omit a subsection if it has no files.</action>
      <action>Print summary:</action>
      <template>
Plan finalized: N implementation tasks ready in {tasks-path}
Research dir: {research-root} (resolved in step 0b)

Run `/tmux:supervisor` to execute the plan.
      </template>
      <action>Proceed to step 11a (blind audit gate).</action>
    </step>

    <step n="11a" title="Blind audit gate">
      <condition>AUDIT_ENABLED is true OR SELF_SPEC is true. SELF_SPEC FORCES this gate: the supervisor authored the spec itself, so the audit sub-agent is the only independent review — when overriding supervisor.unplanned_audit=false, log "Audit forced: SELF_SPEC plan (author == verifier)". If neither flag is set, skip directly to step 11c.</condition>
      <action>First entry only (AUDIT_PASS not yet set): initialize AUDIT_PASS = 1 and clean prior verdict files — in GOAL_MODE `rm -f .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/research/plan-audit-*.md .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/research/plan-approval.md`; in standalone `rm -f docs/architecture/plan-audit-*.md docs/architecture/plan-approval.md`. On loop-backs from step 11b do NEITHER — AUDIT_PASS keeps its incremented value and earlier passes' findings files survive as the ledger the next pass re-verifies.</action>
      <action>Resolve VERDICT_DIR: {research-root} in GOAL_MODE; docs/architecture/ in standalone (create if absent — the daemon's RequirePlanApproval gate looks for docs/architecture/plan-approval.md).</action>
      <action>Read the top-level `lane` key from tasks-path BEFORE composing the sub-agent prompt. The sub-agent stays blind either way — it never learns the lane; it only receives the instruction set composed below.</action>
      <branch condition="top-level lane == solo in tasks-path" title="solo-lane slim audit">
        <action>Compose the sub-agent prompt exactly as specified below with ONE substitution: keep the "Daemon's-eye validate evaluation" bullet verbatim and extend it with the explicit non-vacuity instruction — "a validate command that already passes at baseline (e.g. grepping a token that exists before the change) is a finding" — and score against ONLY dimensions (1) validate-executability and (2) dependency-correctness, dropping dimensions 3–8 from the prompt. Everything else is UNCHANGED: the severity-weighted scoring formula, the PASS rule (score &gt;= 90 AND zero open SEV-1/SEV-2), the never-weaken guardrail, blind isolation, the one-file write, and the verdict-line contract.</action>
      </branch>
      <branch condition="lane key absent or any value other than solo">
        <action>Compose the full 8-dimension prompt below unchanged — byte-identical to a plan with no lane key.</action>
      </branch>
      <action>Run the audit as ONE serial Claude-native sub-agent via the Agent tool. Do NOT create a tmux window, do NOT use windows-send or windows-message — the sub-agent runs in-process and returns its result synchronously. It starts with a FRESH context containing none of this planning conversation; that isolation is what makes the audit blind. Compose a fully self-contained prompt instructing it to:
        - Read ONLY on-disk artifacts, scoped to THIS plan: .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/goal.md and this goal's entry in goals.yaml (GOAL_MODE only), tasks-path, every spec and context file in {research-root}, prior findings files {VERDICT_DIR}/plan-audit-*.md (present on pass 2+), and AGENTS.md or CLAUDE.md for project conventions. It must never see planner conversation state.
        - Daemon's-eye validate evaluation: every validate command is concrete and runnable, a bare command (no shell wrappers or chains), and depends_on edges are valid — no cycles, no dangling references.
        - Score against the 8-dimension checklist — exactly these, no inventions: (1) validate-executability, (2) dependency-correctness, (3) runtime-state-gating, (4) host-container-split, (5) objective-acceptance, (6) spec-discovery-consistency, (7) environment-prerequisites, (8) scope-sanity.
        - Severity-weighted scoring: start at 100; deduct SEV-1 −25 (blocks execution or produces wrong results), SEV-2 −15 (retry loops, cascading failures, silent corruption), SEV-3 −8 (unclear spec likely to waste retries), SEV-4 −3 (style/convention violation); floor at 0. PASS requires score >= 90 AND zero open SEV-1/SEV-2 findings.
        - Guardrail: reach 90% by fixing the plan, never by weakening validate/acceptance — the auditor reports defects; it must never water down validate commands or acceptance criteria to lift the score.
        - On pass 2+: re-verify every RESOLVED claim from prior findings files against the current artifacts BEFORE scoring; a regressed RESOLVED re-opens at its original severity.
        - Write EXACTLY ONE file and nothing else: on pass {VERDICT_DIR}/plan-approval.md (score, timestamp, per-dimension summary); on fail {VERDICT_DIR}/plan-audit-{AUDIT_PASS}.md (score, findings table with severity/dimension/file:line, remediation priority). The audit is otherwise strictly read-only — never modify goals, specs, tasks.yaml, or code.
        - End its final message with exactly one verdict line: AUDIT:PASS score={score} or AUDIT:FAIL score={score} file={abs-path-to-findings-file}.</action>
      <action>Parse the verdict line from the sub-agent's returned final message. There is no window to poll and no timeout to manage.</action>
      <check condition="the Agent call errors OR no parsable AUDIT verdict line in the final message OR AUDIT:FAIL cites a file= that does not exist on disk">
        <action>Retry the sub-agent ONCE with the same prompt. If the retry fails the same way, log "Audit sub-agent failed twice — accepting plan without audit (fail-open)" and treat as audit-pass.</action>
      </check>
      <branch condition="verdict is AUDIT:PASS (or fail-open after two sub-agent failures)">
        <action>Audit passed. Write .tmux-cli/audit-done guard file. Proceed to step 11c.</action>
      </branch>
      <branch condition="verdict is AUDIT:FAIL with an existing file= path">
        <action>Audit failed (pass AUDIT_PASS). Store AUDIT_FAIL_FILE = the file= path from the verdict line. Proceed to step 11b.</action>
      </branch>
    </step>

    <step n="11b" title="Audit replan loop">
      <check condition="AUDIT_PASS >= 3">
        <action>Print escalation: "Plan audit failed after 3 passes. Escalating to human review. See the findings file from the last AUDIT:FAIL verdict."</action>
        <action>STOP — do NOT auto-execute.</action>
      </check>
      <action>Read the findings file at the path stored in AUDIT_FAIL_FILE (from the sub-agent's AUDIT:FAIL verdict line).</action>
      <action>Parse findings: select the replan tier — the most severe severity level that has any findings in the table. SEV-1/SEV-2 (together) when any exist; else SEV-3 (the audit failed on accumulated score with zero severe findings); else SEV-4 as last resort (a score-fail on style nits alone — replanning them beats re-auditing identical artifacts, burning all 3 passes, and parking an autonomous run for a human). Collect every finding in the selected tier with the file:line references its findings-table row cites. A failing audit MUST yield a non-empty replan set — an AUDIT:FAIL with an empty findings table is a malformed verdict (treat per the step 11a malformed-verdict retry).</action>
      <action>Map findings → affected specs via the cited file paths: a finding citing a spec or context file in {research-root} affects that task directly; a finding citing tasks-path or a source file maps to the task(s) whose spec's Code Map / Files to Create/Modify covers it.</action>
      <action>For each affected spec: set task status back to pending in tasks-path. Append ## Audit Feedback (Pass {AUDIT_PASS}) section to the spec's context file containing ALL findings that cite this spec — every severity, not only the selected tier — so one replan round clears the spec's full deduction load instead of leaving sub-tier findings to sink the next pass's score.</action>
      <action>Respawn spec workers for affected tasks via windows-spawn-worker (same flow as step 4).</action>
      <rule condition="SELF_SPEC is true">Audit-fail replans DISPATCH a real worker even on a single-task plan — never self-spec the same module twice. The self-written spec just failed independent review; the replan needs independent eyes. Pass the audit findings via the context file as usual.</rule>
      <action>Route through steps 5–7 (idle/route, S1–S9 verify, kill) until all replanned specs accepted.</action>
      <action>After all replanned specs accepted: route through steps 8b (coverage verification) → 8c (file-overlap detection) → 8d (post-plan sanity) exactly as on the first pass BEFORE re-finalizing — log the 8b coverage map and the 8c file-overlap report a second time. On this 11b re-entry the gates RETURN HERE when complete (never fall through to step 9), and 8b gets a FRESH coverage-pass budget for each audit replan round (the loop is already bounded by AUDIT_PASS).</action>
      <action>Re-finalize: rewrite tasks-path with status: ready, preserving any top-level `lane` key (same rule as step 11), AND re-run step 11's "## Research Files" replace-in-place on goal.md (GOAL_MODE) so replacement spec filenames (new execute-N slugs) are indexed and stale entries dropped.</action>
      <action>Increment AUDIT_PASS. Loop back to step 11a and launch a FRESH audit sub-agent — skip the first-entry initialization/cleanup so prior findings files survive as the re-verification ledger.</action>
    </step>

    <step n="11c" title="Auto-execute handoff">
      <action>Write .tmux-cli/audit-done guard file (idempotent — may already exist from step 11a pass).</action>
      <check condition="AUTO_EXECUTE is true">
        <action>Auto-execute mode enabled (plan.auto_execute=true in setting.yaml). Invoking supervisor automatically.</action>
        <action>Write guard file .tmux-cli/auto-execute-guard (prevents the Stop hook from also restarting the supervisor — without this, both auto-execute AND the Stop hook would send /tmux:supervisor, causing a double invocation).</action>
        <action>Send /clear to PLAN_WID via windows-send.</action>
        <action condition="GOAL_MODE is true">Send `/tmux:supervisor {GOAL_ID}` to PLAN_WID via windows-send — {GOAL_ID} already carries the goal- prefix (e.g. goal-046), so this expands to `/tmux:supervisor goal-046`. Ship the goal id (resolved in step 0b) as a leading token so the fresh supervisor binds to THIS goal authoritatively (its step 0b consumes the goal-{ns} argument) and never re-derives it from the last-writer-wins global .tmux-cli/taskvisor-current-goal marker.</action>
        <action condition="GOAL_MODE is false">Send `/tmux:supervisor .tmux-cli/tasks.yaml` to PLAN_WID via windows-send (standalone — no goal id to ship).</action>
        <action>STOP — a fresh supervisor instance takes over with the finalized tasks.yaml.</action>
      </check>
      <action>STOP. The supervisor takes over from here.</action>
    </step>
  </flow>

  <execution-rules>
    <rule>windows-spawn-worker: single atomic call per worker — with custom deliverable parameter for spec format</rule>
    <rule>NEVER assemble spawn steps manually — always use windows-spawn-worker</rule>
    <rule>windows-message: all planning supervisor↔worker communication (answers, pushbacks, reminders, amends, kills)</rule>
    <rule>windows-kill: only on accepted spec or terminal FAILED; never on PLAN_WID; pass window NAME</rule>
    <rule>Always Read the file cited in a DONE before applying the S1–S9 catalogue; never rely on inline body</rule>
    <rule>If a worker sends DONE without file=, REMIND once; do not accept inline-body DONE</rule>
    <rule>Every tasks.yaml reference in this flow means tasks-path (resolved in step 0b) — per-goal .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/tasks.yaml in GOAL_MODE, top-level .tmux-cli/tasks.yaml in standalone</rule>
    <rule>tasks.yaml status transitions: missing → planning (step 3b) → ready (step 11 only, after user approval)</rule>
    <rule>Research-task context files are created BEFORE tasks.yaml references them</rule>
    <rule>Spec files are created BY workers, verified BY the planning supervisor against S1–S9 — EXCEPT under SELF_SPEC (step 3d, exactly 1 pending task), where the supervisor writes the spec inline through the same spec-validate + S5/S6/S9 gates (max 3 self-revision rounds) and the blind audit is forced</rule>
    <rule>Step 3d dispatch gate: exactly 1 pending task → SELF_SPEC inline (no spawn); 2+ pending tasks → step 4 dispatch with maximum parallelism</rule>
    <rule>All scope and context detail lives in the context .md file — tasks.yaml entries are lean (name, wid, status, context path, depends_on). The context file IS the spec — ensure it is complete and self-contained for /tmux:supervisor consumption</rule>
    <rule>The deliverable parameter on windows-spawn-worker overrides the standard FINDINGS/RISKS/RECOMMENDATION/FILES format with the spec template</rule>
    <rule>windows-send: used ONLY for auto-execute self-restart commands to PLAN_WID in step 11 (/clear, /tmux:supervisor)</rule>
  </execution-rules>

  <stop-conditions>
    <rule>STOP and present specs to user (step 9) ONLY when:
      - All spec workers completed AND findings-driven replan produced no new workers AND coverage verification (step 8b) satisfied or exhausted.
      - User approval phase: steps 9–10 are interactive; the user controls the pace.</rule>
    <rule>Escalate to user during spec-writing ONLY when:
      - Zero executable workers constructable from input.
      - 2 consecutive FAILEDs on the same module after narrowing.
      - User-only knowledge required (credentials, intent, out-of-band facts).
      - Explicit user interrupt.</rule>
    <not-stop>Resolve autonomously per &lt;autonomy-policy&gt;:
      - "Multiple valid decompositions" → pick per &lt;ranking&gt;.
      - "Worker recommended adjusting another module's scope" → amend and continue.
      - "Accepted spec reveals a new module" → add context file, spawn worker, continue.
      - "Worker spec contradicts a prior spec" → record; most-recent-with-evidence wins.</not-stop>
  </stop-conditions>

  <llm final="true">
    <critical-rules>
      • NEVER implement code — produce specs only; implementation is /tmux:supervisor's job
      • NEVER set status to "ready" before user approves (step 11 only) — UNLESS AUTO_APPROVE is true
      • NEVER skip steps 9–10 (user review is mandatory, not optional) — UNLESS AUTO_APPROVE is true
      • DO NOT use sleep; idle is the trigger
      • DO NOT kill PLAN_WID
      • DO NOT advance state on untagged non-idle output — REMIND once and keep waiting
      • DO NOT pass @N to windows-kill — use the window NAME
      • DO NOT accept DONE without file=&lt;abs-path&gt; — REMIND to use file-only protocol
      • DO NOT spawn any worker (step 4) before tasks.yaml is written and verified (step 3b) — blocking gate, no exceptions
      • NEVER spawn a spec worker for a single pending task — the step 3d dispatch gate self-specs it inline through the same validation gates; spawning starts at 2+ pending tasks. SOLE EXCEPTION: step 11b audit-fail replans dispatch a real worker (never self-spec the same module twice)
      • NEVER skip the blind audit (step 11a) when SELF_SPEC is true — it is the only independent review of a self-written spec, regardless of supervisor.unplanned_audit
      • DO NOT serialize spec-writing for implementation dependencies — specs are written by reading source, not by depending on other implementations
      • ALWAYS create research-task context files before writing tasks.yaml entries that reference them
      • ALWAYS verify spec quality against S1–S9 before accepting a worker's DONE
      • ALWAYS use windows-spawn-worker with the custom deliverable parameter — never use the default FINDINGS format for spec workers
      • DO NOT use AskUserQuestion — all user interaction via text output and waiting for messages
      • NEVER use batch Bash scripts (grep loops, for-each shell commands) to validate or process specs — ALWAYS use the proper flow: spec-validate MCP tool per file, workers for spec writing. Batch shortcuts bypass quality gates. Token cost is irrelevant — precision is the goal.
      • NEVER merge, squash, or recompose a user-approved task decomposition — preserve exact count and boundaries. Add detail per task, never change the structure the user approved.
    </critical-rules>
  </llm>
</task>
