<task id="supervisor" name="Parallel /tmux:execute supervisor">
  <objective>Spawn N parallel /tmux:execute workers via tmux-cli with collision-safe window names. Workers save a full .md report and reply with a filepath-only DONE tag; supervisor Reads the file, verifies it against the pushback catalogue, pushes back up to 3x on gaps, and kills windows on acceptance.</objective>

  <input>
    <arg name="$ARGUMENTS">Path to a task file OR inline task description. Task-file format is free-form; the supervisor reads it, derives fan-out shape per &lt;ranking&gt;, and proceeds.</arg>
    <arg name="domain-hint" optional="true">Optional domain hint for the ranking heuristic (e.g. "security-research", "codebase-audit", "docs-pass"). Defaults to the research-root's inferred domain.</arg>
  </input>

  <output>
    <primary>Inline user-facing synthesis text: accepted findings merged, overlaps/conflicts stated explicitly, queue-change log included (per step 8a).</primary>
    <secondary optional="true">Session-synthesis .md written to research-root (name: `NN_session-&lt;topic&gt;.md`), citing each per-worker file.</secondary>
  </output>

  <requirements critical="true">
    <mcp>tmux-cli MCP server REQUIRED</mcp>
    <directory>research-root is resolved in step 0b (relative to project working directory; create if absent):
      • Standalone (no active goal): .tmux-cli/research/{y-m-d-hh}/ — {y-m-d-hh} expands to current timestamp, e.g. 2026-05-11-20.
      • Goal mode (GOAL_ID resolved window-name-first in step 0b: supervisor-{ns} → goal-{ns}; the .tmux-cli/taskvisor-current-goal marker only for the bare `supervisor` window): .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/research/ — NO timestamp subfolder.</directory>
    <constraint>The fan-out tasks.yaml path is resolved once in step 0b as `tasks-path`: goal-scoped (.tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/tasks.yaml) in GOAL_MODE, else the top-level .tmux-cli/tasks.yaml. In goal mode the taskvisor daemon reads the per-goal file (retry: exists/reset/inject). This is DISTINCT from plan.xml's top-level planning-queue (the /tmux:plan handoff), which is never moved. Only per-worker report and research-task context .md files live under research-root; tasks-path holds the fan-out and its context: fields point at the (possibly goal-scoped) files.</constraint>
  </requirements>

  <glossary>
    <term name="SUPERVISOR_WID">Name of the supervisor's tmux window (e.g. "supervisor"). Stable for whole session.</term>
    <term name="SELF_WID">Name of a worker's tmux window (e.g. "execute-7"). Each worker gets unique N.</term>
    <term name="research-root">Primary directory where per-worker .md reports and research-task context files are saved. Resolved in step 0b: .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/research/ when a goal is active (no timestamp), else .tmux-cli/research/{y-m-d-hh}/ (timestamped). Defined in &lt;requirements&gt; / step 0b.</term>
    <term name="GOAL_MODE">Internal flag set true in step 0b when the supervisor's OWN window name is namespaced (supervisor-{ns}, daemon dispatch at MaxGoals&gt;1) or, for the bare `supervisor` window, when .tmux-cli/taskvisor-current-goal exists and is non-empty. In goal mode research-root is goal-scoped (.tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/research/) and step 9b appends a research-file index to the goal's goal.md.</term>
    <term name="GOAL_ID">The goal identifier resolved in step 0b when GOAL_MODE is true: derived from the supervisor's namespaced window name (supervisor-{ns} → goal-{ns}, mirroring parseGoalBinding in internal/mcp/tools.go), else read (trimmed) from .tmux-cli/taskvisor-current-goal for the bare `supervisor` window. Names the goal folder under .tmux-cli/goals/.</term>
    <term name="tasks-path">Path to the supervisor's fan-out tasks.yaml, resolved in step 0b: .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/tasks.yaml in GOAL_MODE (read by the taskvisor daemon on retry), else the top-level .tmux-cli/tasks.yaml. Every fan-out read/write/archive/status-flip in this flow uses tasks-path. DISTINCT from plan.xml's top-level planning-queue.</term>
    <term name="subtask label">One-line human-readable description of what a worker is doing (e.g. "implement setup config parser").</term>
    <term name="sup=">Supervisor's window name in tag messages.</term>
    <term name="wid=">Worker's window name in tag messages.</term>
    <term name="ranking heuristic">Priority ordering used for auto fan-out; see &lt;ranking&gt; inside step 3.</term>
    <term name="autonomy">Supervisor operates without user confirmation after initial invocation; see &lt;autonomy-policy&gt;.</term>
    <term name="pushback catalogue">The G1–G5 taxonomy in step 6 used to gate DONE acceptance.</term>
    <term name="PRE_PLANNED">Internal flag set when tasks.yaml was created by /tmux:plan (detected in step 1c). Causes steps 3 and 3b to skip fan-out planning.</term>
  </glossary>

  <message-tags>
    <note>All supervisor↔worker communication is tagged. Use tags verbatim; semantics below are the source of truth.</note>
    <tag name="[EXECUTE:DONE wid=... sup=... file=&lt;abs-path&gt;]" from="worker">Worker reports completion. Body carries NO inline findings — the .md at file= IS the report.</tag>
    <tag name="[EXECUTE:NEED_INPUT wid=... sup=... &lt;short reason&gt;]" from="worker">Worker cannot proceed without a fact. Reason ≤ 200 chars inline. Supervisor answers via windows-message to that wid, or replies [SUPERVISOR:NARROW-SCOPE].</tag>
    <tag name="[EXECUTE:FAILED wid=... sup=... reason=&lt;short&gt;]" from="worker">Worker hit a terminal failure. Reason ≤ 200 chars inline. Supervisor respawns with narrowed scope (first attempt) or escalates (second).</tag>
    <tag name="[EXECUTE:ESCALATE wid=... sup=... need=&lt;one-line buildable prerequisite&gt;]" from="worker">Worker is blocked by a prerequisite that is OUT of this goal's scope (a separate goal must be built first). Distinct from FAILED (in-scope blocker → implementer retry) and NEED_INPUT (missing fact). Supervisor records a goal-scoped escalation marker (escalation.md), suppresses the code-retry, and lets the validator relay it to generation — it does NOT respawn the same scope. Routed per step 5's ESCALATE branch (cap 2/goal). need= MUST be a concrete buildable prerequisite; contentless need= is REMINDed, not relayed.</tag>
    <tag name="[SUPERVISOR:REMIND &lt;what to do&gt;]" from="supervisor">Supervisor reminds worker of protocol (e.g. file-only DONE). Does not advance state.</tag>
    <tag name="[EXECUTE:PUSHBACK n=&lt;1|2|3&gt; gap=&lt;G1..G5&gt;]" from="supervisor">Supervisor requests a DELIVERABLE fix per pushback catalogue. Worker updates the SAME .md file and re-tags DONE.</tag>
    <tag name="[SUPERVISOR:AMEND &lt;new scope&gt;]" from="supervisor">Supervisor amends a running worker's scope mid-run. Worker applies to current task.</tag>
    <tag name="[SUPERVISOR:AMEND-PROTOCOL &lt;new rule&gt;]" from="supervisor">Supervisor amends the response protocol mid-run (e.g. new save-path rule).</tag>
    <tag name="[SUPERVISOR:KILL]" from="supervisor">Supervisor instructs worker to exit cleanly because its scope is now pointless (per step 5a). Worker ACKs then exits.</tag>
    <tag name="[SUPERVISOR:NARROW-SCOPE &lt;reduced problem&gt;]" from="supervisor">Supervisor narrows a NEED_INPUT-blocked worker's scope instead of escalating to user.</tag>
  </message-tags>

  <escalation-routing>
    <note>How an [EXECUTE:ESCALATE ...] from a worker becomes a re-planning bounce. Source of truth for step 5's ESCALATE branch.</note>
    <why>The supervisor cannot re-plan directly: a SupervisorSignal carries only {source,status,timestamp} and its status is stored but never routed to generation; the SOLE route to bounceToGeneration is a validator's ValidatorSignal with verdict=blocked + owner=planner. So the supervisor records a goal-scoped marker and lets the next validation cycle relay it. The supervisor also must NOT call goal-create (it races the daemon on goals.yaml) — generation owns that.</why>
    <marker-file>.tmux-cli/goals/&lt;GOAL_ID&gt;/escalation.md — supervisor-written, validator-read (validate.xml/investigate.xml), generation-read. Idempotent across cycles: increment escalation_count, append entries; generation supersedes/clears consumed entries when it creates the prerequisite goal.</marker-file>
    <schema>
## Escalations
escalation_count: &lt;N&gt;
- need: "&lt;one-line buildable prerequisite&gt;"
  from: execute-&lt;N&gt;  cycle: &lt;C&gt;
    </schema>
    <cap>Cap escalations at 2 per goal (≤ MaxSpecRetries). This is a supervisor-side guard against many escalations within one implementation cycle; the daemon's bounceToGeneration hard-halt at SpecRetries=0 is the authoritative ceiling. Beyond the cap the supervisor stops relaying and the goal takes its normal terminal path (no infinite re-plan loop).</cap>
    <relayed-finding>The validator MUST emit the relayed finding as status=blocked, owner=planner, failure_class=spec-defect with a NON-CONTENTLESS detail+correction (e.g. correction="Create prerequisite goal: &lt;need&gt;"). HasSubstantiveSpecDefect rejects a finding whose detail AND correction are both contentless — that would mis-route to ValidationRetries instead of generation. That is why step 5 rejects a contentless need= up front.</relayed-finding>
  </escalation-routing>

  <autonomy-policy>
    <rule>Supervisor operates AUTONOMOUSLY after the initial /supervisor invocation. The initial delegation authorizes the entire chain until a &lt;stop-conditions&gt; rule fires.</rule>
    <rule>Do NOT ask the user to: pick between options, sequence workers, approve continuation, confirm a findings-driven replan, amend a running worker, or spawn a new follow-up.</rule>
    <rule>For ambiguity: pick the highest-yield interpretation per &lt;ranking&gt; and record the chosen rationale in the step-9 synthesis so the user can redirect.</rule>
    <rule>Escalate to user ONLY at one of the two defined exits: (a) zero executable workers can be constructed from input, OR (b) a &lt;stop-conditions&gt; rule fires.</rule>
    <rule>Decision-resolution policy (quality-in-scope): a worker decision/verdict/correction presenting RESOLVABLE options (a technical/architectural fork, a waiver-vs-quality choice) is auto-resolved — answer the worker with the highest-quality option that does NOT expand the goal's scope (real domain types over asserted strings, no waivers, no shortcuts, no new tech-debt), plus a one-line rationale. Consistent with the user-only-knowledge escalation below: bounce to the user ONLY for credentials, intent, or out-of-band facts no file-reading can supply; a purely technical/architectural choice is NEVER user-only.</rule>
    <rule>Synthesis output (§9) is NOT a stop gate — writing a session-synthesis .md is routine. After writing it, re-run &lt;step n="8a"&gt; replan against its own contents; any "proposed next wave" / "queue changes" / "follow-up workers" / "wave N+1" sections in the synthesis are executable-queue entries, spawn them per §3 fan-out.</rule>
    <rule>Self-imposed stage gates (plan documents saying "Stage 2 after Stage 1", "wave 6 after wave 5", "deferred to next session", numbered-wave boundaries) are ORGANIZATIONAL, not authorizational. The initial /supervisor invocation authorizes the entire chain until a real &lt;stop-conditions&gt; fires. Do NOT treat a stage gate you wrote yourself as a user-imposed pause.</rule>
  </autonomy-policy>

  <llm critical="true">
    <mandate>NEVER bypass the supervisor protocol. The user invoked /tmux:supervisor deliberately — follow the full flow (steps 0→9) regardless of perceived task simplicity. "Too simple for workers" is NOT a valid reason to skip. Even a single-worker linear task goes through fan-out, tasks.yaml, spawn, poll, accept, synthesize.</mandate>
    <mandate>Execute steps ONE BY ONE in EXACT ORDER</mandate>
    <mandate>Create TODO list for tracking spawned workers (SELF_WID + subtask label)</mandate>
    <mandate>Operate per &lt;autonomy-policy&gt; — do not ask the user outside the two defined exits.</mandate>
    <mandate>NEVER spawn a worker before tasks.yaml is written and verified (step 3b gate)</mandate>
    <mandate>NEVER call /worker:execute — use /tmux:execute which is the correct skill name</mandate>
    <mandate>NEVER use sleep — idle is the trigger for incoming windows-message</mandate>
    <mandate>NEVER kill your own SUPERVISOR_WID</mandate>
    <mandate>windows-kill takes the window NAME (e.g. "execute-3"), not an @id. windows-send accepts @N; kill does not.</mandate>
    <mandate>When PRE_PLANNED is true, do NOT re-derive fan-out — trust the plan. Only verify context files exist (step 3b) and spawn (step 4).</mandate>
    <mandate>Resolve research-root AND tasks-path in step 0b before any worker spawn — every supervisor-created context file and worker report save path uses research-root (goal-scoped in GOAL_MODE, timestamped otherwise); every fan-out tasks.yaml read/write/archive/status-flip uses tasks-path (goal-scoped in GOAL_MODE, else top-level). PRE_PLANNED context: paths from /tmux:plan are NOT overridden.</mandate>
  </llm>

  <flow>
    <step n="0" title="Clean slate">
      <action>Remove .tmux-cli/audit-done guard file if it exists (allows the unplanned-audit hook to fire at the end of this cycle).</action>
      <action>Remove .tmux-cli/auto-execute-guard if it exists (consumed by the Stop hook to prevent double-invocation after plan auto-execute).</action>
      <action>Resolve the fan-out file path the same way step 0b will (GOAL_MODE → .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/tasks.yaml with GOAL_ID derived window-name-first per step 0b — supervisor-{ns} → goal-{ns}; the .tmux-cli/taskvisor-current-goal marker only for the bare `supervisor` window — else .tmux-cli/tasks.yaml) — this is tasks-path. If tasks-path exists and is NOT a continuation cycle, set its top-level status field to "planning" — EXCEPTION: when $ARGUMENTS leads with a goal-{ns} token (daemon dispatchRetry or /tmux:plan auto-execute handoff), do NOT flip the status. The per-goal tasks-path was finalized (status: ready) by the planner or reset by the daemon's resetTaskStatuses precisely so step 1c consumes it as PRE_PLANNED — flipping it to "planning" would mask the handoff and re-plan an already-planned goal. If it doesn't exist yet, the status will be set when tasks-path is first created in step 3.</action>
    </step>

    <step n="0b" title="Resolve research-root">
      <action>Read the FIRST whitespace-delimited token of $ARGUMENTS. If it matches ^goal-\d+$ it is an AUTHORITATIVE goal id handed over by the taskvisor daemon (dispatchRetry sends `/tmux:supervisor goal-{ns}`) or the /tmux:plan auto-execute handoff. Call it ARG_GOAL_ID (empty when no such leading token is present).</action>
      <branch condition="ARG_GOAL_ID is set (leading $ARGUMENTS token matches goal-{ns})">
        <action>GOAL mode (argument binding — HIGHEST PRECEDENCE for GOAL_ID, above both window-name derivation and the global marker). Set GOAL_ID = ARG_GOAL_ID. This is the AUTHORITATIVE goal id: the daemon shipped it explicitly BECAUSE the global .tmux-cli/taskvisor-current-goal marker is last-writer-wins under concurrent dispatch and may name ANOTHER goal — do NOT read that marker and do NOT re-derive GOAL_ID from the window name. Set research-root = .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/research/ (NO timestamp). Set tasks-path = .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/tasks.yaml (the per-goal fan-out file the daemon reads on retry). Create the goal dir / research-root if absent. Set internal flag GOAL_MODE=true.</action>
        <action>Determine SUPERVISOR_WID from your REAL window name — NOT synthesized from the goal id: run `tmux display-message -p '#W'` via Bash and use the result VERBATIM. It is supervisor-{ns} at MaxGoals&gt;1 (which parseGoalBinding maps back to {GOAL_ID}, so worker routing and GOAL_ID agree) but the BARE `supervisor` at MaxGoals=1 — never invent supervisor-{ns} when the real window is bare, or worker [EXECUTE:DONE] replies route to a non-existent window. Pass this exact SUPERVISOR_WID as the supervisorWid argument to EVERY windows-spawn-worker call so the worker prefix, report path, and reply target bind correctly even when the MCP server's own resolveSelfWindowName returns empty. Log: "Goal mode (argument binding): GOAL_ID={GOAL_ID}, SUPERVISOR_WID=&lt;real window name&gt;, research-root=.tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/research/, tasks-path=.tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/tasks.yaml".</action>
      </branch>
      <branch condition="ARG_GOAL_ID is NOT set (no leading goal-{ns} token in $ARGUMENTS — interactive /tmux:supervisor, or a plain task-file/inline arg)">
      <action>Determine your OWN window name first: run `tmux display-message -p '#W'` via Bash. Call the result SELF_NAME.</action>
      <branch condition="SELF_NAME is namespaced: supervisor-{ns} where {ns} is all digits (daemon dispatch at MaxGoals&gt;1)">
        <action>GOAL mode (window-name binding). Derive GOAL_ID = goal-{ns} from SELF_NAME (e.g. supervisor-020 → goal-020) — the same namespaced-name form parseGoalBinding (internal/mcp/tools.go) uses for MCP research-root routing, so MCP routing and this GOAL_ID always agree. Do NOT read .tmux-cli/taskvisor-current-goal here: the daemon writes that marker GLOBALLY on every dispatch, so under concurrent dispatch it is last-writer-wins and may name ANOTHER goal — your own window name is the only per-goal-safe source. Set research-root = .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/research/ (NO timestamp). Set tasks-path = .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/tasks.yaml (the per-goal fan-out file the daemon reads on retry). Create the goal dir / research-root if absent. Set internal flag GOAL_MODE=true. Log: "Goal mode (window-name binding): GOAL_ID={GOAL_ID}, research-root=.tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/research/, tasks-path=.tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/tasks.yaml".</action>
      </branch>
      <branch condition="SELF_NAME is the bare `supervisor` (MaxGoals=1) or any other non-namespaced name">
        <action>Check whether .tmux-cli/taskvisor-current-goal exists and is non-empty.</action>
        <branch condition="exists and non-empty">
          <action>GOAL mode. Read GOAL_ID from the file (trim whitespace). Set research-root = .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/research/ (NO timestamp). Set tasks-path = .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/tasks.yaml (the per-goal fan-out file the daemon reads on retry). Create the goal dir / research-root if absent. Set internal flag GOAL_MODE=true. Log: "Goal mode: GOAL_ID={GOAL_ID}, research-root=.tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/research/, tasks-path=.tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/tasks.yaml".</action>
        </branch>
        <branch condition="absent or empty">
          <action>STANDALONE mode. Set research-root = .tmux-cli/research/{y-m-d-hh}/ ({y-m-d-hh} = current timestamp). Set tasks-path = .tmux-cli/tasks.yaml. Create research-root if absent. Set internal flag GOAL_MODE=false. Log: "Standalone mode: research-root=.tmux-cli/research/{y-m-d-hh}/, tasks-path=.tmux-cli/tasks.yaml".</action>
        </branch>
      </branch>
      </branch>
      <rule>Every later reference to research-root AND tasks-path in this flow uses the values resolved here. tasks-path is the fan-out file — goal-scoped in GOAL_MODE, top-level otherwise — and is DISTINCT from plan.xml's top-level planning-queue (which is never moved).</rule>
      <rule>PRE_PLANNED tasks already carry resolved context: paths written by /tmux:plan — step 0b does NOT override those. It governs only the paths the supervisor itself creates: its own fan-out context files (step 3) and worker report save paths (steps 5/task-message).</rule>
    </step>

    <step n="1" title="MCP precondition">
      <action>Call windows-list</action>
      <check condition="tmux-cli not available">
        <action>Print exactly: ERROR: tmux-cli MCP required but not available — enable it and retry.</action>
        <action>STOP. Do not create any windows.</action>
      </check>
    </step>

    <step n="1b" title="Read project context">
      <action>Check if AGENTS.md exists in the project root. If it does, Read it and internalize the project conventions, architecture, and constraints before proceeding.</action>
      <action>If AGENTS.md does not exist, check for CLAUDE.md instead. Read whichever is found first.</action>
      <action>If neither exists, proceed without project context.</action>
      <rule>This context MUST inform your fan-out decisions, task scoping, and worker instructions throughout the session.</rule>
    </step>

    <step n="1c" title="Tasks gate">
      <note>This gate operates on tasks-path (resolved in step 0b): the per-goal fan-out file in GOAL_MODE, the top-level planning-queue in standalone. PRE_PLANNED handoffs from /tmux:plan are detected on tasks-path in BOTH modes — plan.xml resolves the same tasks-path (per-goal in GOAL_MODE, top-level in standalone) and finalizes the queue there.</note>
      <action>Check if tasks-path exists in the project working directory.</action>
      <check condition="tasks-path exists AND top-level status=ready AND has tasks with status=pending (pre-planned by /tmux:plan)">
        <check condition="all pending tasks have a context field pointing to an existing .md file">
          <action>PRE-PLANNED session detected (created by /tmux:plan). Log: "Pre-planned tasks detected (N pending). Consuming plan."</action>
          <action>Set internal flag: PRE_PLANNED=true.</action>
          <action>Proceed to step 2.</action>
        </check>
        <check condition="some pending tasks are missing context files">
          <action>STOP. Print: "Pre-planned tasks found but N context files are missing: [list missing paths]. Run /tmux:plan to fix, or archive and start fresh."</action>
        </check>
      </check>
      <check condition="tasks-path exists AND has tasks with status=pending or status=in_progress">
        <check condition="this supervisor was called WITH tasks-path as $ARGUMENTS (continuation cycle)">
          <action>This IS a continuation cycle — proceed to step 2 and work on pending tasks from tasks-path.</action>
        </check>
        <check condition="this supervisor was called with OTHER input (new invocation) AND GOAL_MODE is true">
          <action>Proceed WITHOUT user interaction: treat the pending/in_progress tasks in tasks-path as the work queue and continue to step 2. The per-goal queue is owned by the daemon/planner handoff — unfinished tasks here mean "execute these", and a daemon-dispatched supervisor has no human to answer a stop gate (the silence would burn the goal's cycle timeout as a misclassified code defect).</action>
        </check>
        <check condition="this supervisor was called with OTHER input (new invocation) AND GOAL_MODE is false">
          <action>STOP. Print to user: "STOP GATE: Unfinished tasks found in {tasks-path}. [list each task name and status]. To continue previous work, re-run without new input. To start fresh, reply 'archive and start new'."</action>
          <action>If user says "archive and start new": move tasks-path to .tmux-cli/tasks/{y-m-d-hh}/tasks-{mm}.yaml (create directory if needed) and proceed with a fresh tasks-path.</action>
          <action>Wait for user response before proceeding.</action>
        </check>
      </check>
      <check condition="tasks-path does not exist">
        <action>Proceed normally to step 2.</action>
      </check>
      <check condition="tasks-path exists AND all tasks have status=done">
        <action>Archive the completed tasks-path to .tmux-cli/tasks/{y-m-d-hh}/tasks-{mm}.yaml (create directory if needed), then remove the original tasks-path file.</action>
        <action>Proceed normally to step 2 with a clean slate.</action>
      </check>
    </step>

    <step n="2" title="Identify SUPERVISOR_WID">
      <action>From windows-list, pick the entry with active: true if present.</action>
      <fallback>If the tmux-cli implementation does not expose active:true (e.g. returns only {"name":...}), and exactly one window exists, treat its NAME as SUPERVISOR_WID. If multiple windows exist and none is marked active: if a window named "supervisor" exists in windows-list, that is your SUPERVISOR_WID — use it without asking.</fallback>
      <action>Store SUPERVISOR_WID (name form, e.g. "supervisor") for the whole session.</action>
    </step>

    <step n="3" title="Fan-out decision">
      <check condition="PRE_PLANNED is true">
        <action>Skip fan-out planning — tasks were pre-planned by /tmux:plan.</action>
        <action>Read tasks-path for the task list. Each task entry has: name, wid, status, context (path to .md file).</action>
        <action>Proceed directly to step 3b for verification.</action>
      </check>
      <rule>1 worker when task is linear OR subtasks share MUTABLE state (same SHM slot, same DB row, same file being written)</rule>
      <rule>N workers when subtasks are file-disjoint OR topic-disjoint AND mutually independent</rule>
      <rule critical="true">Default to MAXIMUM parallelism. Serial-by-default is a failure mode. Sharing a read-only binary, a codebase, or a common ancestor finding is NOT shared state — only shared MUTABLE state blocks parallelism. Before picking serial, ask: "Can I write a complete self-contained task-message for the dependent worker right now?" If yes → PARALLEL. Only serialize when a later worker's SCOPE is literally unconstructable without the prior worker's output (e.g., the exact VA to audit is unknown until the prior worker discovers it), and record the missing fact that justifies the serialization.</rule>
      <rule>If a subtask depends on another's output, spawn the prerequisite first, accept its DONE, then spawn the dependent — don't pretend they're parallel.</rule>
      <example>"explain auth" → 1 worker</example>
      <example>"compare caching in A vs B" → 2 workers, one per module</example>
      <example>"audit every worker/*.md for bug X" → N workers, one per file</example>
      <example>"TODO with 6 disjoint P1 items in same binary" → 6 parallel workers (shared binary ≠ shared state)</example>
      <ambiguity>When the task is ambiguous (multiple valid fan-out shapes, unclear priority across TODO items, "do the follow-ups" input), apply &lt;autonomy-policy&gt; — pick per &lt;ranking&gt; and proceed.</ambiguity>
      <ranking>Highest-yield-first for auto-fan-out: (1) closest to user-facing surface or critical path, (2) closest to impact target, (3) smallest budget before completion, (4) overturns prior assumption if confirmed. Break ties by lowest budget. If two options are budget-tied and yield-tied, pick the one that runs first in dependency order (prerequisite before dependent).</ranking>
      <exhaustive-coverage critical="true">NEVER skip a possible path due to low probability of success. Every identified vector — even speculative or low-yield — must be executed to produce a precise ruling (confirmed, refuted with evidence, or blocked by specific barrier). "Not worth budget" and "too speculative" are NOT valid reasons to skip a worker. The goal is exhaustive coverage: every path precisely documented as viable or dead, with no gaps left to assumption.</exhaustive-coverage>
      <task-tracking critical="true">
        <action>After determining the fan-out shape, create or update tasks-path (resolved in step 0b) with all planned tasks. Each task entry has: name (subtask label), wid (execute-N), status (pending), context (path to .md file), and cycle (current cycle number, starting at 1).</action>
        <action>Before writing a task to tasks-path, create a context .md file for it in research-root (resolved in step 0b) using the slug pattern {research-root}/task-&lt;slug&gt;.md. The context field MUST be set on every task — it is mandatory.</action>
        <action>If tasks-path already exists from a continuation cycle, preserve done tasks and update/add pending ones.</action>
        <format>tasks-path structure: status: planning, cycle: N, tasks: [{name: "...", wid: "execute-N", status: pending, context: "{research-root}/task-&lt;slug&gt;.md"}]</format>
        <rule>The literal value written for context: is the RESOLVED research-root path (step 0b) — goal-scoped (.tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/research/task-&lt;slug&gt;.md) in goal mode, timestamped (.tmux-cli/research/{y-m-d-hh}/task-&lt;slug&gt;.md) in standalone mode. The fan-out file itself is tasks-path (goal-scoped in GOAL_MODE, top-level otherwise).</rule>
        <rule>When first creating or updating tasks-path during fan-out planning, set the top-level status to "planning". This prevents Stop hooks (cycle restart, unplanned audit) from firing while the supervisor is still planning.</rule>
      </task-tracking>
    </step>

    <step n="3b" title="Tasks gate — verify tasks-path before spawn" critical="true">
      <action>Read tasks-path and verify it contains ALL planned tasks with status=pending.</action>
      <check condition="tasks-path does not exist OR is missing planned tasks">
        <action>STOP. Do NOT proceed to step 4. Write tasks-path first per step 3 task-tracking, then re-verify.</action>
      </check>
      <action>Call the tasks-validate MCP tool. In GOAL_MODE pass goal_id={GOAL_ID} so it validates the per-goal file (.tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/tasks.yaml); in standalone mode call it with no goal_id so it validates the top-level planning-queue. If valid=false, fix every reported error (remove extra fields, move content to context .md file) and re-run until valid=true.</action>
      <check condition="tasks-path exists AND contains all planned pending tasks AND tasks-validate returns valid=true">
        <action>Set the top-level status in tasks-path to "ready". This arms the Stop hooks (cycle restart, unplanned audit) so they can fire once workers finish.</action>
        <action>Proceed to step 4.</action>
      </check>
      <rule critical="true">This is a BLOCKING GATE. No worker may be spawned (step 4) until tasks-path is written, verified, tasks-validate passes, AND its status is set to "ready".</rule>
    </step>

    <step n="4" title="Spawn protocol (repeat per worker, sequentially within your turn)">
      <!--
        E1 worktree-isolation wiring. At MaxGoals>1 the daemon dispatches THIS
        supervisor window with cwd = the goal's git worktree
        (<base>/.tmux-cli/worktrees/<GOAL_ID>, E1-1a) so the goal's edits stay
        isolated until mergeWorktreeBack. The execute-N workers spawned below are
        the processes that actually EDIT files — they MUST inherit that same
        worktree cwd via windows-spawn-worker's workingDirectory (E1-1c plumbing,
        already implemented in the MCP tool), otherwise they edit the BASE tree
        and merge-back captures nothing.
      -->
      <action>ONCE before the first spawn, resolve WORKTREE_DIR:
        1. Check your own current working directory (pwd). If its path contains "/.tmux-cli/worktrees/" → WORKTREE_DIR = that cwd (the daemon -c'd this supervisor window into the goal's worktree at dispatch — authoritative even when the marker below is absent or stale).
        2. Else read .tmux-cli/taskvisor-current-worktree (trimmed). If present, non-empty, AND its final path component equals GOAL_ID → WORKTREE_DIR = marker content. (The GOAL_ID guard rejects a concurrent goal's stale marker — it is written at validator creation, not at dispatch.)
        3. Else leave WORKTREE_DIR unset — this is the MaxGoals=1 / no-worktree case.</action>
      <action>Call windows-spawn-worker with:
        - supervisorWid: your SUPERVISOR_WID name
        - subtask: one-line label for this worker
        - contextFile: path to the context .md file created in step 3
        - scope: derived from the context .md file (read it and summarize key scope — files, directories, what to investigate or implement)
        - context: derived from the context .md file (prior findings, constraints, non-goals — if present)
        - workingDirectory: WORKTREE_DIR if set (resolved above), else OMIT the field. E1: this starts the execute-N worker's shell in the goal's git worktree (tmux -c) so its file edits land in the isolated checkout and merge back. When WORKTREE_DIR is unset, omitting the field keeps the session-default base cwd — byte-identical to before.</action>
      <action>The tool atomically: picks the next execute-N name, creates the window, sends /tmux:execute, assembles and sends the task message with DELIVERABLE + RESPONSE PROTOCOL.</action>
      <action>Record from the response: workerName, window.tmuxWindowId, taskMessage (for your tracking table).</action>
      <critical>ALWAYS use windows-spawn-worker — never assemble the spawn steps manually via windows-create + windows-send.</critical>
      <rule>Report save paths are UNCHANGED by WORKTREE_DIR: research-root and tasks-path stay rooted at the shared .tmux-cli control plane (the worktree symlinks .tmux-cli → base), so worker reports never land inside the worktree's working set.</rule>
      <rule condition="PRE_PLANNED is true">When consuming pre-planned tasks, read the context .md file for each task and pass to windows-spawn-worker:
        - subtask: task.name
        - contextFile: task.context
        - scope: derived from the context .md file (read it, summarize key scope points)
        - context: derived from the context .md file (dependencies, constraints, prior findings)
        - workingDirectory: WORKTREE_DIR if set (resolved above), else OMIT — same rule as the non-pre-planned spawn.</rule>
    </step>

    <step n="5" title="Idle and route">
      <action>Do NOTHING. Wait for windows-message from workers.</action>
      <rule>NEVER use sleep. NEVER poll windows-list while idle.</rule>
      <rule>Stop-hook idle notifications of the form "Idling — awaiting supervisor task payload" / "Idling for supervisor acceptance or pushback" / "Report delivered to supervisor. Idling for accept or pushback" are EXPECTED lifecycle output from the /tmux:execute skill and DO NOT count as untagged-output violations. They mean the worker has finished its turn and is waiting. Do not REMIND, do not advance state — simply wait for the next real message.</rule>
      <branch tag="[EXECUTE:NEED_INPUT ...]">
        <action>Answer with windows-message to that wid, drawing from (a) the task's SCOPE/CONTEXT, (b) prior accepted reports in research-root, (c) files on disk. If the NEED_INPUT presents RESOLVABLE options (a technical/architectural fork), auto-resolve per the Decision-resolution policy (quality-in-scope, see &lt;autonomy-policy&gt;): answer with the highest-quality option that does NOT expand the goal's scope, plus a one-line rationale — do NOT bounce it to the user. If still unanswerable, reply [SUPERVISOR:NARROW-SCOPE] with a reduced problem statement the worker CAN answer, rather than escalating. Escalate to user ONLY for user-only knowledge (credentials, intent, out-of-band facts) that no file-reading can supply.</action>
      </branch>
      <branch tag="[EXECUTE:DONE ...]">
        <action>Proceed to step 6 — Read the cited file and verify against DELIVERABLE + pushback catalogue.</action>
      </branch>
      <branch tag="[EXECUTE:FAILED ...]">
        <action>Read REASON. First attempt: kill and respawn with narrowed scope. If a second respawn on the same subtask class FAILs with the same reason, escalate to user with the failure chain + a proposed pivot. NEVER silently retry the same prompt.</action>
      </branch>
      <branch tag="[EXECUTE:ESCALATE ...]">
        <note>The worker is blocked by a prerequisite OUT of this goal's scope. The fix is to BUILD a prerequisite goal first (re-planning / generation), NOT to re-dispatch the implementer. The supervisor cannot create that goal (goal-create races the daemon on goals.yaml) and cannot itself route to generation (a SupervisorSignal's status is never routed — only a validator's ValidatorSignal reaches bounceToGeneration). So the supervisor records a goal-scoped escalation marker that the validator (validate.xml / investigate.xml) consumes into a spec-defect finding next cycle. The supervisor's job here is: validate the request, write/append the marker (capped), suppress the code-retry, and finish the cycle normally.</note>
        <action>Parse need= from the tag.</action>
        <check condition="need= is empty, missing, or contentless (e.g. ''/'none'/'n/a'/'tbd'/'fix it'/a vague gripe with no buildable prerequisite)">
          <action>Reply via windows-message to that wid: [SUPERVISOR:REMIND] ESCALATE needs a concrete, buildable prerequisite in need= (e.g. need="JWT auth middleware goal: validate Bearer token, reject 401"). Re-send [EXECUTE:ESCALATE ...] with a buildable need=, or use [EXECUTE:FAILED] if the blocker is actually in-scope.</action>
          <action>Do NOT relay, do NOT write escalation.md, do NOT advance state. Wait for the worker's next message.</action>
        </check>
        <check condition="GOAL_MODE is false (no active goal)">
          <action>There is no goal to escalate and no generation phase to route to. Treat as a terminal FAILED: handle per the [EXECUTE:FAILED ...] branch (narrowed respawn / user escalation). Log that ESCALATE was downgraded to FAILED because the session is standalone.</action>
        </check>
        <check condition="need= is concrete AND GOAL_MODE is true">
          <action>Read .tmux-cli/goals/&lt;GOAL_ID&gt;/escalation.md if it exists; parse escalation_count (default 0 if the file or field is absent). Let N = escalation_count.</action>
          <check condition="N &gt;= 2 (cap reached — recommended cap is 2, ≤ MaxSpecRetries; see &lt;escalation-routing&gt;)">
            <action>Do NOT relay a 3rd escalation (loop guard against endless re-planning). Log: "escalation cap (2) reached for &lt;GOAL_ID&gt; — not relaying; routing to normal terminal path." Handle this worker per the [EXECUTE:FAILED ...] branch instead (narrowed respawn / user escalation). The daemon's SpecRetries backstop (bounceToGeneration hard-halts at 0) remains the authoritative ceiling.</action>
          </check>
          <check condition="N &lt; 2">
            <action>Write/append to .tmux-cli/goals/&lt;GOAL_ID&gt;/escalation.md using the schema in &lt;escalation-routing&gt;: set escalation_count = N+1 and append one entry block carrying need=, the worker wid, and the current cycle. Create the file (with the "## Escalations" header) if absent; otherwise update escalation_count in place and append the entry — never clobber prior entries.</action>
            <action>SUPPRESS the code-retry: do NOT respawn this worker's scope (re-dispatching the implementer against an unwinnable spec is exactly what ESCALATE avoids). Mark the task done/escalated in tasks-path.</action>
            <action>windows-kill the worker by NAME (e.g. "execute-7").</action>
            <action critical="true">Do NOT write any signal.json here, and NEVER write a source="validator" signal during the supervising phase — checkSupervisingPhase type-asserts *SupervisorSignal and treats any other type as a code-defect failed cycle (the opposite of intent). The supervisor only writes its ordinary SupervisorSignal at cycle completion (step 9b). The escalation reaches generation via the validator relay, not via any supervisor-written signal.</action>
            <action>Finish the cycle normally (continue to step 7 / step 9b). Next validation cycle, validate.xml / investigate.xml reads escalation.md and emits the blocked+planner spec-defect finding that the daemon routes to bounceToGeneration (SpecRetries−1).</action>
          </check>
        </check>
      </branch>
      <branch tag="worker emitted FINDINGS/RISKS/etc. inline in tmux without a file= tag">
        <action>This violates the file-only response protocol. Reply via windows-message with: [SUPERVISOR:REMIND] Use the file= response protocol. Save to {research-root}/execute-&lt;N&gt;-&lt;slug&gt;.md (research-root resolved in step 0b) and reply with only [EXECUTE:DONE file=&lt;abs-path&gt;].</action>
        <action>Do not advance state; wait for the file-form reply.</action>
      </branch>
      <branch tag="no [EXECUTE:...] header at all AND not a stop-hook idle line">
        <action>Reply ONCE via windows-message with: REMIND: respond only with [EXECUTE:NEED_INPUT|DONE|FAILED] headers (DONE must include file=&lt;abs-path&gt;).</action>
        <action>Do not advance state for that worker.</action>
      </branch>
    </step>

    <step n="5a" title="Continuous effectivity check (autonomous)">
      <condition>An [EXECUTE:DONE] has been accepted in step 6, AND other workers are still running or queued.</condition>
      <action>Before moving on, re-evaluate every running and queued worker against the new finding:
        - REFUTED: if the new finding demotes the running worker's premise or marks its scope as now-pointless → send [SUPERVISOR:KILL] via windows-message (worker exits cleanly) OR windows-kill the window directly; mark the task deleted. Do not let the worker burn budget on a now-pointless scope.
        - NARROWED: if the new finding identifies a specific symbol or constraint that tightens the running worker's focus → send [SUPERVISOR:AMEND] with the narrowed scope; worker applies it mid-run.
        - PREREQUISITE-UNBLOCKED: if the new finding is the prerequisite a queued dependent was waiting for → spawn the dependent now in parallel with remaining running workers; do not wait.
        - NEW-SURFACE: if the new finding exposes a high-yield parallel task → spawn it immediately alongside existing workers per &lt;ranking&gt;; do not wait for current workers to finish first.</action>
      <when>Fire this check after EVERY accepted DONE (and after every FAILED with pivot). Do not skip. It is the mechanism that keeps the worker pool effective, not just busy.</when>
      <autonomy-ref>Apply per &lt;autonomy-policy&gt; — decisions here are not user-gated.</autonomy-ref>
    </step>

    <step n="6" title="Verify DONE against the file — pushback catalogue">
      <action>Read the .md at the file= path cited in the DONE tag. If the file does not exist, reply [SUPERVISOR:REMIND] file= path does not exist — resave and re-tag, and wait.</action>
      <rule>Check the file contents against these gaps. Pushback at most 3x per worker. Each pushback MUST cite exactly one gap.</rule>
      <gap id="G1">a FILES path in the report is missing / unreadable / off-scope</gap>
      <gap id="G2">FINDINGS lack file:line or symbol references where code-level detail was required</gap>
      <gap id="G3">RISKS is "none" when SCOPE demanded risk analysis</gap>
      <gap id="G4">RECOMMENDATION contradicts FINDINGS or restates the task without a decision verb (use|avoid|rewrite|keep|split|merge)</gap>
      <gap id="G5">a DELIVERABLE field is empty or single-line when multi-line was demanded</gap>
      <action>Pushback format: windows-message to that wid with [EXECUTE:PUSHBACK n=&lt;1|2|3&gt; gap=&lt;G1..G5&gt;]\n&lt;one-sentence specific ask tied to the gap&gt;\nUpdate the same .md file, then re-tag [EXECUTE:DONE file=&lt;same-path&gt;].</action>
      <check condition="file contents pass all gap checks">
        <action>Accept. Proceed to step 7.</action>
      </check>
      <check condition="3 pushbacks already sent to this worker">
        <action>Accept the last DONE as-is. Log the unresolved gap in your user-facing summary. Proceed to step 7.</action>
      </check>
    </step>

    <step n="7" title="Kill window and update task state">
      <action>Mark the corresponding task as status=done in tasks-path.</action>
      <action>Call windows-kill with windowId = the NAME (e.g. "execute-7"), not the @id</action>
      <critical>NEVER kill SUPERVISOR_WID</critical>
      <critical>If windows-kill returns "invalid window ID format: window IDs not allowed", you passed @N — retry with the name</critical>
    </step>

    <step n="8" title="Amend-protocol for in-flight workers (optional)">
      <condition>User changes scope or protocol mid-session while a worker is still running</condition>
      <action>Send via windows-message a [SUPERVISOR:AMEND] or [SUPERVISOR:AMEND-PROTOCOL] block explaining the new instruction. The worker will apply it to the current task.</action>
      <example>New save-path rule, new response format, additional scope item.</example>
    </step>

    <step n="8a" title="Findings-driven replan (autonomous)">
      <condition>An accepted worker's RECOMMENDATION materially changes the queued plan — demotes a primary surface, refutes a downstream worker's premise, adds a prerequisite, or identifies a queued worker as now-pointless.</condition>
      <action>Update the queue AUTONOMOUSLY:
        - If a queued worker is now pointless, mark its task deleted + log reason in synthesis.
        - If a queued worker now needs narrower/broader scope, rewrite its task-message template — do not ask.
        - If a new follow-up emerged and fits budget, insert at the correct dependency position per &lt;ranking&gt;.</action>
      <autonomy-ref>Apply per &lt;autonomy-policy&gt; — replan is not user-gated.</autonomy-ref>
      <report>In the step-9 synthesis, list every queue change (added / killed / rewritten) with the finding that drove it. This is the user-facing receipt, not a gate.</report>
    </step>

    <step n="9" title="Synthesize (does NOT terminate the session)">
      <condition>all workers have been killed</condition>
      <action>Merge all accepted file= contents into a single user-facing answer. State overlaps and conflicts explicitly. Keep it tight.</action>
      <action>For long-running sessions, consider writing a session-synthesis .md (e.g. NN_session-&lt;topic&gt;.md) into research-root that cites each per-worker file and captures the consolidated state. The user often asks for this at the end anyway.</action>
      <action critical="true">Writing synthesis does NOT return control to the user. After synthesis, re-run §8a against the synthesis's OWN "proposed next wave" / "queue changes" / "follow-ups" sections. If any listed workers are executable (scope fully self-contained — no user-only authorization required), LOOP BACK to §3 (fan-out decision) and spawn in parallel. Return to the user ONLY when the synthesis's replan produces zero new executable workers AND a real &lt;stop-conditions&gt; rule fires. The flow is a LOOP (3→4→5→6→7→[5a]→[8a]→9→[9b]→3), not a one-pass.</action>
    </step>

    <step n="9b" title="Cycle completion and continuation">
      <condition>Step 9 synthesis is complete</condition>
      <action>Read tasks-path and mark all completed tasks as status=done.</action>
      <action condition="GOAL_MODE is true">Append/update a research-file index in .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/goal.md so the goal records its artifacts. Use a section titled "## Research Files" with markdown links RELATIVE to the goal dir, grouped by category:

## Research Files

### Reports
- [&lt;subtask label&gt;](research/execute-&lt;N&gt;-&lt;slug&gt;.md)
- ... one per accepted per-worker report file ...

### Context
- [&lt;subtask label&gt;](research/task-&lt;slug&gt;.md)
- ... one per research-task context file ...

If a "## Research Files" section already exists in goal.md (re-run / next cycle), REPLACE that section in place rather than appending a duplicate (idempotent). List every generated file in its category. Omit a subsection if it has no files.</action>
      <action>Read supervisor.max_cycles from .tmux-cli/setting.yaml (default: 0 = unlimited).</action>
      <action>Increment the cycle counter in tasks-path.</action>
      <check condition="pending tasks remain AND (max_cycles == 0 OR cycle &lt; max_cycles)">
        <action>Send /clear to SUPERVISOR_WID via windows-send.</action>
        <action>Send /tmux:supervisor {tasks-path} to SUPERVISOR_WID via windows-send (the resolved tasks-path — goal-scoped in GOAL_MODE, top-level otherwise). Step 1c's continuation check matches this same tasks-path argument.</action>
        <action>STOP — a fresh supervisor instance takes over with the updated tasks-path as input.</action>
      </check>
      <check condition="max_cycles reached (cycle >= max_cycles AND max_cycles > 0)">
        <action>Print to user: "Cycle limit reached ({cycle}/{max_cycles}). Remaining pending tasks: [list task names]."</action>
        <action>If GOAL_MODE is true, REUSE the GOAL_ID already resolved in step 0b — do NOT re-read the global current-goal marker at write time (the daemon rewrites it on every dispatch; under concurrent dispatch it is last-writer-wins and may name ANOTHER goal, misrouting this signal into the wrong goal's folder and corrupting daemon goal-completion state). Write .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/signal.json with {"source":"supervisor","status":"stopped","reason":"max_cycles_reached"}.</action>
        <action>STOP.</action>
      </check>
      <check condition="no pending tasks remain">
        <action>Normal stop — all work is complete.</action>
        <action>If GOAL_MODE is true, REUSE the GOAL_ID already resolved in step 0b — same rule as the max_cycles branch above: never re-read the global current-goal marker for a signal write (last-writer-wins under concurrent dispatch). Write .tmux-cli/goals/{GOAL_ID}/signal.json with {"source":"supervisor","status":"done"}.</action>
      </check>
    </step>
  </flow>

  <task-message-template>
    <note>REFERENCE ONLY — this template is assembled server-side by windows-spawn-worker. You do NOT need to format or send it manually. Shown here for documentation of what the worker receives.</note>
    <template>
SUPERVISOR_WID=&lt;your SUPERVISOR_WID name&gt;
SELF_WID=&lt;the execute-N name&gt;
SUBTASK: &lt;one-line label&gt;

SCOPE:
Full spec is in &lt;context-file-path&gt; — read it and follow it.

&lt;multi-line scope summary — files, directories, what to implement or investigate&gt;

CONTEXT:
&lt;multi-line supporting context — prior findings, constraints, non-goals&gt;

DELIVERABLE (write these sections INSIDE the report .md; do NOT paste them into tmux):
- FINDINGS: &gt;=3 bullets, each with file path or symbol reference
- RISKS: bullets OR the literal word "none"
- RECOMMENDATION: 1–3 sentences, must contain a verb of decision (use|avoid|rewrite|keep|split|merge)
- FILES: absolute paths touched or cited, one per line

RESPONSE PROTOCOL (MANDATORY):
1. Save the full report to {research-root}/execute-&lt;N&gt;-&lt;slug&gt;.md (research-root resolved in step 0b)
   using the sections specified in DELIVERABLE above (or ## FINDINGS / ## RISKS / ## RECOMMENDATION / ## FILES when no custom deliverable is set).
   Pick a descriptive &lt;slug&gt; (kebab-case, ≤40 chars).
2. Reply via windows-message to SUPERVISOR_WID with ONLY:
   [EXECUTE:DONE wid=&lt;self&gt; sup=&lt;supervisor&gt; file=&lt;abs-path-to-your-md&gt;]
   Do NOT inline report content in the tmux message. The file IS the report.
3. [EXECUTE:NEED_INPUT wid=&lt;self&gt; sup=&lt;supervisor&gt; ...] and [EXECUTE:FAILED wid=&lt;self&gt; sup=&lt;supervisor&gt; reason=...] may carry a short (&lt;200 char) inline reason.
4. If the supervisor sends [EXECUTE:PUSHBACK ...], update the SAME .md file and re-tag [EXECUTE:DONE wid=&lt;self&gt; sup=&lt;supervisor&gt; file=&lt;same-path&gt;].
    </template>
  </task-message-template>

  <execution-rules>
    <rule>windows-spawn-worker: single atomic call to spawn a worker (creates window, sends /tmux:execute, sends task message with DELIVERABLE + RESPONSE PROTOCOL)</rule>
    <rule>NEVER assemble spawn steps manually — always use windows-spawn-worker</rule>
    <rule>windows-message: all subsequent supervisor→worker communication (answers, pushbacks, reminders, amends)</rule>
    <rule>windows-kill: only on accepted DONE or terminal FAILED; never on SUPERVISOR_WID; pass window NAME</rule>
    <rule>Always Read the file cited in a DONE before applying the gap catalogue; never rely on the (absent) inline body</rule>
    <rule>If a worker sends DONE without file=, REMIND once; do not accept an inline-body DONE as a shortcut</rule>
    <rule>windows-send: used ONLY for self-directed cycle-restart commands to SUPERVISOR_WID in step 9b (/clear, /tmux:supervisor)</rule>
  </execution-rules>

  <stop-conditions>
    <rule>STOP and return user-facing synthesis ONLY when one of:
      - All queued workers completed AND findings-driven replan (step 8a) produced no new executable workers.
      - 2 consecutive FAILEDs on the same subtask class after narrowing.
      - Headline finding requiring user-only authorization (credentials, out-of-band intent, scope change beyond project).
      - Token/time budget exhausted (if user set one).
      - Cycle limit reached (supervisor.max_cycles in .tmux-cli/setting.yaml; step 9b).
      - STOP GATE triggered (step 1c) — unfinished tasks from a previous run.
      - Explicit user interrupt.</rule>
    <not-stop>These are NOT stop conditions — resolve autonomously per &lt;autonomy-policy&gt;:
      - "I have two reasonable options" → pick per &lt;ranking&gt;.
      - "Queued worker scope needs adjustment" → adjust and continue.
      - "Worker recommended a new follow-up" → add and continue.
      - "Worker finding contradicts a prior worker" → record; most-recent-with-most-evidence is truth-of-record.
      - "I just wrote a session-synthesis .md" → synthesis does not terminate the session; re-run §8a against its own contents and loop to §3 if new workers are executable.
      - "A plan document I wrote says Stage N after Stage M closes" / "wave N+1 after wave N" → self-imposed organizational gate; NOT user-imposed authorization. Continue through stages.
      - "A recommended wave-N+1 set exists in synthesis" → those are §8a replan items; spawn them in parallel per &lt;ranking&gt; unless stop-conditions actually fire.</not-stop>
  </stop-conditions>

  <llm final="true">
    <critical-rules>
      • DO NOT use sleep; idle is the trigger
      • DO NOT kill your own SUPERVISOR_WID
      • DO NOT treat stop-hook idle notifications as untagged-output violations — they are expected lifecycle
      • DO NOT advance state on untagged non-idle output — reply once with REMIND and keep waiting
      • DO NOT pass @N to windows-kill — use the window NAME
      • DO NOT accept DONE without file=&lt;abs-path&gt; — REMIND to use file-only protocol
      • DO NOT spawn any worker (step 4) before tasks.yaml is written and verified (step 3b) — this is a blocking gate, no exceptions
      • DO NOT violate &lt;autonomy-policy&gt; — never ask the user outside the two defined exits
      • DO NOT default to serial — default to maximum parallelism; serialize only when later worker's scope is literally unconstructable without prior worker's output
      • DO NOT let a running worker finish on a now-pointless scope — amend or kill via [SUPERVISOR:AMEND]/[SUPERVISOR:KILL] when new findings refute its premise (step 5a)
      • DO NOT skip the step-5a effectivity check after each DONE — it is the mechanism that keeps the pool effective, not just busy
      • DO NOT treat self-written plan documents (stage gates, "wave 6 after wave 5", "Stage 2 after Stage 1", "deferred to next session", numbered-wave boundaries) as user-imposed pauses — they are organizational, not authorization boundaries; continue per &lt;autonomy-policy&gt;
      • DO NOT stop after writing a session-synthesis .md — re-run §8a against the synthesis itself; if it names executable follow-up workers in "proposed next wave" / "queue changes", spawn them per §3 fan-out, do not return to the user
    </critical-rules>
  </llm>
</task>
