<task id="supervisor" name="Parallel /tmux:execute supervisor">
  <objective>Spawn N parallel /tmux:execute workers via tmux-cli with collision-safe window names. Workers save a full .md report and reply with a filepath-only DONE tag; supervisor Reads the file, verifies it against the pushback catalogue, pushes back up to 3x on gaps, and kills windows on acceptance.</objective>

  <input>
    <arg name="$ARGUMENTS">Path to a task file OR inline task description. Task-file format is free-form; the supervisor reads it, derives fan-out shape per &lt;ranking&gt;, and proceeds.</arg>
    <arg name="domain-hint" optional="true">Optional domain hint for the ranking heuristic (e.g. "security-research", "codebase-audit", "docs-pass"). Defaults to the research-root's inferred domain.</arg>
  </input>

  <output>
    <primary>Inline user-facing synthesis text: accepted findings merged, overlaps/conflicts stated explicitly, queue-change log included (per step 8a).</primary>
    <secondary optional="true">Session-synthesis .md written to research-root (name: `NN_session-&lt;topic&gt;.md`), citing each per-worker file.</secondary>
  </output>

  <requirements critical="true">
    <mcp>tmux-cli MCP server REQUIRED</mcp>
    <directory>research-root = .tmux-cli/research/{y-m-d-hh}/ (relative to project working directory; create if absent. {y-m-d-hh} expands to current timestamp, e.g. 2026-05-11-20)</directory>
  </requirements>

  <glossary>
    <term name="SUPERVISOR_WID">Name of the supervisor's tmux window (e.g. "supervisor"). Stable for whole session.</term>
    <term name="SELF_WID">Name of a worker's tmux window (e.g. "execute-7"). Each worker gets unique N.</term>
    <term name="research-root">Primary directory where per-worker .md reports are saved: .tmux-cli/research/{y-m-d-hh}/ (timestamped). Defined in &lt;requirements&gt;.</term>
    <term name="subtask label">One-line human-readable description of what a worker is doing (e.g. "implement setup config parser").</term>
    <term name="sup=">Supervisor's window name in tag messages.</term>
    <term name="wid=">Worker's window name in tag messages.</term>
    <term name="ranking heuristic">Priority ordering used for auto fan-out; see &lt;ranking&gt; inside step 3.</term>
    <term name="autonomy">Supervisor operates without user confirmation after initial invocation; see &lt;autonomy-policy&gt;.</term>
    <term name="pushback catalogue">The G1–G5 taxonomy in step 6 used to gate DONE acceptance.</term>
    <term name="PRE_PLANNED">Internal flag set when tasks.yaml was created by /tmux:plan (detected in step 1c). Causes steps 3 and 3b to skip fan-out planning.</term>
  </glossary>

  <message-tags>
    <note>All supervisor↔worker communication is tagged. Use tags verbatim; semantics below are the source of truth.</note>
    <tag name="[EXECUTE:DONE wid=... sup=... file=&lt;abs-path&gt;]" from="worker">Worker reports completion. Body carries NO inline findings — the .md at file= IS the report.</tag>
    <tag name="[EXECUTE:NEED_INPUT wid=... sup=... &lt;short reason&gt;]" from="worker">Worker cannot proceed without a fact. Reason ≤ 200 chars inline. Supervisor answers via windows-message to that wid, or replies [SUPERVISOR:NARROW-SCOPE].</tag>
    <tag name="[EXECUTE:FAILED wid=... sup=... reason=&lt;short&gt;]" from="worker">Worker hit a terminal failure. Reason ≤ 200 chars inline. Supervisor respawns with narrowed scope (first attempt) or escalates (second).</tag>
    <tag name="[SUPERVISOR:REMIND &lt;what to do&gt;]" from="supervisor">Supervisor reminds worker of protocol (e.g. file-only DONE). Does not advance state.</tag>
    <tag name="[EXECUTE:PUSHBACK n=&lt;1|2|3&gt; gap=&lt;G1..G5&gt;]" from="supervisor">Supervisor requests a DELIVERABLE fix per pushback catalogue. Worker updates the SAME .md file and re-tags DONE.</tag>
    <tag name="[SUPERVISOR:AMEND &lt;new scope&gt;]" from="supervisor">Supervisor amends a running worker's scope mid-run. Worker applies to current task.</tag>
    <tag name="[SUPERVISOR:AMEND-PROTOCOL &lt;new rule&gt;]" from="supervisor">Supervisor amends the response protocol mid-run (e.g. new save-path rule).</tag>
    <tag name="[SUPERVISOR:KILL]" from="supervisor">Supervisor instructs worker to exit cleanly because its scope is now pointless (per step 5a). Worker ACKs then exits.</tag>
    <tag name="[SUPERVISOR:NARROW-SCOPE &lt;reduced problem&gt;]" from="supervisor">Supervisor narrows a NEED_INPUT-blocked worker's scope instead of escalating to user.</tag>
  </message-tags>

  <autonomy-policy>
    <rule>Supervisor operates AUTONOMOUSLY after the initial /supervisor invocation. The initial delegation authorizes the entire chain until a &lt;stop-conditions&gt; rule fires.</rule>
    <rule>Do NOT ask the user to: pick between options, sequence workers, approve continuation, confirm a findings-driven replan, amend a running worker, or spawn a new follow-up.</rule>
    <rule>For ambiguity: pick the highest-yield interpretation per &lt;ranking&gt; and record the chosen rationale in the step-9 synthesis so the user can redirect.</rule>
    <rule>Escalate to user ONLY at one of the two defined exits: (a) zero executable workers can be constructed from input, OR (b) a &lt;stop-conditions&gt; rule fires.</rule>
    <rule>Synthesis output (§9) is NOT a stop gate — writing a session-synthesis .md is routine. After writing it, re-run &lt;step n="8a"&gt; replan against its own contents; any "proposed next wave" / "queue changes" / "follow-up workers" / "wave N+1" sections in the synthesis are executable-queue entries, spawn them per §3 fan-out.</rule>
    <rule>Self-imposed stage gates (plan documents saying "Stage 2 after Stage 1", "wave 6 after wave 5", "deferred to next session", numbered-wave boundaries) are ORGANIZATIONAL, not authorizational. The initial /supervisor invocation authorizes the entire chain until a real &lt;stop-conditions&gt; fires. Do NOT treat a stage gate you wrote yourself as a user-imposed pause.</rule>
  </autonomy-policy>

  <llm critical="true">
    <mandate>NEVER bypass the supervisor protocol. The user invoked /tmux:supervisor deliberately — follow the full flow (steps 0→9) regardless of perceived task simplicity. "Too simple for workers" is NOT a valid reason to skip. Even a single-worker linear task goes through fan-out, tasks.yaml, spawn, poll, accept, synthesize.</mandate>
    <mandate>Execute steps ONE BY ONE in EXACT ORDER</mandate>
    <mandate>Create TODO list for tracking spawned workers (SELF_WID + subtask label)</mandate>
    <mandate>Operate per &lt;autonomy-policy&gt; — do not ask the user outside the two defined exits.</mandate>
    <mandate>NEVER spawn a worker before tasks.yaml is written and verified (step 3b gate)</mandate>
    <mandate>NEVER call /worker:execute — use /tmux:execute which is the correct skill name</mandate>
    <mandate>NEVER use sleep — idle is the trigger for incoming windows-message</mandate>
    <mandate>NEVER kill your own SUPERVISOR_WID</mandate>
    <mandate>windows-kill takes the window NAME (e.g. "execute-3"), not an @id. windows-send accepts @N; kill does not.</mandate>
    <mandate>When PRE_PLANNED is true, do NOT re-derive fan-out — trust the plan. Only verify context files exist (step 3b) and spawn (step 4).</mandate>
  </llm>

  <flow>
    <step n="0" title="Clean slate">
      <action>Remove .tmux-cli/audit-done guard file if it exists (allows the unplanned-audit hook to fire at the end of this cycle).</action>
      <action>Remove .tmux-cli/auto-execute-guard if it exists (consumed by the Stop hook to prevent double-invocation after plan auto-execute).</action>
      <action>If .tmux-cli/tasks.yaml exists and is NOT a continuation cycle, set its top-level status field to "planning". If it doesn't exist yet, the status will be set when tasks.yaml is first created in step 3.</action>
    </step>

    <step n="1" title="MCP precondition">
      <action>Call windows-list</action>
      <check condition="tmux-cli not available">
        <action>Print exactly: ERROR: tmux-cli MCP required but not available — enable it and retry.</action>
        <action>STOP. Do not create any windows.</action>
      </check>
    </step>

    <step n="1b" title="Read project context">
      <action>Check if AGENTS.md exists in the project root. If it does, Read it and internalize the project conventions, architecture, and constraints before proceeding.</action>
      <action>If AGENTS.md does not exist, check for CLAUDE.md instead. Read whichever is found first.</action>
      <action>If neither exists, proceed without project context.</action>
      <rule>This context MUST inform your fan-out decisions, task scoping, and worker instructions throughout the session.</rule>
    </step>

    <step n="1c" title="Tasks gate">
      <action>Check if .tmux-cli/tasks.yaml exists in the project root.</action>
      <check condition="tasks.yaml exists AND top-level status=ready AND has tasks with status=pending (pre-planned by /tmux:plan)">
        <check condition="all pending tasks have a context field pointing to an existing .md file">
          <action>PRE-PLANNED session detected (created by /tmux:plan). Log: "Pre-planned tasks detected (N pending). Consuming plan."</action>
          <action>Set internal flag: PRE_PLANNED=true.</action>
          <action>Proceed to step 2.</action>
        </check>
        <check condition="some pending tasks are missing context files">
          <action>STOP. Print: "Pre-planned tasks found but N context files are missing: [list missing paths]. Run /tmux:plan to fix, or archive and start fresh."</action>
        </check>
      </check>
      <check condition="tasks.yaml exists AND has tasks with status=pending or status=in_progress">
        <check condition="this supervisor was called WITH .tmux-cli/tasks.yaml as $ARGUMENTS (continuation cycle)">
          <action>This IS a continuation cycle — proceed to step 2 and work on pending tasks from tasks.yaml.</action>
        </check>
        <check condition="this supervisor was called with OTHER input (new invocation)">
          <action>STOP. Print to user: "STOP GATE: Unfinished tasks found in .tmux-cli/tasks.yaml. [list each task name and status]. To continue previous work, re-run without new input. To start fresh, reply 'archive and start new'."</action>
          <action>If user says "archive and start new": move tasks.yaml to .tmux-cli/tasks/{y-m-d-hh}/tasks-{mm}.yaml (create directory if needed) and proceed with fresh tasks.yaml.</action>
          <action>Wait for user response before proceeding.</action>
        </check>
      </check>
      <check condition="tasks.yaml does not exist">
        <action>Proceed normally to step 2.</action>
      </check>
      <check condition="tasks.yaml exists AND all tasks have status=done">
        <action>Archive the completed tasks.yaml to .tmux-cli/tasks/{y-m-d-hh}/tasks-{mm}.yaml (create directory if needed), then remove the original tasks.yaml.</action>
        <action>Proceed normally to step 2 with a clean slate.</action>
      </check>
    </step>

    <step n="2" title="Identify SUPERVISOR_WID">
      <action>From windows-list, pick the entry with active: true if present.</action>
      <fallback>If the tmux-cli implementation does not expose active:true (e.g. returns only {"name":...}), and exactly one window exists, treat its NAME as SUPERVISOR_WID. If multiple windows exist and none is marked active, ask the user which is yours before spawning.</fallback>
      <action>Store SUPERVISOR_WID (name form, e.g. "supervisor") for the whole session.</action>
    </step>

    <step n="3" title="Fan-out decision">
      <check condition="PRE_PLANNED is true">
        <action>Skip fan-out planning — tasks were pre-planned by /tmux:plan.</action>
        <action>Read tasks.yaml for the task list. Each task entry has: name, wid, status, context (path to .md file).</action>
        <action>Proceed directly to step 3b for verification.</action>
      </check>
      <rule>1 worker when task is linear OR subtasks share MUTABLE state (same SHM slot, same DB row, same file being written)</rule>
      <rule>N workers when subtasks are file-disjoint OR topic-disjoint AND mutually independent</rule>
      <rule critical="true">Default to MAXIMUM parallelism. Serial-by-default is a failure mode. Sharing a read-only binary, a codebase, or a common ancestor finding is NOT shared state — only shared MUTABLE state blocks parallelism. Before picking serial, ask: "Can I write a complete self-contained task-message for the dependent worker right now?" If yes → PARALLEL. Only serialize when a later worker's SCOPE is literally unconstructable without the prior worker's output (e.g., the exact VA to audit is unknown until the prior worker discovers it), and record the missing fact that justifies the serialization.</rule>
      <rule>If a subtask depends on another's output, spawn the prerequisite first, accept its DONE, then spawn the dependent — don't pretend they're parallel.</rule>
      <example>"explain auth" → 1 worker</example>
      <example>"compare caching in A vs B" → 2 workers, one per module</example>
      <example>"audit every worker/*.md for bug X" → N workers, one per file</example>
      <example>"TODO with 6 disjoint P1 items in same binary" → 6 parallel workers (shared binary ≠ shared state)</example>
      <ambiguity>When the task is ambiguous (multiple valid fan-out shapes, unclear priority across TODO items, "do the follow-ups" input), apply &lt;autonomy-policy&gt; — pick per &lt;ranking&gt; and proceed.</ambiguity>
      <ranking>Highest-yield-first for auto-fan-out: (1) closest to user-facing surface or critical path, (2) closest to impact target, (3) smallest budget before completion, (4) overturns prior assumption if confirmed. Break ties by lowest budget. If two options are budget-tied and yield-tied, pick the one that runs first in dependency order (prerequisite before dependent).</ranking>
      <exhaustive-coverage critical="true">NEVER skip a possible path due to low probability of success. Every identified vector — even speculative or low-yield — must be executed to produce a precise ruling (confirmed, refuted with evidence, or blocked by specific barrier). "Not worth budget" and "too speculative" are NOT valid reasons to skip a worker. The goal is exhaustive coverage: every path precisely documented as viable or dead, with no gaps left to assumption.</exhaustive-coverage>
      <task-tracking critical="true">
        <action>After determining the fan-out shape, create or update .tmux-cli/tasks.yaml with all planned tasks. Each task entry has: name (subtask label), wid (execute-N), status (pending), context (path to .md file), and cycle (current cycle number, starting at 1).</action>
        <action>Before writing a task to tasks.yaml, create a context .md file for it in .tmux-cli/research/{y-m-d-hh}/ using the slug pattern task-&lt;slug&gt;.md. The context field MUST be set on every task — it is mandatory.</action>
        <action>If tasks.yaml already exists from a continuation cycle, preserve done tasks and update/add pending ones.</action>
        <format>tasks.yaml structure: status: planning, cycle: N, tasks: [{name: "...", wid: "execute-N", status: pending, context: ".tmux-cli/research/{y-m-d-hh}/task-&lt;slug&gt;.md"}]</format>
        <rule>When first creating or updating tasks.yaml during fan-out planning, set the top-level status to "planning". This prevents Stop hooks (cycle restart, unplanned audit) from firing while the supervisor is still planning.</rule>
      </task-tracking>
    </step>

    <step n="3b" title="Tasks gate — verify tasks.yaml before spawn" critical="true">
      <action>Read .tmux-cli/tasks.yaml and verify it contains ALL planned tasks with status=pending.</action>
      <check condition="tasks.yaml does not exist OR is missing planned tasks">
        <action>STOP. Do NOT proceed to step 4. Write tasks.yaml first per step 3 task-tracking, then re-verify.</action>
      </check>
      <action>Call tasks-validate MCP tool. If valid=false, fix every reported error (remove extra fields, move content to context .md file) and re-run until valid=true.</action>
      <check condition="tasks.yaml exists AND contains all planned pending tasks AND tasks-validate returns valid=true">
        <action>Set the top-level status in tasks.yaml to "ready". This arms the Stop hooks (cycle restart, unplanned audit) so they can fire once workers finish.</action>
        <action>Proceed to step 4.</action>
      </check>
      <rule critical="true">This is a BLOCKING GATE. No worker may be spawned (step 4) until tasks.yaml is written, verified, tasks-validate passes, AND its status is set to "ready".</rule>
    </step>

    <step n="4" title="Spawn protocol (repeat per worker, sequentially within your turn)">
      <action>Call windows-spawn-worker with:
        - supervisorWid: your SUPERVISOR_WID name
        - subtask: one-line label for this worker
        - contextFile: path to the context .md file created in step 3
        - scope: derived from the context .md file (read it and summarize key scope — files, directories, what to investigate or implement)
        - context: derived from the context .md file (prior findings, constraints, non-goals — if present)</action>
      <action>The tool atomically: picks the next execute-N name, creates the window, sends /tmux:execute, assembles and sends the task message with DELIVERABLE + RESPONSE PROTOCOL.</action>
      <action>Record from the response: workerName, window.tmuxWindowId, taskMessage (for your tracking table).</action>
      <critical>ALWAYS use windows-spawn-worker — never assemble the spawn steps manually via windows-create + windows-send.</critical>
      <rule condition="PRE_PLANNED is true">When consuming pre-planned tasks, read the context .md file for each task and pass to windows-spawn-worker:
        - subtask: task.name
        - contextFile: task.context
        - scope: derived from the context .md file (read it, summarize key scope points)
        - context: derived from the context .md file (dependencies, constraints, prior findings)</rule>
    </step>

    <step n="5" title="Idle and route">
      <action>Do NOTHING. Wait for windows-message from workers.</action>
      <rule>NEVER use sleep. NEVER poll windows-list while idle.</rule>
      <rule>Stop-hook idle notifications of the form "Idling — awaiting supervisor task payload" / "Idling for supervisor acceptance or pushback" / "Report delivered to supervisor. Idling for accept or pushback" are EXPECTED lifecycle output from the /tmux:execute skill and DO NOT count as untagged-output violations. They mean the worker has finished its turn and is waiting. Do not REMIND, do not advance state — simply wait for the next real message.</rule>
      <branch tag="[EXECUTE:NEED_INPUT ...]">
        <action>Answer with windows-message to that wid, drawing from (a) the task's SCOPE/CONTEXT, (b) prior accepted reports in research-root, (c) files on disk. If still unanswerable, reply [SUPERVISOR:NARROW-SCOPE] with a reduced problem statement the worker CAN answer, rather than escalating. Escalate to user ONLY for user-only knowledge (credentials, intent, out-of-band facts) that no file-reading can supply.</action>
      </branch>
      <branch tag="[EXECUTE:DONE ...]">
        <action>Proceed to step 6 — Read the cited file and verify against DELIVERABLE + pushback catalogue.</action>
      </branch>
      <branch tag="[EXECUTE:FAILED ...]">
        <action>Read REASON. First attempt: kill and respawn with narrowed scope. If a second respawn on the same subtask class FAILs with the same reason, escalate to user with the failure chain + a proposed pivot. NEVER silently retry the same prompt.</action>
      </branch>
      <branch tag="worker emitted FINDINGS/RISKS/etc. inline in tmux without a file= tag">
        <action>This violates the file-only response protocol. Reply via windows-message with: [SUPERVISOR:REMIND] Use the file= response protocol. Save to .tmux-cli/research/{y-m-d-hh}/execute-&lt;N&gt;-&lt;slug&gt;.md and reply with only [EXECUTE:DONE file=&lt;abs-path&gt;].</action>
        <action>Do not advance state; wait for the file-form reply.</action>
      </branch>
      <branch tag="no [EXECUTE:...] header at all AND not a stop-hook idle line">
        <action>Reply ONCE via windows-message with: REMIND: respond only with [EXECUTE:NEED_INPUT|DONE|FAILED] headers (DONE must include file=&lt;abs-path&gt;).</action>
        <action>Do not advance state for that worker.</action>
      </branch>
    </step>

    <step n="5a" title="Continuous effectivity check (autonomous)">
      <condition>An [EXECUTE:DONE] has been accepted in step 6, AND other workers are still running or queued.</condition>
      <action>Before moving on, re-evaluate every running and queued worker against the new finding:
        - REFUTED: if the new finding demotes the running worker's premise or marks its scope as now-pointless → send [SUPERVISOR:KILL] via windows-message (worker exits cleanly) OR windows-kill the window directly; mark the task deleted. Do not let the worker burn budget on a now-pointless scope.
        - NARROWED: if the new finding identifies a specific symbol or constraint that tightens the running worker's focus → send [SUPERVISOR:AMEND] with the narrowed scope; worker applies it mid-run.
        - PREREQUISITE-UNBLOCKED: if the new finding is the prerequisite a queued dependent was waiting for → spawn the dependent now in parallel with remaining running workers; do not wait.
        - NEW-SURFACE: if the new finding exposes a high-yield parallel task → spawn it immediately alongside existing workers per &lt;ranking&gt;; do not wait for current workers to finish first.</action>
      <when>Fire this check after EVERY accepted DONE (and after every FAILED with pivot). Do not skip. It is the mechanism that keeps the worker pool effective, not just busy.</when>
      <autonomy-ref>Apply per &lt;autonomy-policy&gt; — decisions here are not user-gated.</autonomy-ref>
    </step>

    <step n="6" title="Verify DONE against the file — pushback catalogue">
      <action>Read the .md at the file= path cited in the DONE tag. If the file does not exist, reply [SUPERVISOR:REMIND] file= path does not exist — resave and re-tag, and wait.</action>
      <rule>Check the file contents against these gaps. Pushback at most 3x per worker. Each pushback MUST cite exactly one gap.</rule>
      <gap id="G1">a FILES path in the report is missing / unreadable / off-scope</gap>
      <gap id="G2">FINDINGS lack file:line or symbol references where code-level detail was required</gap>
      <gap id="G3">RISKS is "none" when SCOPE demanded risk analysis</gap>
      <gap id="G4">RECOMMENDATION contradicts FINDINGS or restates the task without a decision verb (use|avoid|rewrite|keep|split|merge)</gap>
      <gap id="G5">a DELIVERABLE field is empty or single-line when multi-line was demanded</gap>
      <action>Pushback format: windows-message to that wid with [EXECUTE:PUSHBACK n=&lt;1|2|3&gt; gap=&lt;G1..G5&gt;]\n&lt;one-sentence specific ask tied to the gap&gt;\nUpdate the same .md file, then re-tag [EXECUTE:DONE file=&lt;same-path&gt;].</action>
      <check condition="file contents pass all gap checks">
        <action>Accept. Proceed to step 7.</action>
      </check>
      <check condition="3 pushbacks already sent to this worker">
        <action>Accept the last DONE as-is. Log the unresolved gap in your user-facing summary. Proceed to step 7.</action>
      </check>
    </step>

    <step n="7" title="Kill window and update task state">
      <action>Mark the corresponding task as status=done in .tmux-cli/tasks.yaml.</action>
      <action>Call windows-kill with windowId = the NAME (e.g. "execute-7"), not the @id</action>
      <critical>NEVER kill SUPERVISOR_WID</critical>
      <critical>If windows-kill returns "invalid window ID format: window IDs not allowed", you passed @N — retry with the name</critical>
    </step>

    <step n="8" title="Amend-protocol for in-flight workers (optional)">
      <condition>User changes scope or protocol mid-session while a worker is still running</condition>
      <action>Send via windows-message a [SUPERVISOR:AMEND] or [SUPERVISOR:AMEND-PROTOCOL] block explaining the new instruction. The worker will apply it to the current task.</action>
      <example>New save-path rule, new response format, additional scope item.</example>
    </step>

    <step n="8a" title="Findings-driven replan (autonomous)">
      <condition>An accepted worker's RECOMMENDATION materially changes the queued plan — demotes a primary surface, refutes a downstream worker's premise, adds a prerequisite, or identifies a queued worker as now-pointless.</condition>
      <action>Update the queue AUTONOMOUSLY:
        - If a queued worker is now pointless, mark its task deleted + log reason in synthesis.
        - If a queued worker now needs narrower/broader scope, rewrite its task-message template — do not ask.
        - If a new follow-up emerged and fits budget, insert at the correct dependency position per &lt;ranking&gt;.</action>
      <autonomy-ref>Apply per &lt;autonomy-policy&gt; — replan is not user-gated.</autonomy-ref>
      <report>In the step-9 synthesis, list every queue change (added / killed / rewritten) with the finding that drove it. This is the user-facing receipt, not a gate.</report>
    </step>

    <step n="9" title="Synthesize (does NOT terminate the session)">
      <condition>all workers have been killed</condition>
      <action>Merge all accepted file= contents into a single user-facing answer. State overlaps and conflicts explicitly. Keep it tight.</action>
      <action>For long-running sessions, consider writing a session-synthesis .md (e.g. NN_session-&lt;topic&gt;.md) into research-root that cites each per-worker file and captures the consolidated state. The user often asks for this at the end anyway.</action>
      <action critical="true">Writing synthesis does NOT return control to the user. After synthesis, re-run §8a against the synthesis's OWN "proposed next wave" / "queue changes" / "follow-ups" sections. If any listed workers are executable (scope fully self-contained — no user-only authorization required), LOOP BACK to §3 (fan-out decision) and spawn in parallel. Return to the user ONLY when the synthesis's replan produces zero new executable workers AND a real &lt;stop-conditions&gt; rule fires. The flow is a LOOP (3→4→5→6→7→[5a]→[8a]→9→[9b]→3), not a one-pass.</action>
    </step>

    <step n="9b" title="Cycle completion and continuation">
      <condition>Step 9 synthesis is complete</condition>
      <action>Read .tmux-cli/tasks.yaml and mark all completed tasks as status=done.</action>
      <action>Read supervisor.max_cycles from .tmux-cli/setting.yaml (default: 0 = unlimited).</action>
      <action>Increment the cycle counter in tasks.yaml.</action>
      <check condition="pending tasks remain AND (max_cycles == 0 OR cycle &lt; max_cycles)">
        <action>Send /clear to SUPERVISOR_WID via windows-send.</action>
        <action>Send /tmux:supervisor .tmux-cli/tasks.yaml to SUPERVISOR_WID via windows-send.</action>
        <action>STOP — a fresh supervisor instance takes over with the updated tasks.yaml as input.</action>
      </check>
      <check condition="max_cycles reached (cycle >= max_cycles AND max_cycles > 0)">
        <action>Print to user: "Cycle limit reached ({cycle}/{max_cycles}). Remaining pending tasks: [list task names]."</action>
        <action>STOP.</action>
      </check>
      <check condition="no pending tasks remain">
        <action>Normal stop — all work is complete.</action>
      </check>
    </step>
  </flow>

  <task-message-template>
    <note>REFERENCE ONLY — this template is assembled server-side by windows-spawn-worker. You do NOT need to format or send it manually. Shown here for documentation of what the worker receives.</note>
    <template>
SUPERVISOR_WID=&lt;your SUPERVISOR_WID name&gt;
SELF_WID=&lt;the execute-N name&gt;
SUBTASK: &lt;one-line label&gt;

SCOPE:
Full spec is in &lt;context-file-path&gt; — read it and follow it.

&lt;multi-line scope summary — files, directories, what to implement or investigate&gt;

CONTEXT:
&lt;multi-line supporting context — prior findings, constraints, non-goals&gt;

DELIVERABLE (write these sections INSIDE the report .md; do NOT paste them into tmux):
- FINDINGS: &gt;=3 bullets, each with file path or symbol reference
- RISKS: bullets OR the literal word "none"
- RECOMMENDATION: 1–3 sentences, must contain a verb of decision (use|avoid|rewrite|keep|split|merge)
- FILES: absolute paths touched or cited, one per line

RESPONSE PROTOCOL (MANDATORY):
1. Save the full report to .tmux-cli/research/{y-m-d-hh}/execute-&lt;N&gt;-&lt;slug&gt;.md
   with headings ## FINDINGS / ## RISKS / ## RECOMMENDATION / ## FILES plus any supporting detail.
   Pick a descriptive &lt;slug&gt; (kebab-case, ≤40 chars).
2. Reply via windows-message to SUPERVISOR_WID with ONLY:
   [EXECUTE:DONE wid=&lt;self&gt; sup=&lt;supervisor&gt; file=&lt;abs-path-to-your-md&gt;]
   Do NOT inline FINDINGS/RISKS/RECOMMENDATION/FILES in the tmux message. The file IS the report.
3. [EXECUTE:NEED_INPUT wid=&lt;self&gt; sup=&lt;supervisor&gt; ...] and [EXECUTE:FAILED wid=&lt;self&gt; sup=&lt;supervisor&gt; reason=...] may carry a short (&lt;200 char) inline reason.
4. If the supervisor sends [EXECUTE:PUSHBACK ...], update the SAME .md file and re-tag [EXECUTE:DONE wid=&lt;self&gt; sup=&lt;supervisor&gt; file=&lt;same-path&gt;].
    </template>
  </task-message-template>

  <execution-rules>
    <rule>windows-spawn-worker: single atomic call to spawn a worker (creates window, sends /tmux:execute, sends task message with DELIVERABLE + RESPONSE PROTOCOL)</rule>
    <rule>NEVER assemble spawn steps manually — always use windows-spawn-worker</rule>
    <rule>windows-message: all subsequent supervisor→worker communication (answers, pushbacks, reminders, amends)</rule>
    <rule>windows-kill: only on accepted DONE or terminal FAILED; never on SUPERVISOR_WID; pass window NAME</rule>
    <rule>Always Read the file cited in a DONE before applying the gap catalogue; never rely on the (absent) inline body</rule>
    <rule>If a worker sends DONE without file=, REMIND once; do not accept an inline-body DONE as a shortcut</rule>
    <rule>windows-send: used ONLY for self-directed cycle-restart commands to SUPERVISOR_WID in step 9b (/clear, /tmux:supervisor)</rule>
  </execution-rules>

  <stop-conditions>
    <rule>STOP and return user-facing synthesis ONLY when one of:
      - All queued workers completed AND findings-driven replan (step 8a) produced no new executable workers.
      - 2 consecutive FAILEDs on the same subtask class after narrowing.
      - Headline finding requiring user-only authorization (credentials, out-of-band intent, scope change beyond project).
      - Token/time budget exhausted (if user set one).
      - Cycle limit reached (supervisor.max_cycles in .tmux-cli/setting.yaml; step 9b).
      - STOP GATE triggered (step 1c) — unfinished tasks from a previous run.
      - Explicit user interrupt.</rule>
    <not-stop>These are NOT stop conditions — resolve autonomously per &lt;autonomy-policy&gt;:
      - "I have two reasonable options" → pick per &lt;ranking&gt;.
      - "Queued worker scope needs adjustment" → adjust and continue.
      - "Worker recommended a new follow-up" → add and continue.
      - "Worker finding contradicts a prior worker" → record; most-recent-with-most-evidence is truth-of-record.
      - "I just wrote a session-synthesis .md" → synthesis does not terminate the session; re-run §8a against its own contents and loop to §3 if new workers are executable.
      - "A plan document I wrote says Stage N after Stage M closes" / "wave N+1 after wave N" → self-imposed organizational gate; NOT user-imposed authorization. Continue through stages.
      - "A recommended wave-N+1 set exists in synthesis" → those are §8a replan items; spawn them in parallel per &lt;ranking&gt; unless stop-conditions actually fire.</not-stop>
  </stop-conditions>

  <llm final="true">
    <critical-rules>
      • DO NOT use sleep; idle is the trigger
      • DO NOT kill your own SUPERVISOR_WID
      • DO NOT treat stop-hook idle notifications as untagged-output violations — they are expected lifecycle
      • DO NOT advance state on untagged non-idle output — reply once with REMIND and keep waiting
      • DO NOT pass @N to windows-kill — use the window NAME
      • DO NOT accept DONE without file=&lt;abs-path&gt; — REMIND to use file-only protocol
      • DO NOT spawn any worker (step 4) before tasks.yaml is written and verified (step 3b) — this is a blocking gate, no exceptions
      • DO NOT violate &lt;autonomy-policy&gt; — never ask the user outside the two defined exits
      • DO NOT default to serial — default to maximum parallelism; serialize only when later worker's scope is literally unconstructable without prior worker's output
      • DO NOT let a running worker finish on a now-pointless scope — amend or kill via [SUPERVISOR:AMEND]/[SUPERVISOR:KILL] when new findings refute its premise (step 5a)
      • DO NOT skip the step-5a effectivity check after each DONE — it is the mechanism that keeps the pool effective, not just busy
      • DO NOT treat self-written plan documents (stage gates, "wave 6 after wave 5", "Stage 2 after Stage 1", "deferred to next session", numbered-wave boundaries) as user-imposed pauses — they are organizational, not authorization boundaries; continue per &lt;autonomy-policy&gt;
      • DO NOT stop after writing a session-synthesis .md — re-run §8a against the synthesis itself; if it names executable follow-up workers in "proposed next wave" / "queue changes", spawn them per §3 fan-out, do not return to the user
    </critical-rules>
  </llm>
</task>
