<task id="task-list" name="Backend task queue: reconcile, list, consume">
  <objective>Make the backend task queue truthful and actionable: (1) RECONCILE — settle every locally-consumed task whose goal finished (goal done → task resolved, goal failed → task failed) via task-update-status; (2) LIST — render all unresolved tasks; (3) CONSUME (opt-in) — claim tasks and convert them into taskvisor goals, recording the task↔goal mapping so a later run can reconcile them. The lifecycle contract: task-claim is ALWAYS called before any work is taken, and task-update-status ALWAYS marks the outcome.</objective>

  <glossary>
    <term name="MODE">"list" (default) or "consume" — set by a `consume` token in $ARGUMENTS.</term>
    <term name="N">Consume count: integer following the `consume` token. Default 1, hard cap 3.</term>
    <term name="FILTERS">Optional `category=&lt;c&gt;` and `severity=&lt;s&gt;` tokens in $ARGUMENTS. Validate against the closed sets (category: plan, supervisor, validator, execute, general; severity: critical, warning, info) and reject unknown values naming the allowed ones.</term>
    <term name="MAPPING_FILE">.tmux-cli/task-goals.yaml — the local task↔goal ledger: `mappings: [{task_id, goal_id, title, claimed_at}]`. Created on first consume; absence means nothing to reconcile.</term>
    <term name="GOALS_FILE">.tmux-cli/goals.yaml — read-only here (atomic-rename writes make unlocked reads safe). NEVER written by this command.</term>
  </glossary>

  <lane-gate name="solo-lane" title="Solo-lane gate (LANE GATE G1–G5)">
    <decision-rule>ALL of G1–G4 must hold AND the demotion veto must not fire → lane=solo; any miss or a fired veto → full. Evaluated UPSTREAM only; executing agents never self-declare.</decision-rule>
    <criterion id="G1">Exactly one unit of work (single backend task at consume; exactly 1 pending task at plan step 3d).</criterion>
    <criterion id="G2">Every green-state check is a deterministic bare command (grep/test/build) — verification needs no semantic judgment.</criterion>
    <criterion id="G3">Localized edit: no new files, no new public API/schema; expected change touches &lt;=2 existing files (estimated from proposed_fix / spec).</criterion>
    <criterion id="G4">Not critical: task severity in {info, warning} / priority below critical tier.</criterion>
    <criterion id="G5">Runtime demotion (statemachine.go — informational here, enforced in Go): solo honored only on validation cycle 1 — any validation failure, stuck recovery, or retry permanently demotes to full.</criterion>
    <veto id="V" title="Demotion veto — G5 permanence">A solo verdict additionally requires goal.md `## Lane` != full (and the goal's goals.yaml entry lane != full when readable). Either surface reading `full` is a prior-G5-demotion record: the veto fires and the verdict is full regardless of G1–G4 — a demoted goal can never re-enter solo. Absent/unreadable Lane data does NOT fire the veto (it blocks recorded demotions; it is not an affirmation — the fails-closed rule below applies to criteria, not to V).</veto>
    <evaluation-sources>Consume step 3.2 → severity / proposed_fix / the derived validate commands. Plan step 3d → G1 by branch condition; G2 from goal.md `## Validation Rules` + `## Investigation Config` (every investigator must be command-type/pure-command — semantic types like code-review miss G2); G3 from module scope in the research context; G4 from the goal's goals.yaml entry priority &lt; 10 (read-only; atomic-rename writes make unlocked reads safe), falling back to goal.md `## Lane` == solo (consume already passed G4); neither readable → G4 fails closed → full. Veto V → goal.md `## Lane` + the goal's goals.yaml entry lane (read-only; atomic-rename writes make unlocked reads safe). Missing data → criterion fails closed. The staleness gate (consume substep 3.2) runs BEFORE G1–G4 — a stale task is failed and dropped before any lane evaluation.</evaluation-sources>
    <note id="creation-seam">Creation-seam enforcement is enum-only plus two named machine cross-checks in goal-create (internal/mcp tools_taskvisor.go GoalCreate): REJECT lane=solo with an empty validate list (G2 proxy) and WARN-LOG a lane=solo scope spanning &gt;1 top-level directory (G3 proxy). Everything else in G1–G4 remains operator-evaluated convention at the two entry points.</note>
    <note id="B9b-lane-independence">investigate.xml step 2f's inline fast-path is lane-INDEPENDENT by design (B9b): ANY all-pure-command RERUN set inlines in-window, full lane included (goal-061 post-mortem, internal/taskvisor/inline.go). inv_spawned=0 on a full-lane goal whose rerun investigators are all pure-command is EXPECTED behavior, not a lane leak.</note>
  </lane-gate>

  <llm critical="true">
    <mandate>NEVER take work without claiming first — task-claim precedes goal-create, no exceptions</mandate>
    <mandate>NEVER write GOALS_FILE — goals are created ONLY via the goal-create MCP tool; the only file this command writes is MAPPING_FILE</mandate>
    <mandate>NEVER mark a task resolved unless its mapped goal Status is "done" in GOALS_FILE — resolution is earned by the validated goal, not assumed</mandate>
    <mandate>NEVER retry-loop a failed status update — 403/404/422 means another actor advanced the task; drop the mapping with a warning and move on</mandate>
    <mandate>Consume is opt-in and capped at 3 per invocation — never drain the queue</mandate>
  </llm>

  <flow>
    <step n="0" title="Parse arguments and preflight">
      <action>Tokenize $ARGUMENTS; extract MODE, N, FILTERS per the glossary. Unknown tokens → print usage and STOP.</action>
      <action>Read .tmux-cli/setting.yaml and resolve API enablement (flat `apiEnabled` wins over nested `api.enabled`).</action>
      <check condition="reporting disabled">
        <action>Print: "Task API is disabled — set api.enabled: true in .tmux-cli/setting.yaml and retry."</action>
        <action>STOP</action>
      </check>
    </step>

    <step n="1" title="Reconcile (always runs, before listing)">
      <note>FALLBACK actor: the taskvisor daemon now PUSH-resolves a mapped backend task at the moment its goal reaches a durable terminal state (goal→done ⇒ resolved, goal→failed / blocked_by=convergence-circuit-breaker ⇒ failed) and atomically drops the entry from MAPPING_FILE. Reconcile here is the FALLBACK that settles everything the push did not — offline/API-down runs, daemon crashes, and cascade-failed downstream goals — so it must keep reading the same `{task_id, goal_id, title, claimed_at}` ledger shape the daemon writes. Both actors are idempotent: a push that already resolved a task simply leaves no mapping for reconcile to see.</note>
      <action>Read MAPPING_FILE. Absent or empty → skip to step 2.</action>
      <action>Read GOALS_FILE once (read-only).</action>
      <action>For each mapping entry, find its goal_id in GOALS_FILE and decide:</action>
      <branch condition="goal Status == done">
        <action>Call task-update-status with id=task_id, status=resolved, resolution={goal_id, finished_at from the goal, summary: "goal validated and completed"}.</action>
        <action>On success: remove the mapping entry; record "task {task_id} → resolved (goal {goal_id} done)".</action>
      </branch>
      <branch condition="goal Status == failed, OR Status == blocked with blocked_by == convergence-circuit-breaker">
        <action>Call task-update-status with id=task_id, status=failed, resolution={goal_id, reason: the goal's failed_by/blocked_by value}.</action>
        <action>On success: remove the mapping entry; record "task {task_id} → failed (goal {goal_id} {reason})".</action>
      </branch>
      <branch condition="goal Status is pending/running/blocked (non-breaker)">
        <action>Keep the mapping; record as in-flight for the step-2 table.</action>
      </branch>
      <branch condition="goal_id not present in GOALS_FILE (pruned/re-planned)">
        <action>Remove the mapping and print: "WARNING: goal {goal_id} no longer exists — task {task_id} left in its current backend state; handle manually via task-update-status."</action>
      </branch>
      <check condition="task-update-status returns forbidden/not-found/invalid-transition">
        <action>Another actor advanced the task. Remove the mapping, print a one-line warning with the error, and continue with the next entry — never retry.</action>
      </check>
      <action>Rewrite MAPPING_FILE with the surviving entries (write the full file once, after the loop).</action>
      <action>Print a reconcile summary line: "Reconciled: {r} resolved, {f} failed, {k} in-flight, {d} dropped." (omit when all four are 0).</action>
    </step>

    <step n="2" title="List unresolved tasks">
      <action>The backend filters by a single status per call. Compose "unresolved" from three task-list MCP calls: status=new, status=claimed, status=in_progress — each with FILTERS applied and limit=50.</action>
      <action>Merge the pages, de-duplicate by id, and sort: severity (critical &gt; warning &gt; info), then created_at ascending (oldest first).</action>
      <action>Render one table:</action>
      <template>| id | sev | category | status | age | title |
mark rows that appear in MAPPING_FILE with "→ {goal_id}" appended to status (locally in-flight);
age = humanized now − created_at (e.g. 3d, 5h).</template>
      <action>Use description_preview only — never call task-get for rows the user did not ask about.</action>
      <action>Print totals per status; when any call reports total &gt; limit, print: "more available — narrow with category=/severity= filters".</action>
      <check condition="all three calls return zero tasks">
        <action>Print: "No unresolved tasks." Then STOP (consume mode has nothing to claim either).</action>
      </check>
    </step>

    <step n="3" title="Consume — claim and convert to goals (MODE == consume only)">
      <action>Repeat up to N times (stop early when nothing claimable):</action>
      <substep n="3.1" title="Claim BEFORE any work">
        <action>Call task-claim with FILTERS (category/severity).</action>
        <check condition="claimed == false">
          <action>Print: "Nothing claimable (filters: {FILTERS})." and exit the consume loop.</action>
        </check>
        <action>Use the returned task object verbatim — id, title, description, proposed_fix, expected_green_state, severity.</action>
      </substep>
      <substep n="3.2" title="Convert to a goal via goal-create">
        <params>
          <param name="description">Task title, truncated to 120 chars.</param>
          <param name="acceptance">expected_green_state split into individually checkable items, plus: "Backend task {id} is satisfied: {expected_green_state first line}".</param>
          <param name="validate">Concrete bare commands (no shell wrappers, no &amp;&amp; chains), derived in priority order: (1) backticked/recognizable commands inside expected_green_state, (2) commands inside proposed_fix, (3) a minimal deterministic check the green state implies (a test run or a grep against the named artifact). MUST be non-empty — if no command is derivable, the task is not consumable: print "task {id} has no checkable green state — refine it on the backend first", call task-update-status id status=failed resolution={reason: "unconsumable: no derivable validate command"}, drop it, and continue the loop.</param>
          <param name="context">Full task description + "## Proposed fix\n" + proposed_fix + "\n## Origin\nBackend task {id}; resolution is marked automatically by /tmux:task-list reconcile once this goal completes."</param>
          <param name="priority">critical→10, warning→5, info→0.</param>
          <param name="max_retries">3</param>
          <param name="lane">"solo" iff the solo-lane gate passes (gate action below); on any G-miss OMIT this param entirely — absent lane = full, never pass lane: "full".</param>
        </params>
        <staleness-gate title="STALENESS GATE — verify the claimed task still describes the current tree (runs AFTER the validate derivation above, BEFORE the lane gate)">
          <check n="1" title="Baseline-run every derived validate command">Run each derived validate command against the current tree. Exit 0 = green, non-zero = red. ALL green → the task's green state already holds: call task-update-status id status=failed resolution={reason: "unconsumable: stale — green state already holds at baseline"}, create NO goal, drop the task, continue the loop. Baseline-red is NOT sufficient proof of consumability — red can mean "fix not applied" OR "green state obsolete" (check 3 disambiguates).</check>
          <check n="2" title="Verify Evidence quotes against current files">Pick 1–2 verbatim quotes from the task's cited Evidence (quoted text, never line numbers — line citations rot fastest). Each must still appear in the cited file. Missing quote → re-read the cited region and judge: defect GONE → fail as stale (check-1 reason path); defect MOVED → update the goal context param with current line numbers and proceed. A task with no quotable Evidence skips this check — checks 1 and 3 still gate.</check>
          <check n="3" title="Baseline-red must be fix-shaped">goal-create requires at least one baseline-red discriminator whose red-ness is explained by the MISSING FIX, not by a contradicting design change — a red that contradicts the live design means the task's green state is obsolete and now wrong: fail as stale (check-1 reason path).</check>
          <note id="undo">If a stale goal slipped through anyway, the sanctioned undo is `tmux-cli taskvisor goal delete &lt;id&gt;` (single-goal removal; refuses a running goal). goal-prune is nuclear — it wipes ALL taskvisor goal state and is never for single-goal removal.</note>
        </staleness-gate>
        <action>Apply the solo-lane gate (the &lt;lane-gate name="solo-lane"&gt; block at the top of this file) — evaluated AFTER the validate-command derivation and the STALENESS GATE above (G2 judges the derived commands) and BEFORE calling goal-create: G1 from the single claimed task, G2 from the derived validate commands, G3 from proposed_fix, G4 from severity. Log one per-criterion verdict line, e.g. `lane gate: G1 ✓ G2 ✓ G3 ✗ G4 ✓ → full`. ALL of G1–G4 hold → pass `lane: "solo"` to goal-create; any miss → omit the lane param.</action>
        <check condition="goal-create fails">
          <action>Print the error. The task stays claimed on the backend (there is no unclaim) — print: "task {id} remains claimed; re-run /tmux:task-list consume after fixing, or advance it manually with task-update-status." Continue the loop.</action>
        </check>
      </substep>
      <substep n="3.3" title="Record mapping + mark in_progress">
        <action>Append {task_id, goal_id, title, claimed_at: now UTC} to MAPPING_FILE (create the file with a `mappings:` root on first use).</action>
        <action>Call task-update-status with id=task_id, status=in_progress — work is queued, the claim is acted on.</action>
        <action>Print: "task {id} → {goal_id} (claimed, in_progress)".</action>
      </substep>
    </step>

    <step n="4" title="Auto-start taskvisor (MODE == consume, at least one goal created)">
      <check condition="MODE != consume OR no goal was created this run">
        <action>Skip this step entirely.</action>
      </check>
      <substep n="4.1" title="Assess daemon state">
        <action>PID_ALIVE: .tmux-cli/taskvisor.pid exists AND `kill -0 $(cat .tmux-cli/taskvisor.pid)` succeeds.</action>
        <action>ACTIVE: .tmux-cli/taskvisor-active exists.</action>
        <check condition="PID_ALIVE AND ACTIVE">
          <action>Print: "taskvisor is already active — {goal ids} will be scheduled on the next tick." Skip to substep 4.4.</action>
        </check>
      </substep>
      <substep n="4.2" title="Ensure the daemon process is running">
        <check condition="NOT PID_ALIVE">
          <action>Run: tmux-cli taskvisor restart</action>
          <check condition="restart errors (no session / no taskvisor window)">
            <action>Print: "Cannot auto-start: {error}. Start a session with tmux-cli start, then run: tmux-cli taskvisor restart — the queued goals will execute on activation."</action>
            <action>Skip to substep 4.4 (degraded — goals stay queued).</action>
          </check>
        </check>
      </substep>
      <substep n="4.3" title="Activate and confirm">
        <action>Call the taskvisor-start MCP tool (validates pending goals exist and writes the .tmux-cli/taskvisor-start marker; the idle daemon consumes it on its next poll).</action>
        <action>Poll for .tmux-cli/taskvisor-active every 3s, up to 30s.</action>
        <check condition="taskvisor-active appears">
          <action>Print: "taskvisor ACTIVE — executing {goal ids}."</action>
        </check>
        <check condition="timeout">
          <action>Print the last ~10 lines of .tmux-cli/logs/taskvisor.log and: "Daemon did not activate within 30s — inspect the taskvisor window; goals remain queued."</action>
        </check>
      </substep>
      <substep n="4.4" title="Reconcile reminder">
        <action>Print: "Run /tmux:task-list again after the run to reconcile results back to the backend."</action>
      </substep>
    </step>
  </flow>

  <execution-rules>
    <rule>Order is fixed: reconcile → list → consume → auto-start; reconcile always runs so the rendered list is truthful</rule>
    <rule>Claim before work; in_progress after goal creation; resolved/failed only from the mapped goal's terminal status</rule>
    <rule>Only file written: MAPPING_FILE (full-file rewrite after reconcile, append on consume)</rule>
    <rule>GOALS_FILE is read-only; goals are created exclusively through goal-create</rule>
    <rule>Status-update failures (403/404/422) drop the mapping with a warning — never retried, never fatal to the run</rule>
    <rule>Consume cap: 3 per invocation regardless of N</rule>
    <rule>Consume always ends with the daemon executing (or a named, actionable reason why not) — queued-but-idle is a failure of this spec</rule>
    <rule>The solo-lane gate is applied exactly ONCE per claimed task — here at step 3.2, upstream; executing surfaces (supervisor/investigate) only READ the lane, never re-evaluate or self-declare it</rule>
    <rule>Mis-created goal undo: tmux-cli taskvisor goal delete &lt;id&gt; — the sanctioned single-goal removal; goal-prune is nuclear (wipes ALL goal state) and never for single-goal removal</rule>
  </execution-rules>
</task>
