<task id="task-plan-generate" name="Goal generation from discovery outputs">
  <objective>Read validated discovery outputs from docs/architecture/*, generate a precise sequence of taskvisor goals. Each goal is atomic, testable, and has explicit dependencies. Goal IDs are 1-indexed: goal-001, goal-002, etc. This skill starts with a validation gate (Step 0) that checks cross-file consistency before any goal generation begins.</objective>

  <input>
    <note>No $ARGUMENTS — reads docs/architecture/* files implicitly from the working directory. These files are produced by /tmux:task-plan-discover.</note>
  </input>

  <output>
    <primary>goals.yaml with all generated goals — each goal has ID, description, depends_on, phase, acceptance criteria, and max_retries.</primary>
    <secondary>Per-goal goal.md files with Description, Dependencies, Deliverables, Acceptance Criteria, Test Environment reference, Context, Not In Scope, and Investigation Config sections.</secondary>
  </output>

  <requirements critical="true">
    <mcp>tmux-cli MCP server REQUIRED (for goal-create)</mcp>
  </requirements>

  <glossary>
    <term name="LANG">Detected primary language slug (e.g. "php", "go", "python", "node"). Inherited from discovery session state, confirmed in docs/architecture/product-brief.md or project manifest.</term>
    <term name="FRAMEWORK">Detected framework (e.g. "symfony", "laravel", "express", "gin"). Inherited from discovery session state, confirmed in docs/architecture/product-brief.md or project manifest.</term>
    <term name="TEMPLATE_DIR">Path to language-specific templates. Resolved via two-tier lookup: templates/&lt;LANG&gt;-&lt;FRAMEWORK&gt;/ first, then templates/&lt;LANG&gt;/, then templates/_base/. Inherited from discovery.</term>
    <term name="BC_LIST">List of bounded context names extracted from docs/architecture/bounded-contexts.md level-3 headings under "Bounded Context Inventory". Built in Step 0.</term>
    <term name="AGGREGATE_MAP">Map of BC name to list of aggregate names. Extracted from bounded-contexts.md "Aggregates:" fields and cross-checked with domain-model.md headings. Built in Step 0.</term>
    <term name="ENDPOINT_MAP">Map of BC name to list of API endpoints. Extracted from docs/architecture/api-endpoints.md "Bounded Context" table cells. Built in Step 0.</term>
    <term name="GOAL_COUNT">Total number of goals to generate, calculated from the goal count formula: endpoints + auth_flows + listeners + cross_cutting + decisions + (aggregates * 2) + infrastructure. Computed in Step 1 (goal generation).</term>
  </glossary>

  <llm critical="true">
    <mandate>NEVER generate goals if Step 0 validation fails — abort with actionable diagnostics</mandate>
    <mandate>ALWAYS read discovery data from docs/architecture/* files on disk, never from conversation context (G-16)</mandate>
    <mandate>NEVER modify discovery output files — generation is read-only on discovery outputs, write-only on goals</mandate>
    <mandate>ALWAYS validate ALL consistency rules before reporting errors — collect every error, never stop at the first</mandate>
    <mandate>EVERY goal-creation call (goal-create MCP / `taskvisor goal add`) MUST pass structured validate (>=1 project-runnable command), acceptance (>=1 criterion), and scope when the file footprint is known — prose-only rules in goal.md are invisible to the daemon (see the validate-acceptance-mandate in the &lt;conventions&gt; block)</mandate>
  </llm>


  <conventions>
      <rule critical="true" id="CMD-CONV">COMMAND EXECUTION CONVENTION — BINDING ON EVERY LATER STEP. Emit every validate / Investigation-Config command BARE, host-style (`composer install`, `vendor/bin/phpstan analyse --level=9`, `npx playwright test …`). Do NOT hand-prefix with `docker compose exec …`. At dispatch the taskvisor daemon wraps each command by tool family: PHP toolchain (php, composer, bin/console, vendor/bin/*, phpunit, phpstan, ecs, deptrac) → the {{APP_SVC}} container; Node/browser tools (node, npm, npx, playwright) → the {{NODE_SVC}} container; pure host/file commands (test, grep, ls, python3, docker, curl against a published port) left untouched. In local mode the daemon wrap is a no-op, so bare commands run on the host exactly as today. (The wrap is idempotent, so a stray hand-written prefix is harmless — but do not add one.)</rule>
      <rule id="HTTP-CONV">HTTP / health-check convention: a validate command that curls the running app MUST target the Base URL / published host port from test-environment.md (e.g. http://localhost:8080), NEVER a hardcoded port (no :8000). The daemon does NOT rewrite ports — emit the published one. Once the runtime stack is up the app is reachable on the host's published port.</rule>
      <rule critical="true" id="NODE-TOOL-CONV">NODE-TOOLING CONVENTION — BINDING (governs WHETHER a Node command is emitted; the daemon wraps a Node command into {{NODE_SVC}} but never REMOVES one). A Node-runtime tool (node, npm, npx, playwright, swagger-cli) may be emitted ONLY when test-environment.md indicates a frontend/Playwright toolchain (HAS_FRONTEND==true or Playwright installed) — then task-R provisions {{NODE_SVC}} and the daemon routes the command there. In a PHP project that is API-only / Playwright-N/A, NEVER emit a Node-tool command — use the PHP-native equivalent (e.g. validate OpenAPI via `bin/console nelmio:apidoc:dump`, not `npx swagger-cli validate`; never emit `npx playwright` — see the steps 3.18/3.19 guards). The Node-runtime requirement, when present, is recorded in the goal-002 deliverables.</rule>
      <rule critical="true" id="ENSURE-STACK-CONV" condition="HAS_DATABASE">ENSURE-STACK CONVENTION — BINDING ON EVERY LATER STEP. Two parts: (1) SCAFFOLD PRODUCER — goal-002 MUST deliver bin/ensure-test-stack.sh (executable, #!/bin/sh -e, three phases: stack up → test-env migrations → test fixtures); acceptance criterion: `test -x bin/ensure-test-stack.sh`. The script body comes from the language template (.tmux-cli/templates/{{LANG}}-{{FRAMEWORK}}/fixtures.md "Ensure-stack script" section). (2) CONSUMER — every goal whose validate contains an E2E or host-HTTP probe MUST list `bash bin/ensure-test-stack.sh` as a SEPARATE validate line immediately BEFORE the probe line. The daemon runs each validate line independently; never &amp;&amp;-join the ensure-stack invocation with any other command.</rule>
      <rule critical="true" id="HTTP-WAIT-CONV">HTTP-WAIT CONVENTION — BINDING. Never emit a fixed `sleep N` before an HTTP or database readiness probe. Use either: (a) docker mode (preferred): compose service healthchecks + `docker compose up -d --wait` — the --wait flag blocks until all healthchecks pass, then probe; or (b) fallback bounded poll (POSIX sh): `i=0; until curl -sf {{BASE_URL}}/path; do i=$((i+1)); [ $i -ge 30 ] &amp;&amp; exit 1; sleep 2; done`. The bounded poll is the canonical form for Gate-0 / scaffold goals where ensure-stack does not yet exist. Interaction: in post-scaffold goals, ENSURE-STACK-CONV (H1) serializes stack-up before probes — HTTP-WAIT covers the first-boot path where no ensure-stack script exists yet.</rule>
      <rule critical="true" id="E2E-ARTIFACT-CONV" condition="HAS_FRONTEND">E2E FAILURE ARTIFACT CONVENTION — BINDING. When E2E runner is present (HAS_FRONTEND==true), scaffold MUST deliver a playwright.config.ts with: trace: 'retain-on-failure' (captures traces on original failure without requiring in-runner retries), screenshot: 'only-on-failure', reporter: [['list'], ['html', { open: 'never' }]] (non-interactive — list for daemon stdout, html for post-mortem with no browser auto-open), outputDir: 'test-results', retries: 0 (daemon retries at goal level via code_retries budget; zero in-runner retries preserve maximum signal fidelity for the convergence guard). Scaffold MUST add test-results/ to the project .gitignore. Every E2E investigator fail criteria in generated goals MUST cite test-results/ as the artifact path for traces and screenshots.</rule>
      <rule critical="true" id="DOCKER-RUNTIME-FRONTLOAD" condition="RUN_TARGET=docker">In docker mode goal-002 MUST first MATERIALIZE AND START the dev runtime container BEFORE running any PHP-toolchain command. Prepend a fan-out task "task-R" (runtime, prerequisite, runs before task-0): create docker-compose.yaml (service {{APP_SVC}} built from a dev Dockerfile carrying PHP {{php_version}} + the required extensions, plus the DB/services + host:container port mappings from test-environment.md Published Ports) and that Dockerfile, then start the stack with `docker compose up -d --build`. task-0 (composer) and tasks 1-2 then add depends_on=task-R; their PHP commands are emitted BARE and the daemon wraps them into {{APP_SVC}} at dispatch (CMD-CONV). This is the DEV runtime — it replaces the late-stage compose goal for development; step 3.26 is reserved for PRODUCTION deployment extras (ADR-driven) only. Add SC-00 "docker-compose.yaml + dev Dockerfile exist and `docker compose up -d` brings {{APP_SVC}} up healthy" to the acceptance array as the first criterion. ADDITIONALLY when HAS_FRONTEND==true / Playwright is applicable: task-R MUST also add the {{NODE_SVC}} service (default "e2e", FROM an official Playwright image, same compose network as {{APP_SVC}}, with the app source mounted) so the daemon can route bare browser/E2E commands into it — and extend SC-00 to require {{NODE_SVC}} up too. When API-only, do NOT add {{NODE_SVC}}.</rule>
      <rule critical="true" id="E2E-ENV-CONV" condition="HAS_DATABASE">E2E ENVIRONMENT CONTRACT — BINDING. The HTTP vhost that E2E/host-HTTP probes hit MUST serve the same env/DB that bin/ensure-test-stack.sh seeds (--env=test). Concretely: (1) SCAFFOLD PINNING — goal-002's compose spec (docker mode) or .env.test (local mode) MUST pin APP_ENV=test for the E2E-facing service; acceptance criterion SC-18: `grep -q 'APP_ENV=test' docker-compose.yaml` or `grep -q 'APP_ENV=test' .env.test`. (2) HEALTH-CHECK EXPOSURE — the step 3.25 health-check goal's GET /health response MUST include `env` (kernel.environment) and `database` (connected DB name) fields; acceptance criterion HC-04: `curl -s {{BASE_URL}}/health | jq -e '.env == "test" and (.database | test("test"))'`. (3) GATE-0 RE-ASSERTION — after scaffold completes, Gate-0 re-validates the pinning via the same grep probe. Side-effect env keys (G7) extend this contract by adding their required env vars to the same pinning and health-exposure surface.</rule>
      <rule critical="true" id="E2E-SIDEFX-CONV" condition="HAS_DATABASE">E2E SIDE-EFFECT CONTRACT — extends E2E-ENV-CONV at the side-effect-env-keys seam. The E2E-serving test env MUST isolate all side effects so assertions are deterministic and no external system is contacted. Sub-clauses fire conditionally on feature presence from discovery/ADRs: (1) MAILER (condition: symfony/mailer in composer.json) — .env.test MUST contain MAILER_DSN=null://null. This is the Symfony Flex recipe default; the scaffold ASSERTS it (SC-23: `grep -q 'MAILER_DSN=null://null' .env.test`), it does NOT re-deliver it. Generated E2E specs for mail-sending flows (registration, password reset) assert application-visible outcomes (HTTP status, flash message, API response), never actual email delivery. (2) MESSENGER (condition: symfony/messenger in composer.json) — config/packages/test/messenger.yaml MUST exist and route ALL transports to sync:// (`framework: messenger: transports: async: dsn: 'sync://'`) so message handlers complete synchronously before E2E assertions run. The scaffold CREATES this file (SC-24: `test -f config/packages/test/messenger.yaml`). This is the DELTA — Symfony recipes do NOT default messenger to sync in test env. (3) HTTP-CLIENT (condition: symfony/http-client in composer.json) — generated E2E specs MUST assert application-visible outcomes (HTTP status codes, DB state changes, response bodies), NEVER actual external delivery or third-party service responses. No env-var mandate for http-client — isolation is a spec-generation rule, not a runtime config.</rule>
      <rule critical="true" id="E2E-DATA-ISOLATION-CONV" condition="HAS_DATABASE">E2E DATA ISOLATION — BINDING ON E2E-GENERATING STEPS (3.18, 3.19, 3.29). Fixture rows loaded by ensure-stack are READ-ONLY reference data for E2E specs — specs MUST NOT update, delete, or otherwise mutate seeded fixture rows. Each E2E spec creates its OWN mutable test data through the application's UI or API using unique keys (timestamp or UUID suffix, e.g. `Product-{uuid}`) so entities are identifiable and non-colliding across specs. Count and list assertions MUST filter to the spec's own created data (e.g. search by the unique key or filter by a known attribute) — never assert raw totals against the full table, because fixture rows and other specs' data coexist. Re-running doctrine:fixtures:load mid-suite is FORBIDDEN — the load is a purge-and-reload that destroys all spec-created data; the reset unit is the whole suite (one load via ensure-stack before the first spec). dama/doctrine-test-bundle transaction rollback does NOT apply to E2E tests — the Playwright/HTTP test runner and the application server use separate DB connections across process boundaries; do NOT prescribe it for E2E isolation.</rule>
      <rule critical="true" id="E2E-AUTH-STATE-CONV" condition="N_auth_flows>=1 AND HAS_FRONTEND">AUTHENTICATED E2E STATE REUSE — BINDING. When auth flows exist and Playwright is available, a single Playwright `setup` project logs in ONCE per role and writes storageState JSON to a gitignored deterministic path — all other authenticated E2E tests reuse the stored state instead of logging in per test. Concretely: (1) SCAFFOLD CONFIG — goal-002's playwright.config.ts (task-2, condition: HAS_FRONTEND AND N_auth_flows>=1) MUST define a `setup` project running playwright/auth.setup.ts that writes storageState to playwright/.auth/admin.json and playwright/.auth/user.json, plus an `authenticated` project declaring `dependencies: ['setup']` and `use: { storageState: 'playwright/.auth/admin.json' }`; acceptance criterion SC-21. playwright/.auth/ MUST be gitignored. (2) AUTH SETUP DELIVERY — the auth-bootstrap goal (step 3.16a, condition: HAS_FRONTEND) MUST include playwright/auth.setup.ts in its deliverables: the script reads credentials by env-var NAME from docs/architecture/test-environment.md (admin_identifier_env, admin_password_env — never hardcoded, GM-05), logs in as admin and regular user against the APP_ENV=test stack (E2E-ENV-CONV), and writes both storageState JSON files; acceptance criterion AU-11. (3) CONSUMER — every controller-action/E2E goal (step 3.18) whose action is auth_required MUST instruct the implementer to place the E2E test in the authenticated project (inherits storageState) instead of adding inline login steps. (4) PRESERVATION — auth-flow E2E specs (step 3.19) test the REAL login/register/logout UI and MUST NOT use storageState; storageState is a precondition shortcut for OTHER suites only. (5) STATE FRESHNESS — the setup project re-runs on every `npx playwright test` invocation (Playwright project dependencies always execute); ENSURE-STACK-CONV reseeds the DB before the Playwright run, so DB-backed sessions from a prior invocation are wiped — the always-re-auth default is the safe mandate.</rule>
        <scope-derivation>
          The `scope` param is the goal's declared file footprint (array of path globs / namespace prefixes) that the daemon's disjoint-scope co-scheduling gate reads to decide whether two goals may run CONCURRENTLY under MaxGoals&gt;1. DERIVE it from the goal's Deliverables file paths: emit the distinct directory globs that cover every deliverable (e.g. deliverables under src/Booking/Domain/ ⇒ scope ["src/Booking/Domain/**"]; a single file ⇒ that file path). CONSERVATIVE CONTRACT: overlap OR an omitted/unknown scope ⇒ the daemon SERIALIZES the goals (never co-schedules), so it is always safe to omit when the footprint is unclear. An explicit author-provided `scope:` overrides derivation. The runtime reads ONLY this persisted field — it never parses goal.md — so scope MUST be passed here to enable safe co-scheduling.
        </scope-derivation>
        <validate-acceptance-mandate>
          STRUCTURED-FIELDS MANDATE (applies to EVERY goal-creation call in this flow — MCP `goal-create` tool or `tmux-cli taskvisor goal add` CLI alike; see the matching execution-rule). Every call MUST pass:
          1. `--validate` / `validate` param: >=1 concrete, PROJECT-RUNNABLE command — resolved against the detected LANG/FRAMEWORK stack (e.g. `vendor/bin/phpstan analyse src/Booking/`, `go test ./internal/booking/`, `npx playwright test tests/e2e/booking.spec.ts`), NOT prose. A sentence describing what to check is not a validate entry; only a command the daemon can execute verbatim in the project is.
          2. `--acceptance` / `acceptance` param: >=1 criterion.
          3. `--scope` / `scope` param whenever the goal's file footprint is known (path globs per &lt;scope-derivation&gt; above). An empty/omitted scope ⇒ the goal SERIALIZES against ALL concurrent goals (the daemon's DisjointReadySet gate co-schedules only provably disjoint scopes) — scope is the price of parallelism. Omit only when the footprint is genuinely unknown (safe, but serial).
        </validate-acceptance-mandate>
  </conventions>

  <flow>
    <step n="0" title="Validate discovery outputs">
      <rule critical="true">This step is a blocking gate. If any validation error is found, abort with a numbered error list and do NOT proceed to Step 1.</rule>

      <substep n="0.1" title="File existence check">
        <action>Verify the following files and directories exist on disk using test -f / test -d:</action>
        <checklist>
          <file path="docs/architecture/bounded-contexts.md" required="always"/>
          <file path="docs/architecture/domain-model.md" required="always"/>
          <file path="docs/architecture/api-endpoints.md" required="always"/>
          <file path="docs/architecture/cross-cutting.md" required="always"/>
          <file path="docs/architecture/test-environment.md" required="always"/>
          <file path="docs/architecture/adrs/" required="always" type="directory"/>
          <file path="docs/architecture/context-map.md" required="multi-bc-only"/>
        </checklist>
        <action>For context-map.md: count the number of level-3 headings (### lines) under "Bounded Context Inventory" in bounded-contexts.md. If exactly one BC exists, skip the context-map.md check entirely (D-27). If two or more BCs exist, context-map.md is required.</action>
        <action>For each missing required file, collect an error: "Missing required file: docs/architecture/&lt;filename&gt; — run /tmux:task-plan-discover first"</action>
        <rule>Do not stop at the first missing file. Check all files and collect all errors.</rule>
      </substep>

      <substep n="0.2" title="Parse discovery files">
        <action>Read each discovery file and extract structured data:</action>
        <parse-instructions>
          <parse file="bounded-contexts.md">
            <extract what="BC names">Find all level-3 headings (### lines) under the "## Bounded Context Inventory" section. Each heading text is a BC name. Store as BC_LIST.</extract>
            <extract what="Aggregates per BC">For each BC heading, find the "- **Aggregates:** " field. Parse the comma-separated values after the colon as aggregate names (trim whitespace). Store as AGGREGATE_MAP[bc_name] = [aggregate_names].</extract>
          </parse>
          <parse file="domain-model.md">
            <extract what="Aggregate headings per BC">Find level-2 sections (## headings) — these are per-BC domain model files or sections. Under each, find level-3 headings (### lines) — these are aggregate names. Store for cross-checking with AGGREGATE_MAP.</extract>
            <extract what="Read model interfaces">For each aggregate, find "- Read model interface (query): " field. Store whether the value after the colon is empty or non-empty.</extract>
          </parse>
          <parse file="api-endpoints.md">
            <extract what="BC names from endpoints">Find all "| Bounded Context | " table rows. The value in the second column is a BC name. Collect unique BC names referenced by endpoints. Store as ENDPOINT_MAP keys.</extract>
            <extract what="List/search actions">Find endpoints where Method is GET and Path has no trailing ID segment (e.g. /api/bookings vs /api/bookings/{id}), or where Description contains keywords "list", "search", or "index". These are collection/list actions. Tag each with its BC name.</extract>
          </parse>
          <parse file="test-environment.md">
            <extract what="Required fields">Find and check non-emptiness of: base URL (line containing "Base URL" or "base_url"), test credentials (line containing "Test Credentials" or "test_credentials"), DB name (line containing "Test Database" or "DB name" or "db_name"), fixture command (line containing "Fixture Command" or "fixture_command"), Playwright status (line containing "Playwright" and "Status" or "playwright_status").</extract>
          </parse>
        </parse-instructions>
      </substep>

      <substep n="0.3" title="Cross-file consistency checks">
        <action>Apply these 5 validation rules. Collect all errors — do not stop at the first failure.</action>

        <rule n="1" name="BC consistency">Every BC name found in api-endpoints.md (from "Bounded Context" table cells) must have a matching ### heading in bounded-contexts.md under "Bounded Context Inventory". For each BC in api-endpoints.md that has no matching heading in bounded-contexts.md, collect error: "BC '&lt;name&gt;' found in api-endpoints.md but missing from bounded-contexts.md"</rule>

        <rule n="2" name="Aggregates per BC">Every BC listed in bounded-contexts.md must have at least one aggregate in domain-model.md (at least one ### heading under that BC's section). For each BC with zero aggregates, collect error: "BC '&lt;name&gt;' has no aggregates in domain-model.md — every BC must have at least one"</rule>

        <rule n="3" name="Read model for list actions">Every BC that has GET endpoints with collection paths (list/search actions) in api-endpoints.md must have a non-empty "Read model interface (query):" field on at least one aggregate in domain-model.md. For each BC with list actions but no read model interface, collect error: "BC '&lt;name&gt;' has list/search actions but no read model interface noted in domain-model.md"</rule>

        <rule n="4" name="Aggregate name match">Every aggregate name listed in bounded-contexts.md under "- **Aggregates:** " must match a ### heading in domain-model.md for that BC. Comparison is case-insensitive and whitespace-trimmed. For each mismatch, collect error: "Aggregate name mismatch for BC '&lt;bc_name&gt;': bounded-contexts.md has '&lt;name_a&gt;', domain-model.md has '&lt;name_b&gt;'"</rule>

        <rule n="5" name="Test environment completeness">test-environment.md must exist and contain non-empty values for all of: base URL, test credentials, DB name, fixture command, Playwright status. For each missing or empty field, collect error: "test-environment.md missing required field: &lt;field_name&gt;"</rule>
      </substep>

      <substep n="0.4" title="test-environment.md field validation">
        <action>This substep performs detailed field-by-field validation of test-environment.md. For each of the 5 required fields (base URL, test credentials, DB name, fixture command, Playwright status), verify:</action>
        <checks>
          <check field="base URL">Value after the field label is not empty, not just whitespace, and looks like a URL (contains :// or starts with http/https).</check>
          <check field="test credentials">Value after the field label is not empty — at minimum a username or token is specified.</check>
          <check field="DB name">Value after the field label is not empty and not just whitespace.</check>
          <check field="fixture command">Value after the field label is not empty — a concrete command string is present.</check>
          <check field="Playwright status">Value after the field label is not empty and contains one of: "installed", "not installed", "not applicable", "needs", or equivalent status indicator.</check>
        </checks>
        <action>For each field that fails validation, collect error: "test-environment.md missing required field: &lt;field_name&gt;"</action>
      </substep>

      <substep n="0.5" title="Report validation results">
        <branch condition="errors were collected in substeps 0.1-0.4">
          <action>Print all collected errors as a numbered list with file references:</action>
          <template>
Discovery output validation failed. Fix the following issues and retry:

{{#each errors}}
{{index}}. {{error_message}}
{{/each}}

Re-run /tmux:task-plan-discover to regenerate discovery outputs, or edit the files manually.
          </template>
          <action>ABORT. Do NOT proceed to Step 1.</action>
        </branch>

        <branch condition="no errors collected">
          <action>Print: "Discovery output validation passed — {{bc_count}} bounded contexts, {{aggregate_count}} aggregates, {{endpoint_bc_count}} BCs with endpoints verified."</action>
          <action>Store BC_LIST, AGGREGATE_MAP, and ENDPOINT_MAP for use in subsequent steps.</action>
          <action>Proceed to Step 0b.</action>
        </branch>
      </substep>
    </step>

    <step n="0b" title="First-run Preconditions backfill (idempotent)">
      <rule>Runs once per plan after Step 0 passes and BEFORE any goal generation. It brings PRE-EXISTING goal.md files (authored by an earlier plan that predates the Preconditions schema) up to the current schema so the taskvisor §5 auto-resume loop can re-evaluate env/infra-blocked goals.</rule>
      <rule critical="true">Idempotent: a goal.md that already contains a "## Preconditions" heading is left UNTOUCHED — never write a duplicate section. A fresh project with no existing goal.md files is a no-op.</rule>
      <action>Enumerate existing .tmux-cli/goals/goal-*/goal.md files. For each file that does NOT already contain a "## Preconditions" heading, perform substeps 0b.1–0b.2.</action>
      <substep n="0b.1" title="Derive the goal's preconditions">
        <action critical="true">FIRST, derive the DB signals locally. Step 0b runs BEFORE substep 1.2, so HAS_DATABASE/RUN_TARGET/SERVICES_EXTERNAL are NOT yet in scope — compute them HERE, do NOT forward-reference 1.2. Read docs/architecture/test-environment.md and apply the IDENTICAL rules as substep 1.2: RUN_TARGET=docker if "Run Target"==docker else local; SERVICES_EXTERNAL=true if "DB/services location"==external (default false in docker mode); HAS_DATABASE=true if it defines DB connection fields (host, port, user, password, db_name). If test-environment.md is absent, treat HAS_DATABASE=false.</action>
        <action>Parse env/service gates for the goal from the environment-gate template (.tmux-cli/templates/{{LANG}}-{{FRAMEWORK}}/environment-gate.md, falling back to _base) and the project AGENTS.md runtime/preconditions section.</action>
        <action>Map each gate to a line: "- [env] VAR_NAME — remedy" (required env var) or "- [service] host:port — remedy" (reachable TCP service).</action>
        <action>DB sub-branch — applies to the Gate-0 / environment-gate goal ONLY (goal-001, phase=gate — the goal whose gates the environment-gate template defines), never to any other goal. If HAS_DATABASE AND (RUN_TARGET=local OR SERVICES_EXTERNAL), ALSO append to that goal's derived list the two lines below, verbatim and byte-identical to WS1's fresh Gate-0 emission (substep 1.65):</action>
        <lines>
          <line>- [service] &lt;host&gt;:&lt;port&gt; — start/provision the test DB per docs/architecture/test-environment.md</line>
          <line>- [env] DB_PASSWORD — set DB_PASSWORD from docs/architecture/test-environment.md (do not inline the value)</line>
        </lines>
        <rule critical="true">&lt;host&gt;/&lt;port&gt; MUST be substituted with the literal values from test-environment.md (e.g. 127.0.0.1 and 5432). NEVER emit shell-variable syntax ($DB_HOST/$DB_PORT) and NEVER inline the password — the [env] spec is the bare variable NAME (DB_PASSWORD), which the daemon checks via os.LookupEnv (GM-05). The daemon TCP-dials the literal [service] spec, so shell-variable syntax would never resolve.</rule>
        <action>In docker/compose-internal mode (RUN_TARGET=docker AND NOT SERVICES_EXTERNAL), add NEITHER line — the compose-internal DB is provisioned by Scaffold (goal-002), so no Gate-0 ops precondition is required.</action>
        <action>If no gate applies to this goal, use the single literal line "none".</action>
      </substep>
      <substep n="0b.2" title="Inject the section, preserving all other content">
        <action>Insert a "## Preconditions" section (the derived list, or "none") into goal.md immediately BEFORE the "## Not In Scope" heading; if that heading is absent, append the section at end of file.</action>
        <rule>PRESERVE every other section verbatim — Description, Dependencies, Deliverables, Acceptance Criteria, Validation, Context, Investigation Config, Not In Scope. Only the new "## Preconditions" section is added.</rule>
      </substep>
      <action>Proceed to Step 1.</action>
    </step>

    <step n="0c" title="Resolve runtime command-execution model (RUN_TARGET-aware)">
      <rule critical="true">Runs after Step 0b and BEFORE any goal generation. Records HOW commands will be executed so the rest of generation emits the RIGHT commands — but does NOT hand-prefix them. The taskvisor daemon OWNS command-runtime wrapping: it resolves the project ExecRuntime from test-environment.md and wraps every validate/investigator command into the correct container at dispatch (internal/taskvisor wrapcmd.go / execruntime.go). So generation emits BARE, host-style commands and the daemon makes them runnable. This is the single seam that makes a docker-mode plan executable on a host with no local PHP — and there is exactly ONE source of truth (the daemon), never hand-maintained prefixes.</rule>
      <action>Set RUN_TARGET: read docs/architecture/test-environment.md "Run Target" — docker → RUN_TARGET=docker, else local. (IDENTICAL rule to step 0b / substep 1.2 / step 3.26 — do not drift.)</action>
      <action>Fix the runtime SERVICE NAMES that step 2 task-R must create and the daemon execs into (they MUST agree, since the daemon defaults to these): APP_SVC = the PHP/app compose service, default "app" (prefer a service literally named "app"/"php" in the Published Ports block). NODE_SVC = a dedicated Node/Playwright service, default "e2e", created ONLY when RUN_TARGET=docker AND Playwright is applicable.</action>
      <rule ref="CMD-CONV">See &lt;conventions&gt; block above.</rule>
      <rule ref="HTTP-CONV">See &lt;conventions&gt; block above.</rule>
      <rule ref="NODE-TOOL-CONV">See &lt;conventions&gt; block above.</rule>
      <rule ref="ENSURE-STACK-CONV">See &lt;conventions&gt; block above.</rule>
      <rule ref="HTTP-WAIT-CONV">See &lt;conventions&gt; block above.</rule>
      <action>Proceed to Step 1.</action>
    </step>


    <step n="1" title="Generate Gate 0 goal (goal-001)"><load file=".claude/commands/tmux/task-plan-generate/step-1-gate0.xml">READ step-1-gate0.xml NOW and execute its content as this step.</load></step>
    <step n="2" title="Generate Scaffold goal (goal-002)"><load file=".claude/commands/tmux/task-plan-generate/step-2-scaffold.xml">READ step-2-scaffold.xml NOW and execute its content as this step.</load></step>
    <step n="3.14" title="Generate domain layer goals (one per BC)"><load file=".claude/commands/tmux/task-plan-generate/step-3.14-domain.xml">READ step-3.14-domain.xml NOW and execute its content as this step.</load></step>
    <step n="3.15" title="Per-BC application layer goals"><load file=".claude/commands/tmux/task-plan-generate/step-3.15-application.xml">READ step-3.15-application.xml NOW and execute its content as this step.</load></step>
    <step n="3.16" title="Generate infrastructure goals"><load file=".claude/commands/tmux/task-plan-generate/step-3.16-infrastructure.xml">READ step-3.16-infrastructure.xml NOW and execute its content as this step.</load></step>
    <step n="3.16a" title="Generate Auth Bootstrap goal (conditional, phase=auth-bootstrap)"><load file=".claude/commands/tmux/task-plan-generate/step-3.16a-auth-bootstrap.xml">CONDITIONAL (N_auth_flows >= 1): if the condition holds, READ step-3.16a-auth-bootstrap.xml NOW and execute its content as this step; if not, skip without reading.</load></step>
    <step n="3.17" title="Generate Fixtures goal (single goal, phase=fixtures)"><load file=".claude/commands/tmux/task-plan-generate/step-3.17-fixtures.xml">READ step-3.17-fixtures.xml NOW and execute its content as this step.</load></step>
    <step n="3.17.0" title="Controller Path Resolver (shared)"><load file=".claude/commands/tmux/task-plan-generate/step-3.17.0-controller-path-resolver.xml">READ step-3.17.0-controller-path-resolver.xml NOW and execute its content as this step.</load></step>
    <step n="3.18" title="Generate Controller Action Goals"><load file=".claude/commands/tmux/task-plan-generate/step-3.18-controller-actions.xml">READ step-3.18-controller-actions.xml NOW and execute its content as this step.</load></step>
    <step n="3.19" title="Generate Auth flow goals (phase=auth)"><load file=".claude/commands/tmux/task-plan-generate/step-3.19-auth-flows.xml">READ step-3.19-auth-flows.xml NOW and execute its content as this step.</load></step>
    <step n="3.19a" title="Generate dev-env seed-admin goal (conditional, phase=seed)"><load file=".claude/commands/tmux/task-plan-generate/step-3.19a-seed-admin.xml">CONDITIONAL (seed_default_admin=yes AND N_auth_flows >= 1): if the condition holds, READ step-3.19a-seed-admin.xml NOW and execute its content as this step; if not, skip without reading.</load></step>
    <step n="3.20" title="Generate event listener goals (phase=event_listener)"><load file=".claude/commands/tmux/task-plan-generate/step-3.20-event-listeners.xml">READ step-3.20-event-listeners.xml NOW and execute its content as this step.</load></step>
    <step n="3.21" title="Generate Error Handling goal (single goal, phase=error_handling)"><load file=".claude/commands/tmux/task-plan-generate/step-3.21-error-handling.xml">READ step-3.21-error-handling.xml NOW and execute its content as this step.</load></step>
    <step n="3.22" title="Generate HTTP Middleware goal (conditional, phase=middleware)"><load file=".claude/commands/tmux/task-plan-generate/step-3.22-middleware.xml">CONDITIONAL (middleware selected in cross-cutting.md): if the condition holds, READ step-3.22-middleware.xml NOW and execute its content as this step; if not, skip without reading.</load></step>
    <step n="3.23" title="Generate API documentation goal (phase=api_docs) — CONDITIONAL"><load file=".claude/commands/tmux/task-plan-generate/step-3.23-api-docs.xml">CONDITIONAL (OpenAPI/nelmio selected in cross-cutting.md): if the condition holds, READ step-3.23-api-docs.xml NOW and execute its content as this step; if not, skip without reading.</load></step>
    <step n="3.24" title="Generate Messenger transport goal (conditional, phase=messenger)"><load file=".claude/commands/tmux/task-plan-generate/step-3.24-messenger.xml">CONDITIONAL (async/Messenger selected in cross-cutting.md): if the condition holds, READ step-3.24-messenger.xml NOW and execute its content as this step; if not, skip without reading.</load></step>
    <step n="3.25" title="Generate Health Check goal (single goal, phase=health_check)"><load file=".claude/commands/tmux/task-plan-generate/step-3.25-health-check.xml">READ step-3.25-health-check.xml NOW and execute its content as this step.</load></step>
    <step n="3.26" title="Generate Docker/deployment goal (conditional, phase=docker)"><load file=".claude/commands/tmux/task-plan-generate/step-3.26-docker.xml">CONDITIONAL (Docker/container/deployment ADR exists): if the condition holds, READ step-3.26-docker.xml NOW and execute its content as this step; if not, skip without reading.</load></step>
    <step n="3.27" title="Generate CI/CD pipeline goal (conditional, phase=cicd)"><load file=".claude/commands/tmux/task-plan-generate/step-3.27-cicd.xml">CONDITIONAL (CI/CD platform selected in cross-cutting.md): if the condition holds, READ step-3.27-cicd.xml NOW and execute its content as this step; if not, skip without reading.</load></step>
    <step n="3.28" title="Generate Makefile / DX goal (single goal, phase=dx)"><load file=".claude/commands/tmux/task-plan-generate/step-3.28-dx.xml">READ step-3.28-dx.xml NOW and execute its content as this step.</load></step>
    <step n="3.29" title="Generate Final Gate goals (goal-T+3..T+5)"><load file=".claude/commands/tmux/task-plan-generate/step-3.29-final-gates.xml">READ step-3.29-final-gates.xml NOW and execute its content as this step.</load></step>

    <step n="4" title="Post-generation ordering verification">
      <substep n="4.1" title="Load generated goals">
        <action>Read goals.yaml from disk. Extract ordered list of all goals with their: goal ID, phase, depends_on array, BC assignment (if any).</action>
        <action>Build GOAL_SEQUENCE — an ordered array of {id, phase, depends_on, bc} objects in goals.yaml file order.</action>
      </substep>

      <substep n="4.2" title="Validate strict phase ordering (G-04)">
        <action>Define PHASE_ORDER: gate=0, scaffold=1, domain=2, application=3, infrastructure=4, fixtures=5, error_handling=6, auth=7, action=8, event_listener=9. Cross-cutting phases (middleware, api_docs, messenger, health_check, docker, cicd, dx) share rank=10 and are interchangeable among themselves. final_gate=11.</action>
        <action>Walk GOAL_SEQUENCE. For each goal, verify its phase rank is >= the previous goal's phase rank (equal rank is allowed for same-phase goals and cross-cutting phases).</action>
        <check condition="any goal has phase rank LOWER than the preceding goal (excluding cross-cutting interchangeability)">
          <action>Print error: "G-04 VIOLATION: {goal_id} (phase={phase}, rank={rank}) appears after {prev_goal_id} (phase={prev_phase}, rank={prev_rank}) — phase ordering broken."</action>
          <action>ABORT.</action>
        </check>
      </substep>

      <substep n="4.3" title="Validate depends_on acyclicity (G-15)">
        <action>For each goal in GOAL_SEQUENCE, verify that every ID in its depends_on array refers to a goal with a LOWER sequence index.</action>
        <action>Build adjacency list from depends_on. Run cycle detection (DFS with visited/in-stack markers).</action>
        <check condition="any goal depends on a goal with higher or equal sequence index, OR cycle detected">
          <action>Print error: "G-15 VIOLATION: circular dependency detected — {goal_id} depends on {dep_id} which appears at or after it in the sequence."</action>
          <action>ABORT.</action>
        </check>
      </substep>

      <substep n="4.4" title="Validate per-BC ordering (G-04)">
        <action>Group goals by BC assignment. For each BC, collect goals with phases domain, application, infrastructure.</action>
        <action>Verify within each BC: domain goal appears before application goal, application goal appears before infrastructure goal.</action>
        <check condition="any BC has application before domain, or infrastructure before application">
          <action>Print error: "G-04 VIOLATION: BC '{bc_name}' has {phase_a} goal ({goal_id_a}) before {phase_b} goal ({goal_id_b}) — must be domain → application → infrastructure."</action>
          <action>ABORT.</action>
        </check>
      </substep>

      <substep n="4.5" title="Validate controller actions after fixtures (G-04b)">
        <action>Find the fixtures goal (phase=fixtures) sequence index. Find all action goals (phase=action) sequence indices.</action>
        <action>Verify every action goal has a sequence index higher than the fixtures goal.</action>
        <action>Additionally verify every action goal's depends_on includes the fixtures goal ID.</action>
        <check condition="any action goal appears before fixtures or does not depend on fixtures">
          <action>Print error: "G-04b VIOLATION: action goal {goal_id} (index={idx}) appears before or does not depend on fixtures goal {fixtures_id} (index={fixtures_idx})."</action>
          <action>ABORT.</action>
        </check>
      </substep>

      <substep n="4.6" title="Report success">
        <action>Print: "Ordering verification passed: all {N} goals satisfy G-04 (phase ordering), G-04b (actions after fixtures), G-15 (acyclic dependencies)."</action>
      </substep>
    </step>

    <step n="5" title="Escalation bounce — turn an escalation need into a sequenced prerequisite (conditional, phase=generation)">
      <objective>When generation is re-dispatched for a SINGLE bounced goal carrying an executor escalation (a missing out-of-scope prerequisite), create that prerequisite as a real early-phase goal and wire the bounced goal to wait on it. This is the runtime backstop for the rare prerequisite that the initial plan (Steps 0–4) did not anticipate — NOT a path the full initial plan ever takes.</objective>

      <substep n="5.1" title="Detect the bounce mode and gate">
        <action>This step runs ONLY when generation was invoked for a single bounced goal in phase=generation (set by the supervisor's bounceToGeneration after an [EXECUTE:ESCALATE need=…] was routed as a spec-defect). Otherwise — a full initial plan from docs/architecture/* — SKIP this entire step.</action>
        <action>Bind BOUNCED_GOAL_ID = the bounced goal's ID (the goal the supervisor re-dispatched generation for).</action>
        <check condition="not a single-goal phase=generation bounce">
          <action>Print: "Not an escalation bounce — skipping Step 5."</action>
          <action>SKIP to end of flow.</action>
        </check>
      </substep>

      <substep n="5.2" title="Read the escalation need from the newest correction">
        <action>List .tmux-cli/goals/&lt;BOUNCED_GOAL_ID&gt;/corrections/cycle-*.md and pick the NEWEST by cycle number (highest N).</action>
        <action>Read it and extract the escalation `need` line (the concrete missing prerequisite the executor escalated). Bind NEED = that text.</action>
        <check condition="no corrections/cycle-*.md exists OR no need line found">
          <action>Print diagnostic: "Escalation bounce for &lt;BOUNCED_GOAL_ID&gt; but no escalation need found in corrections/cycle-*.md — cannot synthesize a prerequisite." and STOP (do NOT loop; let the SpecRetries drain / human halt take over).</action>
        </check>
      </substep>

      <substep n="5.3" title="Resolve the scaffold anchor">
        <action>Read goals.yaml from disk. Find the goal with phase=scaffold — bind SCAFFOLD_ANCHOR = its ID. The prerequisite depends ONLY on the scaffold anchor (the repo skeleton), NEVER on BOUNCED_GOAL_ID (that would create a cycle).</action>
      </substep>

      <substep n="5.4" title="Derive the prerequisite config from the need">
        <action>Derive PREREQ_DESCRIPTION (≤120 chars; MaxGoalDescriptionLength invariant), PREREQ_PHASE, PREREQ_VALIDATE (commands proving the prerequisite is satisfied), and PREREQ_INVESTIGATION_CONFIG (2–4 investigators; types from the Reference Table) from NEED.</action>
        <rule>PREREQ_PHASE: if NEED concerns authentication / JWT / identity / security config / User entity → phase=auth-bootstrap (reuse the 3.16a auth-bootstrap shape: security.yaml + User entity + JWT keypair as applicable). Otherwise → an early gate/infra prerequisite: phase=gate for a build/config/tooling prerequisite, or phase=infrastructure when the need is a real infra deliverable (an "infra-bootstrap").</rule>
        <rule>The prerequisite is a STANDALONE early-phase goal — it must not re-declare anything the bounced goal owns; it provides only what NEED says is missing.</rule>
      </substep>

      <substep n="5.5" title="Create the prerequisite goal via goal-create">
        <action>Call goal-create MCP tool:</action>
        <params>
          <param name="description">PREREQ_DESCRIPTION (≤120 chars)</param>
          <param name="validate">PREREQ_VALIDATE</param>
          <param name="phase">PREREQ_PHASE</param>
          <param name="investigation_config">PREREQ_INVESTIGATION_CONFIG</param>
          <param name="depends_on">[SCAFFOLD_ANCHOR]</param>
          <param name="max_retries">3</param>
        </params>
        <rule>depends_on=[SCAFFOLD_ANCHOR] ONLY — NEVER [BOUNCED_GOAL_ID] (a cycle; goal-add-prerequisite would reject it anyway).</rule>
        <action>Bind NEW_PREREQ_ID = the returned goal ID.</action>
        <check condition="goal-create returns error">
          <action>Print the error with full context and STOP.</action>
        </check>
      </substep>

      <substep n="5.6" title="Wire the bounced goal to the new prerequisite via goal-add-prerequisite">
        <action>Call goal-add-prerequisite MCP tool with goal_id=BOUNCED_GOAL_ID, prerequisite_id=NEW_PREREQ_ID. This appends NEW_PREREQ_ID to the bounced goal's depends_on (append order is harmless — NextPendingGoal gates on DependsOnSatisfied, so the daemon runs NEW_PREREQ_ID first) and increments the bounced goal's escalation_count.</action>
        <check condition="goal-add-prerequisite returns an escalation-cap error">
          <action>Print diagnostic: "Escalation cap reached for &lt;BOUNCED_GOAL_ID&gt; — refusing to chain another prerequisite. Halting; let SpecRetries drain / a human intervene." and STOP. Do NOT loop or retry.</action>
        </check>
        <check condition="goal-add-prerequisite succeeds">
          <action>Print: "Escalation resolved: created &lt;NEW_PREREQ_ID&gt; (phase=&lt;PREREQ_PHASE&gt;) and wired &lt;BOUNCED_GOAL_ID&gt; to depend on it."</action>
        </check>
      </substep>
    </step>

    <step n="6" title="Handoff to planning">
      <action>Print: "Generation complete. Run /tmux:plan — its blind audit gate (step 11a) audits the finalized plan via a serial native sub-agent before handing off to /tmux:supervisor. With require_plan_approval enabled, execution stays blocked until plan-approval.md records ≥90% with zero open SEV-1/SEV-2."</action>
    </step>


    <!-- ================================================================
         Steps 7+ are added by subsequent tasks.
         To add a new step: create a new shard file in task-plan-generate/
         (step-N-slug.xml) and add a stub with a load directive here,
         BEFORE the closing flow tag.
         ================================================================ -->
  </flow>

  <execution-rules>
    <rule>goal-create MCP: single call per goal with fully validated parameters — never batch or retry without re-validation</rule>
    <rule>All discovery data comes from docs/architecture/* files on disk (G-16) — never from conversation context or memory</rule>
    <rule>Discovery output files are read-only — never modify them during generation</rule>
    <rule>Template resolution uses two-tier lookup: overlay directory first, then _base fallback — never hardcode template content</rule>
    <rule>Validate ALL consistency rules before reporting errors — collect every error, never stop at the first</rule>
    <rule>Goal descriptions max 120 chars — detailed criteria belong in acceptance and validate arrays</rule>
    <rule>depends_on IDs dynamically read from goals.yaml after each goal-create — never hardcode goal IDs</rule>
    <rule critical="true">validate + acceptance on EVERY goal-create: per the &lt;validate-acceptance-mandate&gt; in the &lt;conventions&gt; block, every goal-creation call (MCP goal-create or `taskvisor goal add`) MUST pass >=1 concrete project-runnable validate command (resolved against the detected stack — never prose-only) and >=1 acceptance criterion as STRUCTURED params. The daemon reads only the structured fields; an empty validate triggers the repair fallback's wrong default investigators.</rule>
    <rule>scope on EVERY goal-create: pass a `scope` array of path globs derived from the goal's Deliverables file paths, per the &lt;scope-derivation&gt; rule in the &lt;conventions&gt; block. A single-BC goal emits its BC-scoped dir glob(s) (e.g. ["src/{BC}/Application/**"]); a repo-wide / skeleton / final-gate goal OMITS scope. CONSERVATIVE: overlap OR omitted/unknown scope ⇒ the daemon serializes (never co-schedules) — so omission is always safe, and an explicit author `scope:` overrides derivation. The runtime reads ONLY the persisted scope, never goal.md.</rule>
  </execution-rules>
  <llm final="true">
    <critical-rules>
      * Step 0 is a blocking validation gate — never generate goals if validation fails
      * All discovery data comes from docs/architecture/* files on disk (G-16), never from conversation context
      * Discovery output files are read-only — never modify them during generation
      * Collect ALL validation errors before reporting — never stop at first error
      * Single-BC projects skip context-map.md check (D-27)
      * Step 1 (Gate 0) creates goal-001 with phase=gate — 2-4 investigators, max_retries=5, no dev-deps
      * Gate 0 checks come from environment-gate.md templates (overlay then base), never hardcoded (E-10)
      * DB credentials referenced via docs/architecture/test-environment.md only — never inlined (GM-05)
      * Step 2 (Scaffold) creates goal-002 with phase=scaffold, depends_on=[goal-001] — 4 investigators, 4 fan-out tasks (task-3 conditional on HAS_DATABASE; + task-R when RUN_TARGET=docker), max_retries=3
      * Scaffold reads from templates (php-symfony overlay → _base fallback) and docs/architecture/* — never hardcoded (G-16)
      * Deptrac {BC}DomainAndShare composite layer uses previo2 bool collector pattern from php-symfony/bounded-contexts.md
      * Step 3.14 (Domain) creates one goal per BC with phase=domain, depends_on=[goal-002], 3-4 investigators, fan-out by aggregate count (&gt;1 → multi-task with task-0 shared + task-1..N per aggregate), max_retries=3
      * Domain goals: PD-01..PD-20 acceptance criteria, private constructors (PD-01), named factories (PD-02), final VOs with equals() (PD-03..PD-05), past-tense events (PD-06), collect-only DomainEventTrait (PD-17)
      * Zero Infrastructure/Application imports in Domain namespace (PD-09), no Doctrine annotations (PD-13), cross-BC refs via ID VOs only (PD-15)
      * ACL interfaces in consuming BC's Domain/ACL/ (PD-16), Share types in src/Share/ not duplicated (PD-18, PD-19)
      * Share type ownership: first BC processed claims DomainEventTrait + base DomainException; subsequent BCs reference but don't regenerate
      * File-disjoint rule enforced on multi-task fan-out — shared files (DomainEventTrait, base exception, Share types) go into task-0 prerequisite
      * Step 3.15 (Application) creates one goal per BC with phase=application, depends_on=own BC's domain goal ID (dynamically read from goals.yaml), 3 investigators, single-task fan-out (multi-task only if &gt;6 handlers), max_retries=3
      * Application goals: PA-01..PA-12 acceptance criteria, one handler per use case (PA-01), port-only injection (PA-02), zero infra imports (PA-03/PA-04), command returns void/scalar (PA-06), query returns DTO (PA-07)
      * Application layer does NOT dispatch domain events — flush-then-dispatch is infrastructure's job
      * Read model interfaces live in Application/ReadModel/, not Domain (PD-08)
      * Step 3.16 (Infrastructure) creates one goal per BC with phase=infrastructure, depends_on=own BC's application goal ID, 3-4 investigators, fan-out by entity count (&gt;3 → multi-task), max_retries=3
      * Infrastructure goals: no annotations on domain objects (PI-03), flush-then-dispatch in write repos (PI-06), real DB in integration tests (PI-11), migrations generated not hand-written (PI-10)
      * ACL adapters (PI-16) and custom DBAL types (PI-08) are conditional — included only when cross-BC deps or compound VOs exist
      * Step 3.16a (Auth Bootstrap) is CONDITIONAL — emitted ONLY when N_auth_flows >= 1 (skip entirely on 0). Single goal, phase=auth-bootstrap, depends_on=[SCAFFOLD_GOAL_ID], 3 investigators, max_retries=3. OWNS config/packages/security.yaml (firewall/provider/authenticator) + User entity with password hashing + (when uses_jwt) lexik/jwt-authentication-bundle config + bin/console lexik:jwt:generate-keypair. Carries AU-08/AU-09 (relocated from per-flow auth goals) + AB-JWT (conditional on uses_jwt). User entity defaults to src/Share/ if no identity BC exists. Stored as AUTH_BOOTSTRAP_GOAL_ID for steps 3.18 (auth_required actions) and 3.19 (all auth flows).
      * Step 3.17 (Fixtures) creates a single goal with phase=fixtures, depends_on=ALL infra goal IDs (dynamically collected), 3 investigators, single-task fan-out, max_retries=3
      * Fixtures depends_on MUST include EVERY infrastructure goal ID from goals.yaml — never just the last one (G-03)
      * Test credentials reference docs/architecture/test-environment.md only — never hardcoded in fixtures (GM-05, FX-02)
      * Step 3.18 (Controller Actions) creates one goal per non-auth action (G-05), phase=action, depends_on=[own BC infra + fixtures + error handling + all auth goals] + AUTH_BOOTSTRAP_GOAL_ID (only for auth_required actions), 2-3 investigators, 5 deliverables (GM-12), max_retries=3
      * Auth endpoints (## Auth Flows section) are EXCLUDED from controller action goals — handled by auth step 3.19 only
      * PC-01..PC-17 encoded in acceptance; PC-07..PC-14 conditional on Playwright availability
      * Fan-Out paths from api-endpoints.md used directly for deliverable file paths — never derived from conventions
      * Step 3.19 (Auth Flows) creates one goal per auth flow (N_auth_flows), phase=auth, depends_on=[fixtures + error handling + AUTH_BOOTSTRAP_GOAL_ID], 3 investigators, 5 deliverables (security.yaml + User entity NOT declared — provided by auth-bootstrap), max_retries=3
      * Auth flows read from docs/architecture/cross-cutting.md Step 6.2 output — one goal per flow (Register, Login, Logout, Token Refresh, Password Reset)
      * Auth goals carry AU-01..AU-10 (flow-specific) + PC-01..PC-17 (all flows) acceptance criteria
      * AU-08/AU-09 (security bundle, password hashing) are OWNED by the auth-bootstrap goal (3.16a), NOT per-flow auth goals; per-flow goals keep AU-07/AU-10 + flow-specific AU-01..AU-06 and depend on AUTH_BOOTSTRAP_GOAL_ID. AU-05/AU-06 (role access) tested within Login/Register
      * Auth goal IDs stored as AUTH_GOAL_IDS — all subsequent action goals MUST depend on them
      * Never double-count auth endpoints in per-BC N_actions — auth counted only in N_auth_flows
      * Step 3.19a (Seed Default Admin) is CONDITIONAL — emitted ONLY when seed_default_admin=yes in test-environment.md `## Bootstrap / Seed Default Admin` AND N_auth_flows &gt;= 1 (skip silently when not requested; skip + warn when 0 auth flows). Single goal, phase=seed, depends_on=[auth-bootstrap goal; FALLBACK first phase=auth/Register goal], max_retries=2, acceptance SA-01..SA-06, 2 investigators (command-run + no-inlined-secret file-check). Validate runs `bin/console app:seed-admin --env=dev` (NEVER --env=test) and asserts the admin row exists. Credentials referenced by env-var NAME only (admin_identifier_env / admin_password_env) — never inlined (GM-05); never folded into the --env=test fixtures goal; never seeds prod.
      * Step 3.22 (HTTP Middleware) is CONDITIONAL — skip entirely if docs/architecture/cross-cutting.md has no middleware selected. If middleware selected: single goal, phase=middleware, depends_on=[fixtures goal ID], 3 investigators, max_retries=3
      * Middleware criteria MW-01 (CORS), MW-02 (logging), MW-03 (rate limiting) are each conditional on that feature being selected. MW-04 (kernel registration order) is always included.
      * Middleware files live in src/Share/Infrastructure/Http/Middleware/ (cross-cutting, not per-BC)
      * Step 3.20 (Event Listeners) creates one goal per event listener, phase=event_listener, depends_on=[own BC infra + fixtures] (cross-BC also depends on source BC infra), 2-3 investigators, max_retries=3
      * Event listener goals use EV-01..EV-13 acceptance criteria: EV-01..EV-07 always, EV-08/EV-09 conditional on is_cross_bc, EV-10/EV-11/EV-13 always, EV-12 conditional on async transport
      * Event listeners: integration tests only — NO Playwright E2E tests (spec lines 329-332). Action E2E tests assert HTTP response + direct DB state, not event handler side effects.
      * Cross-BC listeners: Published Language DTO in src/Share/Event/, ACL adapter in consuming BC's Infrastructure/ACL/, handler in Infrastructure/Adapter/ — imports only own BC + Share namespaces
      * Intra-BC listeners: handler in src/{BC}/Infrastructure/EventListener/, no ACL needed, event class from own BC's Domain/Event/
      * Event dispatch chain: aggregate collects via DomainEventTrait (PD-17) → infra repo dispatches after flush (PI-06) → Messenger routes to handler (EV-07) → handler executes side effect
      * Event listener goals NEVER duplicate criteria already covered by domain goals (PD-06/PD-17 event naming and collection) or infra goals (PI-06 flush-then-dispatch) — event listener goals test the handler/subscription side only
      * Step 3.21 (Error Handling) creates a single UNCONDITIONAL goal with phase=error_handling, depends_on=[fixtures goal ID], 3 investigators (implementation-check, quality-gate, test-execution), single-task fan-out, max_retries=3. Records ERROR_HANDLING_GOAL_ID for steps 3.18/3.19. All 8 EH-01..EH-08 criteria are unconditional. Error handling files live in src/Share/Infrastructure/ErrorHandling/ (cross-cutting, not per-BC).
      * Step 3.23 (API Documentation) is CONDITIONAL — skip entirely if docs/architecture/cross-cutting.md has no OpenAPI/nelmio selected. If selected: single goal, phase=api_docs, depends_on=ALL action + auth goal IDs (dynamically resolved), AD-01..AD-04 criteria, 3 investigators, max_retries=3. AUTH_GOAL_IDS may be empty (valid); ACTION_GOAL_IDS must not be empty.
      * Step 3.24 (Messenger Transport) is CONDITIONAL — skip entirely if docs/architecture/cross-cutting.md has no async/Messenger selection. If selected: single goal (cross-cutting, not per-BC), phase=messenger, depends_on=ALL event listener goal IDs (dynamically resolved from goals.yaml phase=event_listener), MT-01..MT-05 criteria, 2 investigators (config check + consumer test), max_retries=3. Transport DSN never hardcoded — references test-environment.md and cross-cutting.md ADR choice (GM-05). Validate commands use --limit=1 --time-limit=5 for CI-safe consumer exit.
      * Step 3.25 (Health Check) creates a single UNCONDITIONAL goal with phase=health_check, depends_on=ALL infrastructure goal IDs (dynamically collected from goals.yaml), HC-01..HC-03 criteria, 2 investigators (endpoint response check, degraded health check), single-task fan-out, max_retries=3. Services list derived from discovery outputs (cross-cutting.md, bounded-contexts.md) — never hardcoded.
      * Step 3.26 (Docker/Deployment) is CONDITIONAL — skip entirely if no ADR in docs/architecture/adrs/ mentions Docker/container/deployment. If selected: single goal, phase=docker, depends_on=ALL previous goal IDs (full goals.yaml scan, not phase-filtered), DK-01..DK-05 criteria, 3 investigators (build check, compose services, app accessibility), max_retries=3. Description 70 chars. Reads services from ADRs + cross-cutting.md + test-environment.md.
      * Step 3.27 (CI/CD Pipeline) is CONDITIONAL — skip entirely if docs/architecture/cross-cutting.md has no CI/CD platform selected. If selected: single goal, phase=cicd, depends_on=ALL previous goal IDs (full goals.yaml scan, not phase-filtered), CI-01..CI-04 criteria, 2 investigators (config validation, pipeline syntax), max_retries=3. CI_PLATFORM detected from cross-cutting.md (GitHub Actions / GitLab CI). CI_CONFIG_PATH derived from platform (.github/workflows/ci.yml or .gitlab-ci.yml).
      * Step 3.28 (Makefile/DX) creates a single UNCONDITIONAL goal with phase=dx, depends_on=ALL non-gate/scaffold goal IDs (dynamically collected from goals.yaml — exclude phase=gate and phase=scaffold), DX-01..DX-04 criteria, 3 investigators (Makefile targets, .env.test file check, lint/fix cycle), single-task fan-out, max_retries=3. .env.test variables reference docs/architecture/test-environment.md only — never hardcoded (GM-05). Not-in-scope excludes CI/CD pipeline config, Docker targets, and production Makefile targets.
      * Step 3.29 (Final Gates) creates exactly 3 UNCONDITIONAL goals with phase=final_gate, depends_on=ALL previous goal IDs (full goals.yaml scan), max_retries=5. Three goals for retry isolation: Deptrac Full (FG-01..FG-07, 2 investigators), E2E Regression (FG-08/FG-09/G-08, 2 investigators), Quality Sweep (FG-10..FG-18, 3 investigators). ALL_GOAL_IDS dynamically collected from goals.yaml — never hardcoded. G-08 compliance: last 3 goals in goals.yaml must be these final gates. FG-01..FG-18 all covered with no gaps across the 3 goals.
      * Investigation Config structure (GM-08/GM-09): Every goal.md Investigation Config section MUST have 2-4 investigators. Each investigator has: type (from Investigation Types Reference Table at spec lines 955-979), paths (file paths to check), commands (shell commands), pass/fail criteria. Conditional investigators include a condition field. Never hardcode investigator definitions — derive types from the Reference Table.
      * Investigation Config OBJECTIVITY (GM-09b) — convergence-critical: every investigator's pass/fail MUST be decidable from a command's exit status or output alone — an exit code, a numeric threshold (wc -l / grep -c / "must output N"), or a presence check (grep -rl returning ≥1 line). The words "coverage", "covers", "appropriate(ly)", "properly", "sufficient", "demonstrably", "as needed", "where applicable", "present" (as a coverage claim) are BANNED in pass/fail text — they make the verdict a judgment call, which is what stalls the dispatch→validate→correct loop (the validator flip-flops, the implementer gets prose, and the goal burns its code-retry budget re-flagging the same finding). A green test suite is NOT proof a required behavior is tested. When an acceptance criterion asserts that specific behaviors/invariants are TESTED, DECOMPOSE it (next rule); the test-execution investigator's pass is then "suite exits 0 AND non-empty AND every presence-grep returns ≥1", never "suite green with X coverage".
      * Acceptance DECOMPOSITION (GM-09c): never emit a compound "tests cover: A, B, C, ..." criterion. Emit one ATOMIC, individually-greppable criterion per item, and for any invariant/uniqueness/existence rule emit a pair — (a) enforcing code exists in src/ and (b) a test asserting the violation/throw exists in tests/. Mirror every decomposed item into BOTH the acceptance array AND a matching presence-grep in the Investigation Config + VALIDATE array, so a single missing item can never hide behind a green suite.
      * Investigation Config delivery (M3): pass investigators via the `investigation_config` goal-create param — NEVER also write a literal Investigation Config markdown heading into the `context` param or a goal.md template. goal-create renders exactly one Investigation Config section from the param (or the deriveInvestigators fallback when omitted); a duplicate produces a doubled or nested section that breaks investigate.xml parsing.
      * Test-environment reference (GM-05): Every goal.md involving database access, E2E testing, or service connectivity MUST include "See docs/architecture/test-environment.md" in its context section. Credentials, DSNs, and connection parameters are NEVER inlined — always reference test-environment.md.
      * Fan-out hints (G-17): Every goal.md MUST include a Fan-Out Hints section. Single-task goals state "single-task". Multi-task goals list task-0 (shared prerequisites), task-1..N (parallel work units), with explicit depends_on within the goal. Fan-out hints drive tasks.yaml generation — missing hints cause task planning failures.
      * Playwright conditional skip: When HAS_FRONTEND=false (from Step 1.2 line 141): skip PC-07..PC-14 in acceptance arrays (Step 3.18.3), skip E2E investigators in Investigation Config, skip E2E Final Gate goal (Step 3.29.3), and print a warning for each skip. HAS_FRONTEND=true preserves full behavior unchanged.
      * Ordering verification (Step 4): After all goals are generated, Step 4 validates phase ordering (G-04), depends_on acyclicity (G-15), per-BC ordering domain→application→infrastructure (G-04), and controller actions after fixtures (G-04b). Any violation is fatal — ABORT with diagnostic naming the violating goal ID and rule.
      * Step 5 (Escalation bounce) is CONDITIONAL — runs ONLY when generation is re-dispatched for a SINGLE bounced goal in phase=generation (after an [EXECUTE:ESCALATE need=…] was routed as a spec-defect); a full initial plan SKIPS it. Read the bounced goal's newest corrections/cycle-*.md, extract the escalation `need`, derive a prerequisite {description≤120, phase, validate, investigation_config} (auth/JWT/identity → phase=auth-bootstrap; else phase=gate/infrastructure), goal-create it with depends_on=[SCAFFOLD_ANCHOR] (NEVER the bounced goal — that is a cycle), then goal-add-prerequisite(goal_id=BOUNCED_GOAL_ID, prerequisite_id=NEW_PREREQ_ID). Append order is harmless (NextPendingGoal gates on DependsOnSatisfied, so the daemon runs the prerequisite first). On an escalation-cap error, print the diagnostic and STOP — never loop (let SpecRetries drain / a human halt take over). A worker must NEVER call goal-create/goal-add-prerequisite — these are generation-only (they race the daemon).
      * Subsequent tasks insert Steps 6+ above the closing comment in &lt;flow&gt;
    </critical-rules>
  </llm>
</task>
